<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>18430213</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1186/1471-2229-8-44</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2395261</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">18430213</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">1471-2229-8-44</infon><infon key="fpage">44</infon><infon key="lpage">44</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kriechbaumer;given-names:Verena</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Weigang;given-names:Linda</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Fiesselmann;given-names:Andreas</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Letzel;given-names:Thomas</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Frey;given-names:Monika</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Gierl;given-names:Alfons</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Glawischnig;given-names:Erich</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Characterisation of the tryptophan synthase alpha subunit in maize</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract_title_1</infon><offset>67</offset><text>Background</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>78</offset><text>In bacteria, such as Salmonella typhimurium, tryptophan is synthesized from indole-3-glycerole phosphate (IGP) by a tryptophan synthase alphabetabetaalpha heterotetramer. Plants have evolved multiple alpha (TSA) and beta (TSB) homologs, which have probably diverged in biological function and their ability of subunit interaction. There is some evidence for a tryptophan synthase (TS) complex in Arabidopsis. On the other hand maize (Zea mays) expresses the TSA-homologs BX1 and IGL that efficiently cleave IGP, independent of interaction with TSB.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract_title_1</infon><offset>627</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>635</offset><text>In order to clarify, how tryptophan is synthesized in maize, two TSA homologs, hitherto uncharacterized ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike, were functionally analyzed. ZmTSA is localized in plastids, the major site of tryptophan biosynthesis in plants. It catalyzes the tryptophan synthase alpha-reaction (cleavage of IGP), and forms a tryptophan synthase complex with ZmTSB1 in vitro. The catalytic efficiency of the alpha-reaction is strongly enhanced upon complex formation. A 160 kD tryptophan synthase complex was partially purified from maize leaves and ZmTSA was identified as native alpha-subunit of this complex by mass spectrometry. ZmTSAlike, for which no in vitro activity was detected, is localized in the cytosol. ZmTSAlike, BX1, and IGL were not detectable in the native tryptophan synthase complex in leaves.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract_title_1</infon><offset>1445</offset><text>Conclusion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>1456</offset><text>It was demonstrated in vivo and in vitro that maize forms a tryptophan synthase complex and ZmTSA functions as alpha-subunit in this complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>1598</offset><text>Background</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1609</offset><text>Tryptophan is an essential amino acid for human nutrition. In kernels of cereals, e.g. maize (Zea mays), the tryptophan content is low, limiting the nutritional value. Significant effort is made to breed maize lines with enhanced tryptophan content [1,2]. In addition to its function as protein component, plants utilize tryptophan as precursor of a large variety of secondary metabolites like terpenoid indole alkaloids, indole glucosinolates, and indolic phytoalexins (reviewed in: [3,4]). Of special importance is the tryptophan-derived plant hormone indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), which is involved in numerous processes, including embryo development, apical dominance, and tropisms [4,5]. These essential functions of tryptophan emphasize the need to understand its synthesis in plants in more detail.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2413</offset><text>In bacteria, such as Escherichia coli and Salmonella typhimurium, tryptophan is synthesized from indole-3-glycerol phosphate (IGP) by a tryptophan synthase (TS) complex [6]. IGP is cleaved by the TS alpha-subunits (TSA) to indole and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate (alpha-reaction). Then indole is transported via a 30 A intermolecular tunnel to the tryptophan synthase beta-subunits (TSB) that catalyze the condensation of indole and serine (beta-reaction) to tryptophan (Figure 1; for review, see [7,8]). This substrate channelling ensures that indole does not escape from the enzyme complex. The reaction mechanism of this bacterial alphabetabetaalpha complex has been studied in great detail. The alpha- and beta-subunits interact in a highly cooperative manner and regulate each other reciprocally by allosteric interactions. In addition, alternative TSBs that are highly active, independent of interaction with the unique TSA, are expressed in some prokaryotes [9]. In fungi interaction of TSA and TSB is obligate as both functions are present on a single polypeptide [9,10].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>3491</offset><text>General scheme of the tryptophan synthase reaction. Indole, which is formed from IGP by the alpha-subunits is channelled to beta-subunits, which synthesize tryptophan from indole and serine.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3682</offset><text>The picture is more complex in higher plants. The homologs of the bacterial TSA and TSB genes are generally duplicated, e.g. the Arabidopsis thaliana genome contains two putative TSA and four putative TSB genes. Currently the role of these different isoforms is not fully understood. Functional relevance of AtTSA1 (At3g54640) and AtTSB1 (At5g54810) was demonstrated by the facultative tryptophan auxotroph mutants trp3 and trp2, respectively [11,12]. AtTSA1 and AtTSB1 are both localized in the plastid [11,13,14]. Based on immunoaffinity chromatography it was strongly suggested that the two proteins form an active alphabeta complex [14]. However, it is not known whether formation of such complexes is a general phenomenon in plants.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4420</offset><text>Among the cereals most information on TSA and TSB homologs is available for maize: Two highly similar TSB genes (ZmTSB1 and ZmTSB2) have been identified, sharing 96% identity on the mature protein level. ZmTSB1 and ZmTSB2 are functionally redundant active TSB enzymes. While single mutations in either gene do not affect tryptophan synthesis, the double mutant orange pericarp (orp1 = Zmtsb1, orp2 = Zmtsb2) is tryptophan auxotroph [15,16]. Four TSA homologs are present: BX1, IGL, ZmTSAlike [17], and ZmTSA (this work). BX1 is essential for providing indole as precursor of the natural pesticide 2,4-dihydroxy-7-methoxy-2H-1,4-benzoxazin-3(4H)-one (DIMBOA) [18]. The 3-dimensional BX1 structure has been determined and shown to be very similar to the active conformation of bacterial TSAs [19]. Igl transcription is triggered by insect feeding and IGL provides indole as a volatile signal for parasitic wasps [17,20]. BX1 and IGL efficiently cleave IGP to form indole, while the activity of bacterial TSA subunits is dependent on the interaction with a beta-subunit [17,18]. These enzymatic properties, their specific transcriptional regulation, and the lack of growth defects of bx1 and igl mutant plants suggested that additional TSA-homologs are involved in tryptophan biosynthesis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5707</offset><text>In this study we aimed to identify the TSA homolog from maize that is involved in tryptophan biosynthesis. ZmTSA is catalytically active and interaction of ZmTSA with a beta-subunit strongly enhances the catalytic efficiency of the alpha-reaction. A protein purification strategy was applied to obtain direct evidence that angiosperms, similarly to bacteria, form a tryptophan synthase complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>6102</offset><text>Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6110</offset><text>Plant material and growth conditions</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6147</offset><text>The following maize (Zea mays) lines were analyzed: B73 (wildtype), bx1 mutant [21], and the tsb mutants (orp1 +/orp1 orp2) and (orp1 orp2/+ orp2) [15] that were kindly provided by the maize genetic stock center. Seedlings were germinated in a beaker rolled in wet filter paper (603/N, 75 g m-2, Sartorius) at 28 C in the dark and after three days the seedlings were transferred to soil and incubated in a Heraeus HPS 2000 growth chamber (light: 100 mumol m-2 s-1; 16 h/d).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6621</offset><text>Identification of ZmTSA and heterologous expression of standard proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6694</offset><text>For isolation of cDNAs a library prepared from 12 day old seedlings, line bx1 [21] was used [17]. A ZmTSAlike cDNA clone was isolated based on the genomic sequence [17] and confirmed to be full-length by RACE. The ZmTSA cDNA was cloned [GenBank:EU334442] based on the EST AY107255 (gene bank) and the EST-TUG Zmtuc03-08-11.4557 (maize genomic database) and confirmed to be full-length based on the genomic sequence. ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike were analyzed for plastid targeting sequences using the programs &quot;TargetP&quot; and &quot;iPSORT&quot; [22,23].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7227</offset><text>BX1 and IGL expression and purification have been described previously [17,18]. For heterologous expression of ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike, an NdeI/BglII-fragment, for ZmTSB1 expression an NdeI/BamHI-fragment of the coding sequence excluding plastid-targeting sequences was amplified by PCR. The following primers were used: ZmTSA: GCATATGCCGCGCAGCATCTCCG, TCTTACGCTCTTTGCTAACGAAAATGG; ZmTSAlike: CGCATATGGCCAACGGCGGCG, GGGAGTGAGATCTGCTCACGGC; ZmTSB1: CATATGGCGGCCTCCCCCGCTGCCG, CTCGGATCCAGCCCTCCTCTCCGGTG. The coding sequences were cloned into pET28a His-tag vector, heterologously expressed, and purified under native conditions by His-tag affinity purification via Ni-NTA agarose according to the manufacturers' suggestions (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7973</offset><text>For the detection of TSA/TSB complex formation in vitro, size exclusion chromatography (HiLoad 16/60 Superdex 200 prep grade, Amersham Biosciences, Little Chalfont, UK) was performed using 100 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 100 mM KCl at 0.5 ml min-1 and 20 C. The column was calibrated using the protein standards cytochrome c (12.4 kD), carbonic anhydrase (29 kD), bovine albumin (66 kD), alcohol dehydrogenase (150 kD), and beta-amylase (200 kD).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>8413</offset><text>Transcription analysis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8436</offset><text>For detection of ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike expression total RNA was isolated from the wildtype line B73 and quantitative real time PCR was carried out using the LightCycler/Syb -Green dye system (Roche, Mannheim, Germany) with the following primer pairs: ZmTSA: CACTGCTGGAGACCCTGACT, GGTTCATGGCAATGCGGCCT; ZmTSAlike: CCACAAAGGCAGCGCTCGGAGGTG, GCCTCGCTCCTCAGCAACGTCGTCT; GAPDH C: GCTAGCTGCACCACAAACTGCCT, TAGCCCCACTCGTTGTCGTACCA.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8859</offset><text>Tissues analyzed are the following: leaf from 12 d old plants (12 d leaf), 12 d leaf methyl jasmonate treated, 12 d leaf elicitor treated [20], 4 d shoot dark grown, 6 d shoot dark grown, 6 d shoot light grown, 3 week root, 10 week crown root, 8 week stem, 10 week leaf, husk, silk, cob, tassel, kernel 1 week after pollination (wap), kernel 3 wap.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>9208</offset><text>Tryptophan synthase activity assays</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9244</offset><text>Plant protein fractions (200 mug) or purified recombinant enzyme (2 mug) were incubated 3 h for plant protein, 5 min for recombinant proteins, respectively, at 30 C, in 80 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 8.2 containing the following substrates: alpha-reaction: 100 muM IGP [24]; beta-reaction: 50 muM indole, 60 mM L-serine, 50 muM pyridoxal phosphate; alphabeta-reaction: 100 muM IGP, 60 mM L-serine, 50 muM pyridoxal phosphate, concentration ranges were analyzed for determination of kinetic parameters.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9752</offset><text>The products indole and tryptophan were quantified by HPLC (RP-column: LiChroCART 125-4, RP-18, 5 mum; Merck, West Point, PA) using diode array (PDA-100, Dionex, Idstein, Germany) and fluorescence detection (RF-10AXL, Shimadzu, Duisburg, Germany; excitation: 285 nm, emission: 360 nm). The mobile phase was delivered with a flow rate of 1 ml min-1 with an initial mixture of 15% (v/v) MeOH in 0.3% (v/v) HCOOH followed by a 15 min linear gradient to 100% MeOH.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>10213</offset><text>Plant protein purification</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10240</offset><text>Leaf tissue (50 g) was homogenized in liquid nitrogen and extracted in 5 ml 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, containing 10 mM EDTA, 5 mM DTE, 1 mM PMSF, and 10% Polyclar AT (Serva, Heidelberg, Germany) and centrifuged 20 min at 10.000 g (4 C). The supernatant was subjected to an anion exchange column (MonoQ HR 5/5, Amersham) equilibrated with 100 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 10 mM EDTA, 5 mM DTE, 100 mM NaCl at 4 C. The column was then washed with 10 Vol of the same buffer and eluted with 100 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0 containing 10 mM EDTA, 5 mM DTE, and 1 M NaCl in a 20 Vol linear gradient. Fractions around 450 mM NaCl showed TS activity and were subjected (0.5 ml min-1, 20 C) to gel permeation chromatography (HiLoad 16/60 Superdex 200 prep grade, Amersham, equilibrated with 100 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0 including 100 mM KCl). The column was eluted with the same buffer (180 ml, 0.5 ml min-1). 1 ml fractions were collected and tested for alpha- and beta-activity. The 54 to 56 ml fractions were precipitated by addition of 10% TCA, redissolved in 10 mul 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 6.8, 20 mM DTT, 2% (w/v) SDS, 0.01% (w/v) bromphenol blue, 10% (w/v) glycerol, and subjected to SDS-PAGE.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11404</offset><text>After fixation for &gt; 2 h with a 40% (v/v) MeOH/10% (v/v) HOAc solution and washing in water for 2 x 10 min the gels were stained over night with Coomassie dye (0.08% (w/v) Coomassie Brilliant Blue G250, 1.6% (w/v) ortho-phosphoric acid, 8% (w/v) (NH4)2SO4, 20% (v/v) MeOH) and destained in 1% (v/v) HOAc [25]. The protein bands between 25 and 60 kD were cut out and the gel piece was further destained in a thermo mixer with water (2 x 30 min 37 C), 200 mM NH4HCO3, pH 7.8 (2 x 30 min 37 C), and 50% acetonitrile (ACN) (2 x 5 min 37 C). The gel slice was shrunk in 100% ACN, the liquid supernatant was removed and the gel dried in a SpeedVac for 5 min.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>12057</offset><text>Identification of tryptophan synthase protein components: sample preparation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12134</offset><text>Tryptic digestion: 100 mul trypsin solution (200 ng mul-1, Promega) were directly pipetted on the gel piece, incubated for 10 min on ice to allow the trypsin to move into the gel and then covered with 500 mul 25 mM NH4HCO3 followed by 16 h incubation at 37 C. Digestion was stopped by adding 50 mul of 10% trifluoroacetic acid and the supernatant was transferred to a new tube. Peptides were extracted by consecutive basic and acid extraction. Basic extraction: 50 mul 40 mM NH4HCO3 were added to the gel, shaken for 30 min at 37 C, and the supernatant transferred to a new tube. The same incubation followed after addition of 50 mul ACN. Both steps were repeated and the supernatants pooled. Acid extraction: The gel piece was extracted twice in 50 mul 5% (v/v) HCOOH for 30 min. The gel piece was shrunk twice in 50 mul ACN. All the collected supernatants were pooled, dried in a SpeedVac and dissolved in 100 mul 20 mM ammonium acetate buffer, pH 7.4, 10% (v/v) ACN, 5 mM DTT.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13114</offset><text>A further step of digestion was performed in solution (10 mul trypsin solution, 200 ng mul-1, 8 h, 37 C) to apply a maximum amount of hydrolyzed peptides without miscleavage. Latter is important for a reproducible identification of qualifying peptides.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13367</offset><text>Liquid chromatography - mass spectrometry (LC-MS)</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13417</offset><text>An Agilent micro HPLC system (series 1100, Waldbronn, Germany) consisting of a quaternary capillary pump (G1376A), a degasser unit (G1379A), an auto sampler (G1377A), and a column in a thermostat set to 40 C (G1316A) was used in combination with a single time-of-flight mass spectrometer (LC/MSD TOF, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, USA). The chromatographic separation was performed with a Zorbax SB C18 column (150 x 0.5 mm i.d.; 5 mum, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, USA) by 8 mul sample injections. Prior to injection, the trypsinized protein samples were mixed with 200 mul 20 mM NH4Ac, 10% ACN (v/v), 5 mM DTT, pH 7.4, sonified for 15 min, filtrated via HV filter, and stored in an autosampler vial. The HPLC separation flow rate was 50 mul min-1. At the beginning of each chromatographic run, the composition of the mobile phase was kept at 95% 20 mM NH4Ac/5% ACN (v/v), following a gradient to 20% 20 mM NH4Ac/80% ACN (v/v) within 5 min and this final value was held for 15 min.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14411</offset><text>MS measurements were performed in positive ionization mode with the mass spectrometer equipped by an ESI source. The applied MS parameter were as follows: 350 C drying gas temperature, 420 Lh-1 drying gas flow rate, 20 psig nebulizer gas pressure, 4000 V capillary voltage, 60 V skimmer voltage and 215 V fragmentor voltage. The mass-range was set to 150 - 3200 m/z and data acquisition was 0.88 cycles/sec. The drying gas nitrogen was supplied by a nitrogen generator (nitrogen purity &gt;= 99.5%, Domnick Hunter, Willich, Germany). The ChemStation software (Rev. B.01.01, Agilent, Waldbronn, Germany) was used for system control and the Analyst QS software (LC-MS TOF Software, Ver. A.01.00 (B663), June, 2004) for the data acquisition.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>15147</offset><text>Expression of ZmTSA- and ZmTSAlike-GFP-fusion proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15202</offset><text>To construct vectors for expression of GFP-fusion protein [26], the stop codon of the ZmTSA coding sequence was replaced by a BglII restriction site, using the following primers: 5'-CGACTACACCAAATGAAAGAATGGAG-3' (forward), 5'-CTCGAGAGATCTGGCAATGCGGCCTTCAGG-3' (reverse). The full size ZmTSA cDNA fragment, in which the stop codon was eliminated, was then cut from the vector with EcoRI/BglII and cloned into the EcoRI/BamHI sites of the pEZS-NL vector (D. Ehrhardt, Carnegie Institution). The ZmTSA-eGFP chimera was cut with EcoRI, blunted, cut with XbaI, and cloned into the SmaI/XbaI sites of the PvuII-deletion of pPCVE35E plant transformation vector. The same strategy was used for the construction of the ZmTSAlike-eGFP chimeric cDNA, with the primer pair: CAAGCTGGCATACATGGAC/GGTACCAGATCTGGCATAGCAGCCTTCATA.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16016</offset><text>Transfection of maize protoplasts and confocal microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16074</offset><text>Maize LG22 seedlings were grown on an 8 h dark, 20 C/16 h light, 26 C regime for 6 to 8 days and were then transferred to the dark for 3 days. Protoplasts were isolated from the second true leaves essentially as described previously [27,28]. Digestion was performed in 1% (w/v) cellulase R10, 0,5% (w/v) Macerozyme R10 (both from Yakult Honsha), 0.6 M mannitol, 10 mM MES, pH 5.7, 1 mM CaCl2 for 2 h at 28 C on a rotating shaker (40 rpm). After filtration through a 65-mum nylon mesh, the protoplasts were collected by 3 min centrifugation at 200 g, followed by centrifugation at 100 g in floating solution (25% sucrose (w/v), 10 mM MES, 20 mM KCl). Floating protoplasts were washed in 0.6 M mannitol, 4 mM MES, 20 mM KCl and counted. Electroporation was performed with 2.5 x 105 protoplasts and 40 mug of each plasmid in 300 mul 4 mM MES-KOH, pH 5.7, 0.6 M mannitol, 20 mM KCl. Transformed protoplasts were incubated in the dark at 25 C for 20 h in 4 mM MES-KOH, pH 5.7, 0.6 M mannitol, 4 mM KCl.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17072</offset><text>Confocal microscope images were taken using an Olympus FV1000 confocal laser microscope with a 40x water objective. The excitation wavelength for eGFP detection was 488 nm.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>17245</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>17253</offset><text>Isolation of ZmTSA</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17272</offset><text>In maize, four genes encoding TSA homologs are present. Bx1, Igl, and ZmTSAlike have been described previously [17,18]. A search of the GeneBank and maize genomic database (see Availability and requirements section for URL) revealed putative TSA sequences, which do not constitute alleles of Bx1, Igl, or ZmTSAlike. These sequences, partly represented by the Tentative Unique Gene (TUG) Zmtuc03-08-11.4557, correspond to a new gene, now designated ZmTSA. ZmTSA is located on chromosome 7 (contig AC191027, GeneBank). A full-length ZmTSA cDNA clone was isolated [GenBank:EU334442]. Most plant TSAs have divergent N-terminal sequences that have no counterpart in bacteria and represent transit peptides for plastid import. When this variable part is excluded from the analysis, ZmTSA is 63% identical to BX1, 67% to IGL, and 72% to ZmTSAlike on protein level, respectively [for an alignment, see Additional file 1].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18186</offset><text>Expression and subcellular localization</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18226</offset><text>For a further characterization of the closely related genes ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike their transcription levels were determined by RT-PCR in different tissues and developmental stages. ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike transcripts were detected in all 16 tissues analyzed [see Additional file 2] and generally, ZmTSA was the predominant isoform expressed. The average transcript levels relative to GAPDH in these preparations were determined as 1.80 +- 0.93 fg fg-1 for ZmTSA and 0.20 +- 0.15 fg fg-1 for ZmTSAlike. The virtually homogeneous expression of ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike qualifies them as candidates to function in tryptophan biosynthesis in maize. In contrast, Bx1 is predominantly transcribed in seedlings and Igl is specifically induced in response to herbivore attack [17,18,20].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18996</offset><text>There is a number of data suggesting that plant tryptophan biosynthesis is predominantly localized in the plastids [13,29]. ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike were analyzed in silico for putative targeting sequences using &quot;TargetP&quot; and &quot;iPSORT&quot; [22,23]. ZmTSA was predicted to be plastid localized, while ZmTSAlike, 45 amino acids shorter at the N-terminus, was expected to be retained in the cytoplasm.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19385</offset><text>To obtain experimental evidence, plasmids conferring expression of ZmTSA- and ZmTSAlike-GFP fusion proteins were transformed into maize protoplasts. GFP and chlorophyll autofluorescence were analyzed by confocal microscopy (Figure 2). In case of ZmTSA GFP fluorescence coincided with the chlorophyll autofluorescence of the chloroplasts (Figure 2A-C), demonstrating plastidic localization of ZmTSA. In contrast, ZmTSAlike-GFP was localized in the cytosol (Figure 2D-F).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>19855</offset><text>Subcellular localization of ZmTSA and ZmTSAlike fused to eGFP in maize cells. Analysis of maize mesophyll protoplasts transiently expressing ZmTSA::eGFP (A-C) or ZmTSAlike::eGFP (D-F). A, D: GFP fluorescence; B, E: Red chlorophyll autofluorescence in chloroplasts; C, F: Merged images.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>20141</offset><text>ZmTSA has tryptophan synthase alpha activity</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20186</offset><text>We determined the kinetic parameters for the TS alpha-reaction for the two candidates. Purified recombinant ZmTSA was tested for conversion of IGP to indole. A low, but clearly detectable IGP turnover (Kcat = 0.006 s-1) was observed (Table 1). No alpha-activity of recombinant ZmTSAlike was detected in analogous experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>20512</offset><text>Kinetic parameters of Zea mays tryptophan synthase and comparison with characterized homologs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>20607</offset><text>   Reaction Recombinant Enzyme(s) Substrate KM (muM) kcat (s-1) kcat/KM(mM-1 s-1)   alpha ZmTSA IGP 458 +- 94 0.006 +- 0.002 0.013  alpha ZmTSA+ZmTSB1 IGP 52 +- 6 0.019 +- 0.004 0.37  beta ZmTSB1 Indole 24 +- 4 0.29 +- 0.04 12.1  beta ZmTSA+ZmTSB1 Indole 28 +- 6 0.44 +- 0.07 15.7  alphabeta ZmTSA+ZmTSB1 IGP 47 +- 9 0.45 +- 0.06 9.6  alpha ZmTSAlike IGP n. d. n. d. n. d.  alpha ZmTSAlike+ZmTSB1 IGP n. d. n. d. n. d.    alpha BX1 [18] IGP 13 2.8 215  alpha IGL [17] IGP 100 2.3 23    alpha EcTSA 1) IGP 480 0.002 0.004  alpha EcTSA + EcTSB 1) IGP 27 0.2 7.4  alpha StTSA + StTSB 2) IGP 100 0.14 1.4  beta StTSA + StTSB 2) Indole 15 3.6 240  alphabeta StTSA + StTSB 2) IGP 20 3 150</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>21290</offset><text>1) [31], Ec: E. coli.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>21312</offset><text>2) [35], St: S. typhimurium.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>21341</offset><text>n. d.: For ZmTSAlike no IGP turnover was detected.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>21392</offset><text>Formation of a tryptophan synthase complex in vitro</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21444</offset><text>In bacteria alpha activity of the TS complex is two orders of magnitude higher than that of TSA alone. Therefore, ZmTSA was allowed to interact with purified recombinant ZmTSB1 for 1 h at 4 C adding 60 mM serine and 50 muM pyridoxal phosphate. To investigate complex formation with ZmTSB1in vitro, the ZmTSA/ZmTSB1 mixture was subjected to size exclusion chromatography (Figure 3). ZmTSA and ZmTSB1 formed a complex of approximately 160 kD (Figure 3A) that according to SDS-PAGE analysis (data not shown) contained both proteins in a 1:1 stoichiometry. These results are consistent with formation of a ZmTSA2ZmTSB12 heterotetramer. The kinetic parameters of ZmTSA, ZmTSB1, and ZmTSA/ZmTSB1 heteromers were determined (Table 1). Heteromerisation with ZmTSB1 resulted in a 32-fold increase of the catalytic efficiency of ZmTSA.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>22270</offset><text>In vitro complex formation. Combinations of recombinant proteins, 0.5 mg each, were allowed to assemble 1 h at 4 C. An aliquot each was analyzed by size exclusion chromatography and the elution of protein was monitored by absorption at 280 nm. A: ZmTSA + ZmTSB1, the retention volume of the major peak corresponds the size of an alpha2beta2 tetramer. B: ZmTSAlike + ZmTSB1, two peaks corresponding an alpha monomer and a beta2 dimer are observed. C: ZmTSB1 without addition of a TSA homolog; putative beta2 dimers are formed.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22796</offset><text>No interaction of ZmTSB1 with ZmTSAlike, BX1, or IGL was detectable. The native molecular masses of ZmTSAlike, BX1, and IGL were estimated by gel filtration to around 30 kD, indicating that these proteins were monomers in solution (Figure 3B and data not shown). ZmTSB1 apparently formed dimers of approximately 90 kD (Figure 3B,C). No prominent larger complexes were observed. ZmTSAlike remained inactive with IGP as substrate also when the beta-subunit was added to the preparation (Table 1). The experiment was repeated with thrombin digested proteins to exclude lack of complexation due to sterical hindrance caused by the His-tag yielding identical results (data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>23476</offset><text>Tryptophan synthase activity in leaf protein extracts</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23530</offset><text>To investigate, whether alpha2beta2 TS complexes are also formed in vivo, protein extracts of B73 wildtype maize and the mutant lines bx1, Zmtsb1, and Zmtsb2 were separated by size exclusion chromatography. Individual fractions were tested for conversion of IGP to indole + glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate (alpha reaction) and of indole + serine to tryptophan (beta reaction) (Figure 4). In a fraction representing proteins of approx. 160 kD both alpha- and beta-activity was detected (app. KMIGP = 47 +- 7 muM; app. KMindole = 5 +- 2 muM, B73). This fraction was as well capable of the total (alphabeta) TS reaction in all genotypes tested (IGP to tryptophan turnover rates of 96 to 122 pmol mg-1 min-1). beta-Activity was also clearly detected in the fraction of approx. 90 kD proteins, the size of putative beta-dimers. The Zmtsb1 Zmtsb2 (orp1 orp2) double mutant is devoid of beta-activity and shows severe growth defects [15]. Here, the respective single mutants Zmtsb1 (orp1 +/orp1 orp2) and Zmtsb2 (orp1 orp2/+ orp2) were tested and each yielded beta-activity in both the 90 kD and the 160 kD complex fractions (Figure 4D). This indicates that ZmTSB1 and ZmTSB2 are functionally redundant and may both form active beta-dimers as well as active alphabetabetaalpha TS complexes. In extracts from B73 wildtype, as well as Zmtsb1 or Zmtsb2 mutants a second alpha-activity peak was determined in a fraction of approximately 30 kD, corresponding to the monomer size of TSA homologs. In extracts of bx1 mutants this activity was not present, indicating that monomeric alpha-activity in leaves is predominantly due to activity of BX1 enzyme.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>25166</offset><text>Determination of enzymatic activities in leaf extracts fractionized by size exclusion chromatography. Formation of indole from IGP (alpha-reaction, A, B) and of tryptophan from indole + serine (beta-reaction, C, D) was quantified. The wildtype line B73, bx1 mutant (A, C), and tsb1 and tsb2 mutants (B, D) were analyzed.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>25487</offset><text>ZmTSA is a component of the tryptophan synthase complex in maize</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25552</offset><text>To identify constituents of the 160 kD TS complex in planta a mass-spectrometry-based approach was applied. Sequence qualifying peptides, i.e. peptides allowing annotation, were obtained for ZmTSA, ZmTSAlike, BX1, IGL, and ZmTSB1 by the analysis of tryptic digests of recombinant proteins using liquid chromatography with time-of-flight mass spectrometry coupled by electrospray ionisation (LC-ESI-ToF-MS). The resulting detection signals of peptides were compared with theoretically expected tryptic peptide masses [see Additional files 3 and 4]. 46.0% of the total sequence was covered for ZmTSA, 36.5% for ZmTSAlike, 40.4% for ZmTSB1, 50.0% for BX1, and 56.9% for IGL.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26224</offset><text>To identify the active alpha-subunit of the TS complex in maize, TS activity was partially purified from leaf extracts by subsequent ion exchange and size exclusion chromatography. The 160 kD protein fraction was concentrated and separated by SDS-PAGE. Proteins between approx. 25 kD (smaller than TSA size) and 60 kD (larger than TSB size) were cut out of the gel. A tryptic digest of these proteins was analyzed by LC-ESI-ToF-MS and surveyed for peptides sequence qualifying for ZmTSA, ZmTSAlike, BX1, IGL, and ZmTSB1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26745</offset><text>Four peptides characteristic for ZmTSA were present as major peptide signals in this tryptic digest of the 160 kD fraction containing active TS (Table 2, Figure 5). The probability for a specific random dodeca-peptide, such as e.g. identified GTTFEDVISMVK is in the order of approximately 10-15. Therefore, ZmTSA was conclusively identified as component of a maize TS complex. No peptides specific for ZmTSAlike, BX1, or IGL were detected [see Additional file 3]. The peptides ADGTGPLIYLK and DATSEAIR were identified, which could be assigned to either of the highly similar active ZmTSB isoforms. For ZmTSB1 the specific peptide QALNVFR was identified. No ZmTSB2 specific peptide was clearly assigned. However, based on Zmtsb1 mutant analysis (Figure 4) it is very likely that also ZmTSB2 is present in TS complexes in vivo. In summary, ZmTSA and ZmTSB1 were identified by LC-ESI-ToF-MSas constituents of TS complexes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>27665</offset><text>ZmTSA sequence qualifying peptides identified in a tryptic digest of tryptophan synthase partially purified from leaves.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>27786</offset><text>   ret. time (min) m/z charge EIC intensity calc. mass peptide   15.1 371.239 1+ 5.60E+03 370.449 AALP  15.5 687.361 2+ 7.00E+04 1373.480 TLEEAASPEEGLK  15.7 663.860 2+ 5.00E+02 1326.528 GTTFEDVISMVK  18.2 359.151 1+ 1.30E+03 359.440 ALR</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>28024</offset><text>EIC: Extracted ion chromatogram</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>28056</offset><text>Identification of ZmTSA as component of the tryptophan synthase complex. The approach is exemplified by the peptides ALR (A-D, m/z = 359.151) and GTTFEDVISMVK (E-H, m/z = 663.860). These fragments are characteristic for ZmTSA (B, F) and were absent in ZmTSAlike (C, G) and ZmTSB1 (D, H). Both fragments were identified in a trypsin hydrolysate of the active tryptophan synthase fraction (A, E). The peptide and the corresponding 13C/34S isotopic peaks were detected (inserts in A, B, E, F).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>28547</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28558</offset><text>Evidence for physical interaction of tryptophan synthase alpha and beta subunits in plants was provided by immunoaffinity chromatography for Arabidopsis [14] and by size exclusion chromatography for maize (this study). For the identification of the maize tryptophan synthase components in vivo, specific sequence qualifying peptides were assigned by LC-MS. This approach allows the analysis of enzyme complexes that are not sufficiently stable for application of a larger variety of chromatographic separations, necessary for purification to homogeneity. Applying this method, ZmTSA was identified as alpha-subunit of a tryptophan synthase complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29207</offset><text>The apparent molecular weight strongly indicates that in maize tryptophan synthase is functional as alphabetabetaalpha heterotetramer, similar as in bacteria [30,31]. In maize ZmTSA is the principal alpha-subunit of the complex. Catalytic efficiency of ZmTSA was enhanced more than 30-fold by interaction with the beta-subunit (Table 1). Such activating interaction between alpha- and beta-subunit is also well known from bacteria like E. coli (Table 1). In E. coli this activation was mutual, i.e. beta-activity strongly increased upon formation of an alpha2beta2 TS complex [32]. In contrast, no significant activation of the maize beta-subunit by ZmTSA was observed (Table 1). The reason for this difference between the bacterial and plant enzyme is not known.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29971</offset><text>In maize, ancestral TSAs have been recruited for secondary metabolism. The TSA homologs BX1 and IGL catalyze the formation of indole, which functions as DIMBOA precursor or volatile signal [17-19] (Table 1) and BX1 monomer activity was observed in leaf extracts (Figure 4). In addition, TSB dimers that have been observed in leaf extracts (Figure 4) and in vitro (Figure 3), which possibly function in salvage of indole by its conversion to tryptophan. It remains open, whether a mechanism involving BX1 monomer and TSB dimer contributes significantly to the total metabolic flux towards tryptophan. The bx1 mutant and the bx1 igl double mutant (M. Frey, unpublished data) are fully viable; therefore this process is not essential at any stage of development.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30731</offset><text>We propose that, despite the availability of the highly active monomers BX1 and IGL, in maize tryptophan is predominantly synthesized through a tryptophan synthase complex containing ZmTSA and ZmTSB1 or ZmTSB2, respectively. Probably this complex has been retained during evolution for tryptophan synthesis, as it enables substrate channelling and allosteric regulation. Knockout mutants could serve as ultimate proof for ZmTSA being essential. Therefore we have extensively screened public databases as well as the large Pioneer HiBred TUSC collection for Mu-transposon insertion mutants [33] in ZmTSA. However, no insertion alleles were identified. It remains open, whether Zmtsa knockout mutants are lethal.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31442</offset><text>Based on import studies, subcellular fractionation, and target sequence prediction, it is suggested that in plants the biosynthesis of aromatic amino acids is predominantly localized in plastids (for review, see [29]). Consistent with these data ZmTSA contains a chloroplast targeting sequence and ZmTSA::GFP fusion proteins were targeted to the plastid (Figure 2). Interestingly, the TSA homolog ZmTSAlike lacks such a transit peptide and ZmTSAlike::GFP fusion proteins were located in the cytosol (Figure 2). It has been debated whether the biosynthesis of aromatic amino acids is also partially active in the cytoplasm, as e.g. a cytoplasmic isoform of chorismate mutase is expressed in Arabidopsis [34]. As recombinant ZmTSAlike, expressed in E. coli, did not show any alpha-activity it remains unclear, whether ZmTSAlike functions as cytosolic TSA isoform. ZmTSAlike might either require specific conditions and modifications or it has an unknown function in plant metabolism.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>32424</offset><text>Conclusion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32435</offset><text>Four TSA homologs exist in maize. Only one of these isoforms, ZmTSA, is involved in the formation of a tryptophan synthase complex. Based on our data and previous results for Arabidopsis thaliana we propose that a ubiquitous tryptophan synthase complex is responsible for tryptophan formation in angiosperms, like in fungi and bacteria.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>32772</offset><text>Abbreviations</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32786</offset><text>ACN: acetonitrile; bx1: benzoxazinless1; GAPDH: glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; IGL: indole-3-glycerol phosphate lyase; IGP: indole-3-glycerol phosphate; TSA: tryptophan synthase alpha subunit; TSB: tryptophan synthase beta subunit; wap: weeks after pollination.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>33059</offset><text>Availability and requirements</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33089</offset><text>Maize genomic database: </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>33114</offset><text>Authors' contributions</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33137</offset><text>VK designed, conducted, and analyzed the majority of experiments and supported drafting the manuscript. LW carried out the LC-MS analysis. AF analyzed the sub-cellular localisation of proteins. TL designed and supervised the LC-MS analysis and interpretation. MF conducted transcription analysis, supervised localisation studies and cloning, and revised the manuscript. AG conceptualised the project, coordinated the group, and revised the manuscript. EG supervised the project, supported experiment design and analysis, and wrote the draft of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>33743</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">227</infon><infon key="lpage">233</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gibbon;given-names:BC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Larkins;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15797618</infon><infon key="source">Trends Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>33766</offset><text>Molecular genetic approaches to developing quality protein maize</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">525</infon><infon key="lpage">535</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Huang;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Frizzi;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Florida;given-names:CA</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kruger;given-names:DE</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Luethy;given-names:MH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16830184</infon><infon key="source">Plant Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">61</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>33831</offset><text>High lysine and high tryptophan transgenic maize resulting from the reduction of both 19- and 22-kD alpha-zeins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">29</infon><infon key="lpage">66</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Facchini;given-names:PJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11337391</infon><infon key="source">Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">52</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>33943</offset><text>Alkaloid biosynthesis in plants: biochemistry, cell biology, molecular regulation, and metabolic engineering applications.</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">55</infon><infon key="lpage">58</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kriechbaumer;given-names:V;suffix:Glawischnig, E</infon><infon key="source">Journal of Nano &amp; Bio Tech</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">2</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>34066</offset><text>Auxin biosynthesis within the network of tryptophan metabolism</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">249</infon><infon key="lpage">272</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ljung;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hull;given-names:AK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kowalczyk;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Marchant;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Celenza;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Cohen;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Sandberg;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12036253</infon><infon key="source">Plant Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">49</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>34129</offset><text>Biosynthesis, conjugation, catabolism and homeostasis of indole-3-acetic acid in Arabidopsis thaliana</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1161</infon><infon key="lpage">1170</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Crawford;given-names:IP;suffix:Yanofsky, C</infon><infon key="source">Proceedings of the National Acadademy of Science, USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">44</infon><infon key="year">1958</infon><offset>34231</offset><text>On the separation of the tryptophan synthetase of Escherichia coli into two protein components</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">140</infon><infon key="lpage">151</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Miles;given-names:EW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11893063</infon><infon key="source">Chem Rec</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>34326</offset><text>Tryptophan synthase: a multienzyme complex with an intramolecular tunnel</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">127</infon><infon key="lpage">186</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Miles;given-names:EW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">400853</infon><infon key="source">Adv Enzymol Relat Areas Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">49</infon><infon key="year">1979</infon><offset>34399</offset><text>Tryptophan synthase: structure, function, and subunit interaction</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">14111</infon><infon key="lpage">14119</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Leopoldseder;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hettwer;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sterner;given-names:R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17115706</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">45</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>34465</offset><text>Evolution of multi-enzyme complexes: the case of tryptophan synthase</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2941</infon><infon key="lpage">2946</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Matchett;given-names:WH</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:DeMoss;given-names:JA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">123527</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">250</infon><infon key="year">1975</infon><offset>34534</offset><text>The subunit structure of tryptophan synthase from Neurospora crassa</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">345</infon><infon key="lpage">358</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Last;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bissinger;given-names:PH</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Mahoney;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Radwanski;given-names:ER</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Fink;given-names:GR</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1840915</infon><infon key="source">Plant Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>34602</offset><text>Tryptophan mutants in Arabidopsis: the consequences of duplicated tryptophan synthase beta genes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">353</infon><infon key="lpage">361</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Radwanski;given-names:ER</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Barczak;given-names:AJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Last;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9003322</infon><infon key="source">Mol Gen Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">253</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>34699</offset><text>Characterization of tryptophan synthase alpha subunit mutants of Arabidopsis thaliana</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">6081</infon><infon key="lpage">6087</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zhao;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Last;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7890741</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">270</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>34785</offset><text>Immunological characterization and chloroplast localization of the tryptophan biosynthetic enzymes of the flowering plant Arabidopsis thaliana</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">657</infon><infon key="lpage">667</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Radwanski;given-names:ER</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zhao;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Last;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7476868</infon><infon key="source">Mol Gen Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">248</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>34928</offset><text>Arabidopsis thaliana tryptophan synthase alpha: gene cloning, expression, and subunit interaction</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">711</infon><infon key="lpage">719</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wright;given-names:AD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Moehlenkamp;given-names:CA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Perrot;given-names:GH</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Neuffer;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Cone;given-names:KC</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1356534</infon><infon key="source">Plant Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>35026</offset><text>The maize auxotrophic mutant orange pericarp is defective in duplicate genes for tryptophan synthase beta</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">998</infon><infon key="lpage">1000</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wright;given-names:AD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sampson;given-names:MB</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Neuffer;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Michalczuk;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Slovin;given-names:JP</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Cohen;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17731524</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">254</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>35132</offset><text>Indole-3-acetic acid biosynthesis in the mutant maize orange pericarp, a tryptophan auxotroph</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">14801</infon><infon key="lpage">14806</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Frey;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stettner;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Pare;given-names:PW</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Schmelz;given-names:EA</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Tumlinson;given-names:JH</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Gierl;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11106389</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>35226</offset><text>An herbivore elicitor activates the gene for indole emission in maize</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">696</infon><infon key="lpage">699</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Frey;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Chomet;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_10">surname:Simcox;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_11">surname:Gierl;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Glawischnig;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Stettner;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Grun;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Winklmair;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Eisenreich;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Bacher;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Meeley;given-names:RB</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Briggs;given-names:SP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9235894</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>35296</offset><text>Analysis of a chemical plant defense mechanism in grasses</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">608</infon><infon key="lpage">620</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kulik;given-names:V</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hartmann;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Weyand;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Frey;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Gierl;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Niks;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Dunn;given-names:MF</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Schlichting;given-names:I</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16120446</infon><infon key="source">J Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">352</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>35354</offset><text>On the structural basis of the catalytic mechanism and the regulation of the alpha subunit of tryptophan synthase from Salmonella typhimurium and BX1 from maize, two evolutionarily related enzymes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1047</infon><infon key="lpage">1055</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Frey;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Spiteller;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Boland;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gierl;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15110684</infon><infon key="source">Phytochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">65</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>35551</offset><text>Transcriptional activation of Igl, the gene for indole formation in Zea mays: a structure-activity study with elicitor-active N-acyl glutamines from insects</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">27</infon><infon key="lpage">30</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hamilton;given-names:RH</infon><infon key="source">Weeds</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">1964</infon><offset>35708</offset><text>A corn mutant deficient in 2,4-dihydroxy-7-methoxy-1,4-benzoxazin-3-one with an altered tolerance of atrazine.</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">298</infon><infon key="lpage">305</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bannai;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tamada;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Maruyama;given-names:O</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Nakai;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Miyano;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11847077</infon><infon key="source">Bioinformatics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>35819</offset><text>Extensive feature detection of N-terminal protein sorting signals</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1005</infon><infon key="lpage">1016</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Emanuelsson;given-names:O</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Nielsen;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Brunak;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:von Heijne;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10891285</infon><infon key="source">J Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">300</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>35885</offset><text>Predicting subcellular localization of proteins based on their N-terminal amino acid sequence</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="lpage">10</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Creighton;given-names:TE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">4909097</infon><infon key="source">Eur J Biochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1970</infon><offset>35979</offset><text>A steady-state kinetic investigation of the reaction mechanism of the tryptophan synthetase of Escherichia coli</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">427</infon><infon key="lpage">448</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Neuhoff;given-names:V</infon><infon key="source">Electrophoresis</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1985</infon><offset>36091</offset><text>Clear background and highly sensitive protein staining with Coomassie Blue dyes in polyacrylamide gels: A systemic analysis </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3718</infon><infon key="lpage">3723</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cutler;given-names:SR;suffix:Ehrhardt, DW, Griffitts, JS, Somerville, CR</infon><infon key="source">Proceedings of the National Acadademy of Science, USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>36216</offset><text>GFP::cDNA fusions enable visualization of subcellular structures in cells of Arabidopsis at a high frequency.</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">225</infon><infon key="lpage">245</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sheen;given-names:J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1668653</infon><infon key="source">Plant Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>36326</offset><text>Molecular mechanisms underlying the differential expression of maize pyruvate, orthophosphate dikinase genes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1027</infon><infon key="lpage">1038</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sheen;given-names:J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2136626</infon><infon key="source">Plant Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">2</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>36435</offset><text>Metabolic repression of transcription in higher plants</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">737</infon><infon key="lpage">749</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schmid;given-names:J;suffix:Amrhein, N</infon><infon key="source">Phytochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">39</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>36490</offset><text>Molecular organization of the shikimate pathway in higher plants.</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">472</infon><infon key="lpage">478</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kirschner;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lane;given-names:AN</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Strasser;given-names:AW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1899027</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">30</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>36556</offset><text>Reciprocal communication between the lyase and synthase active sites of the tryptophan synthase bienzyme complex</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">375</infon><infon key="lpage">385</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Weischet;given-names:WO</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kirschner;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">949972</infon><infon key="source">Eur J Biochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">65</infon><infon key="year">1976</infon><offset>36669</offset><text>Steady-state kinetic studies of the synthesis of indoleglycerol phosphate catalyzed by the alpha subunit of tryptophan synthase from Escherichia coli. Comparison with the alpha2 beta2-complex</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">571</infon><infon key="lpage">582</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lane;given-names:AN</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kirschner;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6402362</infon><infon key="source">Eur J Biochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">129</infon><infon key="year">1983</infon><offset>36861</offset><text>The catalytic mechanism of tryptophan synthase from Escherichia coli. Kinetics of the reaction of indole with the enzyme--L-serine complexes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1537</infon><infon key="lpage">1540</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Mena;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ambrose;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Meeley;given-names:RB</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Briggs;given-names:SP</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Yanofsky;given-names:MF</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Schmidt;given-names:RJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8929416</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>37002</offset><text>Diversification of C-function activity in maize flower development</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">815</infon><infon key="lpage">821</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Eberhard;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ehrler;given-names:TT</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Epple;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Felix;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Raesecke;given-names:HR</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Amrhein;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Schmid;given-names:J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8953244</infon><infon key="source">Plant J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>37069</offset><text>Cytosolic and plastidic chorismate mutase isozymes from Arabidopsis thaliana: molecular characterization and enzymatic properties</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">10678</infon><infon key="lpage">10683</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kawasaki;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bauerle;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Zon;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ahmed;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Miles;given-names:EW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3112150</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">262</infon><infon key="year">1987</infon><offset>37199</offset><text>Site-specific mutagenesis of the alpha subunit of tryptophan synthase from Salmonella typhimurium. Changing arginine 179 to leucine alters the reciprocal transmission of substrate-induced conformational changes between the alpha and beta 2 subunits</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_0">surname:Stettner;given-names:C</infon><infon key="source">DIMBOA-Biosynthese in Mais: Isolierung und funktionelle Charakterisierung des Bx1-Gens</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>37448</offset></passage></document></collection>
