<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>18508778</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M709628200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2490792</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">18508778</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">21799</infon><infon key="fpage">21799</infon><infon key="issue">31</infon><infon key="lpage">21807</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bhalla;given-names:Akhil</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Chicka;given-names:Michael C.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Chapman;given-names:Edwin R.</infon><infon key="p">This work was supported, in whole or in part, by the  . This work was also supported by  the  (to E. R. C.).  The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment  of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked  &quot;;advertisement&quot; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section  1734 solely to indicate this fact.</infon><infon key="subtitle">UNCOVERING A CLASS OF INHIBITORY  ISOFORMS*</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Analysis of the Synaptotagmin Family during Reconstituted Membrane  Fusion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>75</offset><text>Ca2+-triggered exocytosis in neurons and neuroendocrine cells is  regulated by the Ca2+-binding protein synaptotagmin (syt) I.  Sixteen additional isoforms of syt have been identified, but little is known  concerning their biochemical or functional properties. Here, we assessed the  abilities of fourteen syt isoforms to directly regulate SNARE (soluble  N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor (NSF) attachment protein  receptor)-catalyzed membrane fusion. One group of isoforms stimulated neuronal  SNARE-mediated fusion in response to Ca2+, while another set  inhibited SNARE catalyzed fusion in both the absence and presence of  Ca2+. Biochemical analysis revealed a strong correlation between  the ability of syt isoforms to bind 1,2-dioleoyl phosphatidylserine (PS) and  t-SNAREs in a Ca2+-promoted manner with their abilities to enhance  fusion, further establishing PS and SNAREs as critical effectors for syt  action. The ability of syt I to efficiently stimulate fusion was specific for  certain SNARE pairs, suggesting that syts might contribute to the specificity  of intracellular membrane fusion reactions. Finally, a subset of inhibitory  syts down-regulated the ability of syt I to activate fusion, demonstrating  that syt isoforms can modulate the function of each other.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1359</offset><text>Over the last decade significant progress has been made in defining the  molecular machinery that mediates Ca2+-triggered exocytosis from  neurons and neuroendocrine cells. A key discovery was the observation that the  clostridial neurotoxins, botulinum (serotypes A-G) and tetanus toxin, block  neurotransmitter and hormone release by cleaving a group of proteins called  soluble N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor (NSF) attachment protein  receptors (SNAREs),4  revealing that SNAREs are required for secretion  (1). SNAREs are conserved from  yeast to humans (2), and are  classified into two categories: vesicle SNAREs (v-SNAREs) and target membrane  SNAREs (t-SNAREs). In the case of synaptic vesicle exocytosis, the v-SNARE is  synaptobrevin (syb) 2 (also referred to as vesicle-associated membrane protein  (VAMP) II) and the t-SNAREs are syntaxin 1A and SNAP-25B. These three SNARE  proteins spontaneously assemble together into highly stable ternary complexes,  suggesting that interactions between v- and t-SNAREs might link the vesicle  and target membrane to drive fusion (reviewed in Ref.  2). Indeed, Weber et  al. (3) reconstituted  neuronal v-SNAREs and t-SNAREs into two populations of liposomes and utilized  a fluorescence dequenching assay to demonstrate that the assembly of  trans-SNARE pairs was in fact sufficient to drive membrane fusion  in vitro. Hence, SNAREs have emerged as the core of a conserved  membrane fusion machine.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2812</offset><text>The Ca2+-binding protein, synaptotagmin (syt) I, serves as a  major Ca2+ sensor that regulates SNARE-mediated fusion  (4-6).  Syt I was identified as an abundant constituent of synaptic vesicles and large  dense core vesicles (7,  8). Biochemical studies  established that Ca2+ triggers the rapid penetration of two  conserved Ca2+-binding motifs in the cytoplasmic domain of syt I,  called C2 domains (Fig.  1A), into membranes that harbor anionic phospholipids  (9-11).  This interaction might help to draw the two bilayers together to facilitate  fusion, or might buckle the plasma membrane toward the vesicle membrane,  lowering the energy barrier for fusion  (6,  12).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3486</offset><text>Syt I also binds to the t-SNAREs syntaxin 1A  (13) and SNAP-25B  (14), at all stages of SNARE  complex assembly, and these interactions are promoted by Ca2+ on  very fast time scales (15).  These findings established a biochemical link between the putative  Ca2+ sensor and the fusion machinery. Biochemical experiments also  revealed that Ca2+ syt I can drive the folding of SNARE  proteins into functional complexes  (16), and cell-based  experiments support the idea that syt operates, in part, via direct  interactions with SNAREs (15,  17-19).  However, another group has concluded that Ca2+-regulated  interactions between syt I  (20,  21) and IX  (22,  23) with SNARE proteins does  not play a role in excitation-secretion coupling, and this issue remains a  subject of debate.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4271</offset><text>Genetic studies support the idea that syt I plays a critical role in  triggering rapid exocytosis (5,  6). Direct support for this  model stems from the finding that syt I imparts Ca2+ sensitivity to  SNARE-catalyzed membrane fusion reactions that have been reconstituted in  vitro (24). In this  reduced system, both phosphatidylserine (PS) and t-SNAREs were critical  effectors for the action of syt I  (16,  25). While these findings have  helped to provide a general understanding of how syt I might function to  regulate exocytosis, its detailed mechanism of action is still far from  understood. Moreover, sixteen additional isoforms of syt have been identified  (26), and little is known  concerning the functional and biochemical properties for many isoforms of syt.  A number of studies have shown that a subset of syt isoforms bind  PS-containing liposomes in a Ca2+-promoted manner  (27,  28) and that some isoforms of  syt interact with the syx-SNAP-25 t-SNARE heterodimer in the absence of  Ca2+ (27). However,  a comprehensive analysis of whether or not all isoforms of syt bind  membrane-embedded t-SNAREs in a Ca2+-promoted manner has not been  undertaken. Moreover, the functional properties of most isoforms of syt remain  unknown, and it is unclear if all syt isoforms function as Ca2+  sensors for SNARE-catalyzed membrane fusion, in a manner similar to syt I, or  whether some isoforms display unique Ca2+-independent  functions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5722</offset><text>Previously, we found that two other isoforms, syt VII and syt IX, also  stimulated SNARE-catalyzed membrane fusion in response to Ca2+, but  with markedly different [Ca2+]1/2 values  (25). Hence, different  isoforms of syt might underlie, at least in part, the distinct Ca2+  requirements for neurotransmitter release observed for different cell types  (4). In addition, all isoforms  of syt might not act to stimulate membrane fusion or secretion. For example,  syt IV, an isoform that is up-regulated in response to activity  (29), does not engage in any  known Ca2+-dependent effector interactions  (30,  31), and down-regulates large  dense core exocytosis in PC12 cells  (31-33).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6407</offset><text>Here, we examined the functional and biochemical properties of fourteen  isoforms of syt. One group of syts bound to PS and target membrane SNAREs in a  Ca2+-promoted manner and activated fusion. A second group of syts  failed to respond to Ca2+ but were able to inhibit SNARE-mediated  fusion. Furthermore, a subset of this latter group of syts reduced the ability  of syt I to activate fusion by competing for syt-SNARE interactions, providing  evidence that syts can modulate the function of one another. Finally, the  ability of syt I to efficiently stimulate fusion was specific for certain  SNARE pairs, suggesting that syts might contribute to the specificity of  intracellular membrane fusion reactions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>7119</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7143</offset><text>Plasmids and Protein Purification:For all experiments, the  cytoplasmic domain of the indicated syt isoform was used. cDNA encoding syts  I-XII are described in Ref.  28, and cDNA encoding the  cytoplasmic domains of syt XIII and XV were provided by M. Craxton (Laboratory  of Molecular Biology, Cambridge, UK). The amino acid residues encoding these  cytoplasmic domains (C2A-C2B) are as follows: I, 96-421; II, 139-423; III,  290-569; IV, 152-425; V, 218-491; VI, 143-426; VII, 134-403; VIII, 97-395; IX,  104-386; X, 223-501; XI, 150-430; XII, 114-421; XIII, 158-427; XV, 139-421.  Each isoform was subcloned into either pTrc-HisA (Invitrogen) or pET28a  (Novagen).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7812</offset><text>Syts were expressed in Escherichia coli and purified as previously  described (25). Briefly,  bacterial pellets were resuspended in 25 mm HEPES-KOH, 400  mm KCl, 20 mm imidazole, and 5 mm  beta-mercaptoethanol, and then lysed by sonication followed by addition of  Triton X-100 (final 2% v/v). Bacteria were pelleted, and extracts were mixed  with Ni-nitrilotriacetic acid-agarose (Qiagen) for 2 h at 4  C. Beads were  washed two times in wash buffer (25 mm HEPES-KOH, 400 mm  KCl, 20 mm imidazole, and 5 mm beta-mercaptoethanol, 1  mm MgCl2) plus 10 mug/ml DNase and RNase (Roche  Applied Science) to remove any bound RNA/DNA. Two more washes were carried out  in the resuspension buffer. Proteins were eluted from beads in the  resuspension buffer with 500 mm imidazole and 10% glycerol (w/v)  and dialyzed overnight against 25 mm HEPES pH 7.4, 200  mm KCl, 10% glycerol (w/v), 1 mm dithiothreitol (Buffer  A). Because of technical difficulties, we were unable to express and purify  appropriate quantities of recombinant syt XIV and XVI from E.  coli.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8867</offset><text>Plasmids to generate recombinant full-length synaptobrevin 2 and the  full-length t-SNARE heterodimer (syntaxin 1A and SNAP-25B), were provided by  J. E. Rothman (Columbia University), and proteins were expressed and purified  as described (3,  24). cDNA encoding full-length  rat syntaxin 1A and syntaxin 4 were provided by R. H. Scheller (Genentech, San  Francisco, CA) and J. M. Edwardson (Cambridge, UK), respectively. cDNA  encoding full-length SNAP-25B was provided by M. C. Wilson (University of New  Mexico). cDNA encoding SNAP-23 and SNAP-29 were provided by R. Jahn (Max  Planck Institute, Gottingen, Germany). The following t-SNARE heterodimer pairs  were subcloned into pRSF-Duet (Novagen) and expressed as above:  syntaxin1A/SNAP-23, syntaxin1A/SNAP-29, syntaxin4/SNAP-23, and  syntaxin4/SNAP-25B. Primary references for syb 2, SNAP-25B, and syntaxin 1A  can be found in Ref. 16.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9760</offset><text>Preparation of Protein-free and SNARE-bearing Vesicles:All  lipids were obtained from Avanti Polar Lipids (Alabaster, AL). Reconstitution  of v-SNARE and t-SNARE vesicles was carried out as previously described  (3,  24). v-SNAREs were  reconstituted using a lipid mix composed of 30% 1-palmitoyl, 2-oleoyl  phosphatidylethanolamine (PE), 52% 1-palmitoyl, 2-oleoyl phosphatidylcholine  (PC), 15% 1,2-dioleoyl phosphatidylserine (PS), 1.5%  N-(7-nitro-2-1,3-benzoxadiazol-4-yl)-1,2-dipalmitoyl  phosphatidylethanolamine (NBD-PE, donor), and 1.5% N-(lissamine  rhodamine B sulfonyl)-1,2-dipalmitoyl phosphatidylethanolamine (Rhodamine-PE,  acceptor). t-SNAREs were reconstituted in 30% PE, 55% PC, and 15% PS (mol  mol-1). When PS was omitted, PC was increased to 70% for the  t-SNARE vesicles. v-SNARE and t-SNARE vesicles were reconstituted to give  ~100 copies or ~80 copies per vesicle, respectively, as described  (24). At ~80  copies/vesicle, the t-SNARE concentration in the fusion assay is ~3  mum. Protein-free (pf) vesicles were prepared as described  previously (24).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10837</offset><text>Flotation Assays:Flotation assays were carried out as  described previously with modifications  (24,  25). Briefly, pf vesicles with  (30% PE/15% PS/55% PC) or without (30% PE/70% PC) PS, or t-SNARE vesicles (30%  PE/70% PC), were mixed with syt (10 mum). All binding reactions  were carried out in a total volume of 100 mul of Buffer A with either 0.2  mm EGTA or 1 mm Ca2+. Samples were incubated  with shaking for 1 h at room temperature and were then mixed with an equal  volume of 80% Accudenz medium, transferred to a Beckman ultracentrifuge tube  and layered with 150 mul each of 35 and 30% Accudenz media in Buffer A.  Finally, samples were layered with 20 mul of Buffer A lacking glycerol and  centrifuged at 280,000 x g for 2.5 h at 4  C. All  buffers/media contained either 0.2 mm EGTA or 1 mm  Ca2+.40 mul of vesicles from the 0%/30% interface were collected  from each tube, and one-third of the collected sample was resolved by SDS-PAGE  and stained with Coomassie Blue. All gels contain standards (stds) that serve  as references for the electrophoretic mobility of the proteins used in the  flotation assays. For competition experiments in  Fig. 6, the indicated  concentrations of syt IV, VIII, and XII were included in reactions along with  10 mum syt I. All Coomassie-stained gels are representative  examples from &gt;=3 trials.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>12183</offset><text>Conservation of the putative Ca2+ ligands  among different isoforms of syt. A, model depicting the  structure of syt. The image was generated using the crystal structure of the  cytoplasmic domain of syt III  (37); remaining segments were  added with a drawing program. B, schematic diagram showing  the five Ca2+-coordinating residues in the C2A and C2B domains of  syt I. The diagram is modified and reproduced with permission from the authors  of Ref. 51. C,  conservation among the Ca2+ ligands in the C2A and C2B domains of  syt I-XIII and XV. Numbers correspond to the order of the five aspartate  residues that function as Ca2+ ligands in the C2A domain of syt I  (D172, 178, 230, 232, 238) and C2B (D303, 309, 363, 365, 371)  (6). Single letter  codes indicate substitutions of conserved aspartate residues; (+) denotes  conservation of an aspartate, and (-) indicates a gap. Based on conservation  of the Ca2+ ligands, we predicted which syts might (+) and might  not (-) stimulate in vitro SNARE-mediated fusion in response to  Ca2+.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13227</offset><text>Fusion Assays:Each reaction consisted of 45 mul of  purified t-SNARE vesicles (30% PE/15% PS/55% PC) and 5 mul of purified,  v-SNARE vesicles (30% PE/1.5% NBD-PE/1.5% Rhodamine-PE/15% PS/52% PC) plus 0.2  mm EGTA or 1 mm Ca2+ in a total volume of 75  mul of Buffer A. 10 mum syt was added where indicated. For  competition experiments in Fig.  5, the indicated concentrations of syt IV, VIII, and XII were  included in reactions along with 10 mum syt I. Fusion reactions  were carried out in 96-well plates, and NBD fluorescence was monitored at 37   C in a plate reader (Biotek Instruments; excitation 460 nm, emission 538  nm). After 2 h, 0.5% n-dodecylmaltoside (w/v, Roche Applied Science)  was added to maximally dequench the NBD fluorescence. Raw fluorescence was  normalized to obtain % maximum fluorescence as described  (24,  34). Error bars represent S.E.  from n &gt;= 3. Percent stimulation in Ca2+ in  Fig. 3B was calculated  by Equation 1.    Percent stimulation over (-)syt was calculated by Equation 2.    </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>14247</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14255</offset><text>Conservation of the Ca2+ Ligands in the  C2A and C2B Domains of Syt:To date, seventeen isoforms of syt have  been identified in vertebrates  (26). All members of this  protein family share similar overall domain structures (shown in  Fig. 1A); the  cytoplasmic domains are comprised of tandem C2 domains (C2A and C2B) that are  tethered together by a short linker (Fig.  1A)  (35-37).  C2 domains, first identified in protein kinase C, are now found in a variety  of proteins where they often, but not always, mediate binding to  Ca2+ and phospholipids  (38). In syt I, both C2  domains mediate Ca2+-regulated interactions with anionic  phospholipids and t-SNAREs (6).  However, the five aspartic acid residues that coordinate Ca2+ ions  in each C2 domain of syt I (Fig.  1B) are conserved in only a subset of isoforms  (Fig. 1C, see also  Refs. 27,  39). The strict conservation  of these Ca2+ ligands in syt I-VII and IX-X suggest that these  isoforms bind Ca2+ and therefore might be able to stimulate fusion  mediated by neuronal SNARE proteins. In contrast, syt VIII, XI-XIII, and XV  harbor substitutions that are expected to disrupt Ca2+ binding  activity in both C2 domains, suggesting that these isoforms would be incapable  of coupling Ca2+ to fusion.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15517</offset><text>Divergent Activities of syt Isoforms during Neuronal SNARE-mediated  Membrane Fusion:In vitro studies revealed that in response  to Ca2+, syt I stimulates SNARE-catalyzed membrane fusion  (12,  24), providing direct evidence  that syt I can act as a Ca2+ sensor for exocytosis in vivo  (4-6).  More recently, this observation was extended to two other syt family members,  syt VII and IX (25). In  contrast, syt IV failed to stimulate membrane fusion in reconstituted fusion  assays (12), consistent with  its putative role as a negative regulator of secretion from neuroendocrine  cells  (31-33).  However, the ability of the other thirteen isoforms of syt to regulate  membrane fusion remained unknown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>16222</offset><text>Normalized fusion data from fourteen isoforms of syt. A,  illustration depicting the in vitro fusion assay used in this study.  Fusion of v-SNARE (syb; v) vesicles, containing a donor (D)  and acceptor (A) FRET pair, with unlabeled t-SNARE vesicles (syntaxin  1A/SNAP-25B; t), results in dilution of the FRET pair and an increase  in donor fluorescence. B, syt isoforms differentially regulate fusion  between v- and t-SNARE vesicles. Fusion was monitored for 120 min at 37  C  in the absence (-syt) or presence (+syt, 10 mum) of different syt  isoforms, normalized to the maximum donor fluorescence signal (% max  Fl), and plotted as a function of time. Reactions were carried out in 0.2  mm EGTA or 1 mm Ca2+. Representative traces  for the different syt isoforms are shown from &gt;=3 independent trials.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17027</offset><text>Using the in vitro membrane fusion assay, we screened fourteen syt  isoforms for their abilities to regulate fusion between v-SNARE vesicles (v),  that harbor synaptobrevin 2, and t-SNARE vesicles (t), that harbor syntaxin  1A/SNAP-25B heterodimers (Fig.  2A). Raw fusion data are shown in  Fig. 2B; only a subset  of syt isoforms stimulated SNARE-catalyzed fusion in the presence of  Ca2+: syt I-III, V-VII, and IX-X. This group of syts corresponded  to the isoforms that were predicted to serve as Ca2+ sensors  (Fig. 1C), with the  exception of syt IV, which has one Asp to Ser substitution in the C2A domain  but harbors an intact set of putative Ca2+ ligands in C2B. These  data were quantified in Fig.  3A, where the average extent of fusion (% maximum  fluorescence intensity), from all trials was plotted for each syt isoform.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17862</offset><text>To better visualize the impact of syt isoforms on fusion and to highlight  differences that might have been obscured by averaging across all trials  (because of sample-to-sample differences in the overall extent of fusion), we  compared the extent of fusion obtained in Ca2+ to the extent of  fusion obtained in EGTA within each individual trial  (Fig. 3B, Equation 1  under &quot;;Experimental Procedures&quot;), then averaged the data. In  addition, we compared the extent of fusion obtained by  Ca2+ syt to fusion mediated by v- and t-SNAREs in the  absence of syt (Fig.  3C, Equation 2 under &quot;;Experimental  Procedures&quot;), again within each individual trial, and then calculated  the average values. The former plot shows the range of stimulation mediated by  syts under our experimental conditions, whereas the latter plot indicates the  extent to which each syt isoform was able to stimulate or suppress fusion  mediated by SNAREs themselves. A key finding was that syts IV, VIII, XI, and  XII were unable to respond to Ca2+, but were able to inhibit fusion  mediated by SNAREs alone (Fig.  3C).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18953</offset><text>Stimulation of Membrane Fusion Is Related to the Ability of syts to  Engage PS and t-SNAREs in Response to Ca2+:In  response to Ca2+, the tandem C2 domains of syt I engage t-SNAREs  and the anionic phospholipid PS, and previous studies indicate that these  interactions are critical for the regulation of membrane fusion  (15,  16,  18,  24,  25). However, others have  concluded that syt I operates independently of its Ca2+-promoted  interactions with SNAREs (20,  21), and that syt IX functions  without binding SNAREs at all  (22,  23). To further explore the  mechanism of action of syts, we carried out experiments to relate their  activity in the fusion assay with their abilities to engage both PS and  t-SNAREs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19674</offset><text>We utilized a co-flotation assay (Fig.  4A and Ref.  24) to determine which of the  syt isoforms that had been screened in the fusion assay interact with  full-length, membrane-embedded, syntaxin 1A/SNAP-25B heterodimers, and PS. All  of the syt isoforms tested exhibited some degree of t-SNARE and PS binding  activity in the absence of Ca2+  (Fig. 4, B, C, and  E). However, only the stimulatory syts I-III, V-VII, and  IX-X bound t-SNAREs and PS in a Ca2+-promoted manner  (Fig. 4B). The syts  that failed to stimulate fusion, isoforms IV, VIII, XI, XII, XIII, and XV,  also bound t-SNAREs and PS, but these interactions were not enhanced by  Ca2+. The t-SNARE binding data are in agreement with previously  observed results for syts I, VII, and IX  (25) (but see also Ref.  22), and the PS binding data  are in agreement with a study focused on syts I-XII  (28). Protein-free PC/PE  vesicles were used as a negative control; no binding of any isoform of syt to  these vesicles was detected, indicating syt lipid interactions are  specific for PS under our experimental conditions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>20759</offset><text>Syt isoforms differentially regulate neuronal SNARE-catalyzed membrane  fusion. A, average extent of fusion (% max FI) at  t = 120 min, in either 0.2 mm EGTA (open bars) or  1 mm Ca2+ (filled bars), was plotted for each  syt isoform. (-)syt indicates fusion between v- and t-SNARE vesicles in the  absence of syt. The data plotted here are averages across all trials.  Error bars represent S.E. (n &gt;= 3). B, average %  stimulation in Ca2+ (fusion in Ca2+ compared with fusion  in EGTA within each individual trial and then averaged; Equation 1 in  &quot;;Experimental Procedures&quot;) was plotted for v- and  t-SNARE-mediated fusion and for each syt isoform. Error bars  represent S.E. (n &gt;= 3). C, average % stimulation over  (-)syt (fusion by Ca2+ syt compared with fusion mediated by  SNAREs in the absence of syt within each individual trial and then averaged;  Equation 2 in &quot;;Experimental Procedures&quot;) was plotted for each syt  isoform. Error bars represent S.E. (n &gt;= 3).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21729</offset><text>The extent to which syt associated with t-SNARE vesicles in EGTA or  Ca2+ was quantified using densitometry and normalized to the  syntaxin band in the corresponding lane; the % change in t-SNARE binding in  response to Ca2+ was plotted  (Fig. 4C). The amount  of syt that bound to PS-containing vesicles in the presence of Ca2+  was also plotted (Fig.  4E). These two plots  (Fig. 4, C and  E) exhibited similar patterns; syts that bind PS in  response to Ca2+ also bind t-SNAREs in response to Ca2+,  and vice versa. These findings agree with the notion that syt acts by  engaging membranes and SNAREs at the same time and that these interactions are  coupled (10,  16).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22402</offset><text>We then plotted the effect syts had on SNARE-mediated fusion (% stimulation  over (-)syt from Fig.  3C) against the % increase in Ca2+-promoted  binding to t-SNAREs (Fig.  4D) and against the extent of PS binding in the presence  of Ca2+ (Fig.  4F). These plots illustrate a strong correlation between  the ability of a syt isoform to bind both of these effectors in a  Ca2+-dependent manner with their abilities to stimulate  SNARE-catalyzed fusion in response to Ca2+. Similarly, there is a  strong correlation between syts that interact with t-SNAREs and PS in a  Ca2+-independent manner with their abilities to inhibit  SNARE-catalyzed fusion. In no case did a syt isoform stimulate fusion without  binding to PS and t-SNAREs in a Ca2+-promoted manner, supporting a  model in which syts stimulate fusion through Ca2+-dependent  interactions with both of these effectors.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23277</offset><text>Syt Isoforms Can Modulate the Activity of Each Other:In the  course of screening syts I-XIII and XV, we identified a class of syts (IV,  VIII, XI, and XII) that failed to respond to Ca2+ in our  biochemical assays and that inhibited SNARE-catalyzed fusion  (Fig. 3C). These  findings prompted the idea that these inhibitory syts might antagonize the  action of syt isoforms that stimulate fusion in response to Ca2+  (e.g. see Ref. 33).  To test this idea, we asked whether a subset of inhibitory syts could affect  the ability of syt I to stimulate SNARE-catalyzed membrane fusion. We fixed  the amount of syt I in the fusion assay and titrated increasing amounts of  syts IV (Fig. 5, A and  B), VIII (Fig. 5,  C and D), and XII  (Fig. 5, E and  F). Syt IV and VIII inhibited syt-stimulated fusion in a  dose-dependent manner, whereas syt XII had no appreciable effect over the  range of concentrations tested. We note that higher concentrations of syt IV,  VIII, and XII could not be tested because of low protein yields and volume  constraints of the fusion assay. Syt XI, another inhibitory syt, behaved in a  similar manner to syt IV and VIII, i.e. it inhibited syt I-stimulated  fusion in a dose-dependent  manner.5 Because syt I  and IV have been co-localized to large dense core vesicles (LDCVs) in PC12  cells (29,  33), these findings support  the idea that different syt isoforms on the same secretory organelle might  serve to fine-tune the efficiency of exocytosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24756</offset><text>Next, we found that syts IV and VIII significantly reduced  Ca2+-promoted binding of syt I to t-SNAREs  (Fig. 6, A and  B, left and right panels). In contrast,  syt XII, the inhibitory syt that failed to suppress syt I-stimulated fusion,  significantly reduced syt I t-SNARE interactions only when added to the  assay in a 3-fold molar excess of syt I  (Fig. 6C,  left and right panels). Thus, it appears that inhibitory  isoforms of syt can impact fusion in two ways: first, they directly inhibit  SNARE-mediated fusion, and second, they displace syt I from the fusion  complex. These properties are clearly apparent for syt IV and VIII; syt XII  differs to some extent as this isoform exhibits less inhibitory activity in  terms of both shutting down SNARE function and displacing syt I. Moreover,  these experiments provide further support for the idea that syts act, at least  in part, via direct interactions with t-SNAREs to regulate fusion.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25704</offset><text>Specificity of Functional Pairing between syts and t-SNAREs during  Membrane Fusion:At present, approximately thirty-six SNARE proteins  have been identified in humans  (2). Different SNAREs are  targeted to distinct subcellular compartments where they catalyze many, and  perhaps all, intracellular membrane fusion events  (40). It was proposed that  pairing between specific v- and t-SNAREs encodes the specificity of  intracellular membrane fusion reactions  (41). While SNARE pairing  clearly plays a central role in the specificity of fusion, it is now  established that other mechanisms also come into play  (42).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>26324</offset><text>Syts differ in their ability to bind PS and t-SNAREs. A,  diagram of the flotation assay used to monitor binding of the different syt  isoforms to t-SNARE vesicles (t), or protein free vesicles, with  (PF(+PS)) or without PS (PF). Syt will float to the top of the gradient only  if it interacts with vesicles. After centrifugation, samples are collected  from the top of the gradient and analyzed by SDS-PAGE; proteins are visualized  by staining with Coomassie Blue. B, flotation assays were carried out  as depicted in panel A. Binding was monitored in either 0.2  mm EGTA (-) or 1 mm Ca2+(+). A representative  gel from three independent trials is shown for each syt isoform. For the syt  IV gel only, a line was added between the t-SNARE and syt IV standards to  indicate lanes that were originally spaced further apart on the same gel and  were combined for this figure. C, amount of syt that co-floated with  t-SNARE vesicles in 0.2 mm EGTA or 1 mm Ca2+  from panel B was quantified using densitometry and normalized to the  syntaxin band in each lane. The average % increase in t-SNARE binding in the  presence of Ca2+ versus EGTA was calculated using  normalized data and plotted for each isoform. Error bars represent  S.E. (n = 3). In panels C-F, red is used to denote  the inhibitory syts indicated in Fig.  3C. D, for each syt isoform, % stimulation over  syt (from Fig. 3C) was  plotted against the average % increase in t-SNARE binding for each syt isoform  from panel C. E, the amount of syt bound to PS-harboring  vesicles in 1 mmCa2+ from panel B was  quantified using densitometry. The average total optical density is plotted  for each isoform (because there is no other band in each lane against which  the syt signal can be normalized as in panel C). Error bars  represent S.E. (n &gt;= 3). F, % stimulation over (-)syt  (from Fig. 3C) was  plotted against the average amount of syt bound to PS-harboring vesicles in 1  mm Ca2+ from panel E.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28284</offset><text>Utilizing a subset of the plasma membrane SNAREs (SNAP-25B, SNAP-23,  syntaxin 1A, and syntaxin 4) and a ubiquitously expressed SNARE (SNAP-29), we  asked whether syt t-SNARE pairing might also contribute to the  specificity of membrane fusion reactions. First, we observed that the extent  of fusion between syb 2 vesicles and target vesicles that harbored distinct  sets of t-SNAREs differed for some t-SNARE pairs. Namely, syntaxin 1A/SNAP-29  and syntaxin 4/SNAP-25B did not fuse as efficiently as did syntaxin  1A/SNAP-25B, syntaxin 1A/SNAP-23, or syntaxin 4/SNAP-23 vesicles, all of which  exhibited similar levels of fusion (Fig.  7, red and green traces).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28948</offset><text>We then tested the ability of syt I to stimulate fusion mediated by these  different SNARE pairs. We found that syt I stimulated fusion whenever syntaxin  1A or SNAP-25B were present on the t-SNARE vesicle, but failed to efficiently  stimulate fusion when both syntaxin 1A and SNAP-25B had been replaced with  syntaxin 4 and SNAP-23 (see also Ref.  43). In addition,  Ca2+ syt was able to activate otherwise weak SNARE-mediated  fusion reactions (e.g. syntaxin 1A/SNAP-29 and syntaxin 4/SNAP-25B  t-SNARE vesicles) by severalfold (Fig.  7). Moreover, syt I had only a slight effect on fusion between syb  2 vesicles and syntaxin 4/SNAP-23 vesicles even though this particular SNARE  pair catalyzed fusion in a manner that was similar to reactions mediated by  syntaxin 1A/SNAP-25B and syntaxin 1A/SNAP-23. Thus, syt I does not stimulate  all SNARE-mediated fusion reactions equally, but rather, discriminates between  t-SNAREs, potentially adding a level of specificity to SNARE-mediated fusion  reactions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>29955</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29966</offset><text>Previous studies characterized the effect of syts I, IV, VII, and IX on  fusion mediated by neuronal SNAREs  (12,  24,  25). In the current study we  extended this analysis to include fourteen isoforms of syt. Most of these  isoforms inhibited fusion, to a limited extent under our experimental  conditions, in the absence of Ca2+ (e.g. syt I; see also  Ref. 24). We note that all  isoforms of syt tested bound t-SNAREs to some extent in EGTA. These  Ca2+-independent syt-t-SNARE interactions may function by halting  SNARE complex assembly and inhibiting fusion in the absence of  Ca2+. Syts I-III, V-VII, IX, and X stimulated fusion in response to  Ca2+, whereas syts IV, VIII, XI-XIII, and XV failed to facilitate  fusion in the presence or absence of Ca2+. Furthermore, some of the  syts that failed to stimulate fusion actually inhibited fusion (Figs.  2 and  3). Without exception,  stimulatory syts bound to PS and t-SNAREs in response to Ca2+  whereas inhibitory syts did not (Fig.  4). Moreover, a subset of inhibitory syts reduced the extent of  syt I-stimulated fusion. These data indicate that the presence of different  isoforms of syts on the same secretory organelle might fine-tune the  efficiency (Fig. 5),  Ca2+-sensitivity  (25), and mode of exocytosis  (31) by competing for  interactions with effectors. Below, we relate these in vitro findings  with studies aimed at understanding the function of syt isoforms in cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>31408</offset><text>Syts IV and VIII, but not XII, inhibit syt I-mediated stimulation of  membrane fusion. Syt I (10 mum) stimulates fusion between v-  and t-SNARE vesicles in response to Ca2+ (panels A,  C, and E, red trace). A, increasing  concentrations of syt IV were added to fusion reactions containing 10  mum syt I and 1 mm Ca2+. Fusion was  monitored for 120 min at 37  C and plotted as % max Fl over time.  B, average extent of fusion from the data in panel A (%  max Fl) at t = 120 min was plotted as a function of [syt  IV]. C, experiments were carried out as in panel A except  syt VIII was used in place of syt IV. D, data from panel C  were plotted as a function of [syt VIII]. E, experiments were carried  out as in panel A except syt XII was used in place of syt IV.  F, data from E were plotted as a function of [syt XII]. In  all plots, error bars represent S.E. (n = 3).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>32279</offset><text>Syt isoforms compete with one another for binding to t-SNAREs.  A, left, binding of syt I and IV to t-SNARE (t)  vesicles was carried out in the absence (-) or presence (+) of  Ca2+. Syts were assayed individually and in the indicated  combinations using 10 mum each syt, or 10 mum syt I  and 30 mum syt IV (representing a 1:1 and 1:3 molar ratio of syt  I:competitor syt, respectively). One-third of each sample was subjected to  SDS-PAGE; gels were stained with Coomassie Blue. Right, the amount of  syt I bound to t-SNAREs was quantified by densitometry, normalized to the  SNAP-25 band in each lane, and plotted as a percentage of SNAP-25. Data  represent the average and S.E. from n &gt;= 3. B, experiments  were carried out as in panel A, except syt VIII was used in place of  syt IV. C, experiments were carried out as in panel A,  except syt XII was used in place of syt IV. Statistical analysis was carried  out using a Student's t test; *, p &lt; 0.05;  **, p &lt; 0.01; n.s. (not significant)  p &gt; 0.05. All gels are representative from &gt;=3 trials. In  panel A only, the line on the gel (left panel) separates  groups of lanes that were originally spaced further apart on the same gel and  were combined for the figure.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>33501</offset><text>Specificity of functional pairing between syt I and t-SNAREs. Fusion  reactions were carried out as described in the legend to  Fig. 2A using t-SNARE  vesicles that harbored the indicated t-SNARE pairs and v-SNARE vesicles than  harbored syb 2. Fusion was monitored in the absence (-syt) or presence (+syt)  of 10 mum syt I in either 0.2 mm EGTA or 1  mm Ca2+ and plotted as the % max fluorescence intensity  over time. Representative traces from three independent trials are shown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33984</offset><text>A recent flurry of reports addressed the role of syt II, which is highly  homologous to syt I, during exocytosis at synapses. In specific subsets of  neurons, syt II plays a critical role in Ca2+-triggered  neurotransmitter release (23,  44-46)  and can restore rapid release when expressed in syt I knock-out cortical  neurons (23). However, the  mechanism by which syt II functions had not been explored in detail. Syt II  binds PS in response to Ca2+ and here we show that this isoform  also interacts with the t-SNAREs syntaxin 1A and SNAP-25B in a  Ca2+-promoted manner, and stimulates SNARE-catalyzed fusion. So, as  expected, syt II likely shares the same mechanism of action as syt I  (27,  46).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34688</offset><text>It was previously reported that syt IX does not bind to neuronal t-SNAREs  (22) but is able to rescue  fast neurotransmitter release in syt I knock-out neurons  (23). Together, these studies  would seem to rule out both Ca2+-independent and  Ca2+-dependent syt-SNARE interactions during exocytosis. However,  another study employing three different kinds of binding assays demonstrated  that syt IX does in fact bind neuronal t-SNAREs in a Ca2+-promoted  manner (25). Here, we confirm  these observations, as well as the fact that syt IX can directly stimulate  SNARE-catalyzed fusion in response to Ca2+. So, analogous to syts I  and II, syt IX is likely to regulate membrane fusion via  Ca2+-promoted interactions with both PS and t-SNAREs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35431</offset><text>Syt IV, a seizure-induced isoform with a single Asp to Ser substitution of  one of the Ca2+ ligands in the C2A domain  (29) is unable to bind PS and  t-SNAREs in a Ca2+-dependent manner  (Fig. 4, B, C, and  E and Refs.  30,  31). Syt I and IV are  co-localized to large dense core vesicles in PC12 cells, where up-regulation  of syt IV was shown to decrease the frequency of large dense core vesicle  membrane fusion events and to destabilize fusion pores  (31,  33). Syt IV also favored the  formation of tiny fusion pores, with one-fifth the transmitter flux of  full-sized kiss-and-run fusion pores, that always close without dilating  (31,  33). So, syt IV negatively  regulates the rate of exocytosis and also affects fusion pore structure and  dynamics. The inhibitory role of syt IV is important in neurons as well.  Activity-induced up-regulation of syt IV negatively regulates the release of  neurotrophic factors from dense core vesicles, thereby regulating synaptic  plasticity. Up-regulation of syt IV might act homeostatically to dampen  overactive circuits.6  Here, we demonstrate that syt IV itself inhibits SNARE-catalyzed membrane  fusion (Figs. 2 and  3; see also Ref.  12). We also show that syt IV  down-regulates Ca2+ syt I-stimulated membrane fusion in our  reduced assay system (Fig. 5, A  and B), in part by competing with syt I for interactions  with t-SNAREs (Fig.  6A). Therefore, using a reconstituted system, we have  recapitulated the negative regulatory role syt IV plays during dense core  vesicle exocytosis. It should be noted that syt IV might play a positive role  during other kinds of fusion events. For example, syt IV appears to be  required for homotypic fusion of immature secretory granules (ISGs) in PC12  cells (47), perhaps by  operating on a distinct set of SNAREs. Syt IV was also reported to play a  positive role in secretion from glial cells  (48).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37331</offset><text>Syt IV (29) and syt X  (49) are of particular  interest because their expression levels are induced by activity.  Interestingly, these two isoforms had opposite effects in the in  vitro fusion assay; syt IV inhibited SNARE-catalyzed fusion, whereas syt  X stimulated fusion (Figs. 2  and 3). These two isoforms  might be expressed in distinct regions of the brain. For example, in  situ hybridization experiments in mouse brain have shown that the syt IV  and X mRNA signals are very strong in the hippocampus and dentate gyrus,  respectively, but show little overlap within these regions (Allen Brain  Atlas). On the other hand, the syt I mRNA signal overlaps significantly with  both the syt IV and syt X mRNA signals. A detailed analysis of the tissue  distribution and subcellular localization of syt IV and X will provide insight  into why these two activity-induced isoforms have such different effects on  fusion mediated by neuronal SNARE proteins. One possibility is that syt X is  preferentially expressed in inhibitory neurons and facilitates inhibitory  synaptic transmission. In this scenario, up-regulation of syt X could serve to  dampen overactive neuronal circuits. Finally, it was reported that syt XII was  expressed on synaptic vesicles but failed to co-immunoprecipitate with  neuronal t-SNAREs (50). In  contrast, our co-flotation assays clearly demonstrate significant levels of  Ca2+-independent binding of syt XII to membrane-embedded t-SNAREs  (Fig. 4). Failure to detect  binding by Maximov et al.  (50) could be because of  differences in experimental conditions; i.e. using purified  components as opposed to co-immunoprecipitation from brain extracts where the  low abundance of syt XII might fall below the limits of detection. If syt I  and XII are indeed expressed on the same synaptic vesicles at similar levels,  our results indicate that syt XII might not be able to modulate the function  of syt I during synaptic transmission.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39296</offset><text>In conclusion, we have shown that the ability of syts to mediate  Ca2+-triggered membrane fusion is strictly related to their  abilities to engage PS and t-SNAREs in a Ca2+-dependent manner. We  also identified a subset of inhibitory syts that antagonized syt I function  during fusion by competing for syt SNARE interactions, further  establishing t-SNAREs as critical syt effectors. Finally, we further confirm  that syt I is selective for certain SNARE pairs over others  (Fig. 7 and Refs.  16,  43), supporting the hypothesis  that during intracellular membrane transport and exocytosis, the action of  syts on specific t-SNAREs might contribute to the specificity of  SNARE-mediated membrane fusion events.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40008</offset><text>Whether the syt isoforms that are inhibitory in our fusion assay screen  (using neuronal SNAREs) stimulate fusion mediated by other SNARE pairs is an  interesting question that remains to be addressed. Elucidation of the  expression pattern and subcellular localization of each isoform of syt is  needed to determine which t-SNAREs a given syt isoform will encounter in  vivo.</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Niemann, H., Blasi, J., and Jahn, R. ()     -185</infon><infon key="fpage">179</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14731646</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>40385</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jahn, R., and Scheller, R. H. ()    -643</infon><infon key="fpage">631</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16912714</infon><infon key="source">Nat.  Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40386</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Weber, T., Zemelman, B. V., McNew, J. A., Westermann, B., Gmachl,  M., Parlati, F., Sollner, T. H., and Rothman, J. E. ()     -772</infon><infon key="fpage">759</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9529252</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>40387</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Augustine, G. J. ()    -326</infon><infon key="fpage">320</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11399430</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin.  Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>40388</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Koh, T. W., and Bellen, H. J. ()    -422</infon><infon key="fpage">413</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12900172</infon><infon key="source">Trends  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>40389</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chapman, E. R. ()    -641</infon><infon key="fpage">615</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18275379</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev.  Biochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">77</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>40390</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Matthew, W. D., Tsavaler, L., and Reichardt, L. F.  ()    -269</infon><infon key="fpage">257</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7298720</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">1981</infon><offset>40391</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Perin, M. S., Fried, V. A., Mignery, G. A., Jahn, R., and Sudhof,  T. C. ()     -263</infon><infon key="fpage">260</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2333096</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">345</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>40392</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chapman, E. R., and Davis, A. F. ()    -14001</infon><infon key="fpage">13995</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9593749</infon><infon key="source">J.  Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">273</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>40393</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Davis, A. F., Bai, J., Fasshauer, D., Wolowick, M. J., Lewis, J.  L., and Chapman, E. R. ()    -376</infon><infon key="fpage">363</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10571230</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>40394</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hui, E., Bai, J., and Chapman, E. R. ()     -1777</infon><infon key="fpage">1767</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16782782</infon><infon key="source">Biophys. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40395</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Martens, S., Kozlov, M. M., and McMahon, H. T. ()     -1208</infon><infon key="fpage">1205</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17478680</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">316</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>40396</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bennett, M. K., Calakos, N., and Scheller, R. H.  ()     -259</infon><infon key="fpage">255</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1321498</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">257</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>40397</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Schiavo, G., Stenbeck, G., Rothman, J. E., and Sollner, T. H.  ()     -1001</infon><infon key="fpage">997</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9023371</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">94</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>40398</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bai, J., Wang, C. T., Richards, D. A., Jackson, M. B., and Chapman,  E. R. ()    -942</infon><infon key="fpage">929</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15046725</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">41</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40399</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bhalla, A., Chicka, M. C., Tucker, W. C., and Chapman, E. R.  ()    -330</infon><infon key="fpage">323</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16565726</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40400</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Earles, C. A., Bai, J., Wang, P., and Chapman, E. R.  ()     -1123</infon><infon key="fpage">1117</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11551981</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">154</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>40401</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhang, X., Kim-Miller, M. J., Fukuda, M., Kowalchyk, J. A., and  Martin, T. F. ()    -611</infon><infon key="fpage">599</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12062043</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">34</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>40402</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tucker, W. C., Edwardson, J. M., Bai, J., Kim, H. J., Martin, T.  F., and Chapman, E. R. ()    -209</infon><infon key="fpage">199</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12860971</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">162</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>40403</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shin, O. H., Rizo, J., and Sudhof, T. C. ()     -656</infon><infon key="fpage">649</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12055633</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>40404</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shin, O. H., Rhee, J. S., Tang, J., Sugita, S., Rosenmund, C., and  Sudhof, T. C. ()    -108</infon><infon key="fpage">99</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12526776</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">37</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>40405</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shin, O. H., Maximov, A., Lim, B. K., Rizo, J., and Sudhof, T. C.  ()     -2559</infon><infon key="fpage">2554</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14983047</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40406</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Xu, J., Mashimo, T., and Sudhof, T. C. ()     -581</infon><infon key="fpage">567</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17521570</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">54</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>40407</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tucker, W. C., Weber, T., and Chapman, E. R. ()     -438</infon><infon key="fpage">435</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15044754</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">304</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40408</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bhalla, A., Tucker, W. T., and Chapman, E. R. ()     -4764</infon><infon key="fpage">4755</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16093350</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Biol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>40409</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Craxton, M. ()    </infon><infon key="fpage">259</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17672888</infon><infon key="source">BMC  Genomics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>40410</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rickman, C., Craxton, M., Osborne, S., and Davletov, B.  ()     -686</infon><infon key="fpage">681</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14713287</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">378</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40411</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hui, E., Bai, J., Wang, P., Sugimori, M., Llinas, R. R., and  Chapman, E. R. ()    -5214</infon><infon key="fpage">5210</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15793006</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">102</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>40412</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Vician, L., Lim, I. K., Ferguson, G., Tocco, G., Baudry, M., and  Herschman, H. R. ()    -2168</infon><infon key="fpage">2164</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7892240</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>40413</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chapman, E. R., Desai, R. C., Davis, A. F., and Tornehl, C. K.  ()     -32972</infon><infon key="fpage">32966</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9830048</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">273</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>40414</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wang, C. T., Lu, J. C., Bai, J., Chang, P. Y., Martin, T. F.,  Chapman, E. R., and Jackson, M. B. ()     -947</infon><infon key="fpage">943</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12931189</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">424</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>40415</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Machado, H. B., Liu, W., Vician, L. J., and Herschman, H. R.  ()    -341</infon><infon key="fpage">334</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15079862</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci. Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">76</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40416</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wang, C. T., Grishanin, R., Earles, C. A., Chang, P. Y., Martin, T.  F., Chapman, E. R., and Jackson, M. B. ()     -1115</infon><infon key="fpage">1111</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11691996</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">294</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>40417</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Parlati, F., Weber, T., McNew, J. A., Westermann, B., Sollner, T.  H., and Rothman, J. E. ()    -12570</infon><infon key="fpage">12565</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10535962</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.  U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">96</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>40418</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Perin, M. S., Brose, N., Jahn, R., and Sudhof, T. C.  ()     -629</infon><infon key="fpage">623</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1985919</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">266</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>40419</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sutton, R. B., Davletov, B. A., Berghuis, A. M., Sudhof, T. C., and  Sprang, S. R. ()    -938</infon><infon key="fpage">929</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7697723</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">80</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>40420</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sutton, R. B., Ernst, J. A., and Brunger, A. T. ()     -598</infon><infon key="fpage">589</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10545502</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">147</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>40421</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nalefski, E. A., Wisner, M. A., Chen, J. Z., Sprang, S. R., Fukuda,  M., Mikoshiba, K., and Falke, J. J. ()     -3100</infon><infon key="fpage">3089</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11258923</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">40</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>40422</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Craxton, M. ()    </infon><infon key="fpage">43</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15238157</infon><infon key="source">BMC  Genomics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40423</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bock, J. B., Matern, H. T., Peden, A. A., and Scheller, R. H.  ()     -841</infon><infon key="fpage">839</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11237004</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">409</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>40424</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rothman, J. E. ()    -63</infon><infon key="fpage">55</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7969419</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">372</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>40425</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bonifacino, J. S., and Glick, B. S. ()     -166</infon><infon key="fpage">153</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14744428</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">116</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40426</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Stein, A., Radhakrishnan, A., Riedel, D., Fasshauer, D., and Jahn,  R. ()    -911</infon><infon key="fpage">904</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17891149</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>40427</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pang, Z. P., Melicoff, E., Padgett, D., Liu, Y., Teich, A. F.,  Dickey, B. F., Lin, W., Adachi, R., and Sudhof, T. C. ()     -13504</infon><infon key="fpage">13493</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17192432</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40428</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pang, Z. P., Sun, J., Rizo, J., Maximov, A., and Sudhof, T. C.  ()     -2050</infon><infon key="fpage">2039</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16642042</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">25</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40429</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nagy, G., Kim, J. H., Pang, Z. P., Matti, U., Rettig, J., Sudhof,  T. C., and Sorensen, J. B. ()    -643</infon><infon key="fpage">632</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16407561</infon><infon key="source">J.  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40430</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ahras, M., Otto, G. P., and Tooze, S. A. ()     -251</infon><infon key="fpage">241</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16618809</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">173</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>40431</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhang, Q., Fukuda, M., Van Bockstaele, E., Pascual, O., and Haydon,  P. G. ()    -9446</infon><infon key="fpage">9441</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15197251</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>40432</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Babity, J. M., Armstrong, J. N., Plumier, J. C., Currie, R. W., and  Robertson, H. A. ()    -2641</infon><infon key="fpage">2638</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9122248</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">94</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>40433</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Maximov, A., Shin, O. H., Liu, X., and Sudhof, T. C.  ()     -124</infon><infon key="fpage">113</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17190793</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">176</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>40434</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chapman, E. R. ()    -508</infon><infon key="fpage">498</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12094216</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>40435</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>40436</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: SNARE, soluble NSF  (N-ethylmaleimide-sensitive factor) attachment receptor; max FI,  maximum fluorescence intensity; PE, 1-palmitoyl, 2-oleoyl  phosphatidylethanolamine; PC, 1-palmitoyl, 2-oleoyl phosphatidylcholine; PS,  1,2-dioleoyl phosphatidylserine; syb, synaptobrevin; syt, synaptotagmin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>40760</offset><text>A. Bhalla, unpublished data.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>40789</offset><text>C. Dean, H. Liu, F. M. Dunning, P. Y. Chang, M. B. Jackson, and E. R.  Chapman, submitted manuscript.</text></passage></document></collection>
