<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>18723513</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M802475200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2570879</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">18723513</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">29424</infon><infon key="fpage">29424</infon><infon key="issue">43</infon><infon key="lpage">29432</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ang;given-names:Xiaolu L.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Seeburg;given-names:Daniel P.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sheng;given-names:Morgan</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Harper;given-names:J. Wade</infon><infon key="p">Author's Choice:Final version full access.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Regulation of Postsynaptic RapGAP SPAR by Polo-like Kinase 2 and the  SCFbeta-TRCP Ubiquitin Ligase in Hippocampal  Neurons*S</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>126</offset><text>The ubiquitin-proteasome pathway (UPP) regulates synaptic function, but  little is known about specific UPP targets and mechanisms in mammalian  synapses. We report here that the SCFbeta-TRCP complex, a  multisubunit E3 ubiquitin ligase, targets the postsynaptic spine-associated  Rap GTPase activating protein (SPAR) for degradation in neurons. SPAR  degradation by SCFbeta-TRCP depended on the activity-inducible  protein kinase Polo-like kinase 2 (Plk2). In the presence of Plk2, SPAR  physically associated with the SCFbeta-TRCP complex through a  canonical phosphodegron. In hippocampal neurons, disruption of the  SCFbeta-TRCP complex by overexpression of dominant interfering  beta-TRCP or Cul1 constructs prevented Plk2-dependent degradation of SPAR.  Our results identify a specific E3 ubiquitin ligase that mediates degradation  of a key postsynaptic regulator of synaptic morphology and function.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1034</offset><text>Dendritic spines are tiny, actin-rich, dynamic protrusions radiating from  the dendritic shaft of principal neurons and comprise the postsynaptic  compartment of most glutamatergic synapses of the mammalian brain. The size  and morphology of dendritic spines are correlated with their function. Thus,  large mushroom-shaped spines tend to be more stable than small thin spines,  contain more alpha-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methylisoxazole-4-proprionic acid  receptors, and mediate stronger synaptic connections  (1,  2). The morphology of spines,  which changes during development and in response to synaptic activity, is  influenced by multiple signaling pathways that emanate from postsynaptic  glutamate receptors and act upon the actin cytoskeleton and associated  proteins in the postsynaptic density  (PSD)5  (2-4).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1849</offset><text>SPAR (spine-associated Rap GTPase activating protein (GAP)) is a PSD  protein that regulates spine morphogenesis and forms a complex with the  scaffold protein PSD-95 and N-methyl-d-aspartate-type  glutamate receptors (5).  Overexpression of SPAR results in enlargement of spine heads, an effect  dependent upon the ability of SPAR to rearrange actin and function as a  RapGAP. In contrast, dominant-negative SPAR produces long and thin spines  (5). SPAR, in turn, is  regulated by polo-like kinase 2 (Plk2; also known as serum-inducible  serine/threonine kinase (SNK))  (6). Synaptic activity induces  Plk2 expression  (6-8),  leading to degradation of SPAR, a mechanism recently shown to be critical in  activity-dependent synaptic scaling (a principal form of homeostatic  plasticity) (9,  43).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2647</offset><text>SPAR turnover depends upon the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway (UPP) since  ubiquitinated SPAR accumulates in the presence of active Plk2 when proteasomes  are inhibited (6). This  necessitates the involvement of at least one E3 ubiquitin (Ub) ligase  targeting SPAR. More generally, the UPP is known to play an important role in  the activity-dependent turnover of several proteins in the PSD  (10), a process that likely  involves activity-driven redistribution of proteasomes into spines  (11). However, as is the case  for many neuronal processes in which the UPP has been implicated, the  molecular and regulatory components upstream of the proteasome responsible for  targeting the ubiquitination of SPAR and other PSD proteins are unknown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3391</offset><text>Skp1/Cul1/F-box protein (SCF) complexes are one of the best understood E3  Ub-ligases with regard to mechanism of substrate recognition  (12,  13). By recruiting substrates  to the SCF complex, F-box proteins dramatically increase the specificity and  rate of ubiquitin transfer to substrates. The F-box protein beta-TRCP has  been shown to target critical signaling proteins for degradation, including  IkappaBalpha, beta-catenin, and Cdc25A  (14-18).  Its function in neurons, however, has remained unexplored. Here, we  identifybeta-TRCP as the F-box protein that targets Plk2-phosphorylated SPAR  for degradation in neurons. Biochemical studies revealed that SPAR interacted  with the SCFbeta-TRCP complex through a canonical beta-TRCP  phosphodegron. Induction of Plk2 activity led to SPAR turnover, and this was  prevented by dominant negative disruption of the SCFbeta-TRCP  complex or point mutations in the phosphodegron of SPAR preventing SPAR from  interacting with beta-TRCP.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>4379</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4403</offset><text>DNA Plasmids:Expression plasmids expressing cDNA with a CMV  promoter for myc-SPAR, HA-Plk2, and HA-Plk2K108M were previously  described (6).  pCMV-HA-Plk2D201A was created from pCMV-HA-Plk2 using PCR-based  mutagenesis. cDNA for full-length SPAR as well as SPAR fragments were  amplified from pGW1-myc-SPAR  (5) and cloned into pENTR-6,  compatible with the GATEway cloning system (Invitrogen). These were used for  in vitro LR clonase reactions into pDEST-53 (for GFP-SPAR) or  pDEST-N-myc (for myc-SPAR fragments). Point mutations in the beta-TRCP  phosphodegron were generated by PCR-based mutagenesis using pCMV-myc-SPAR or  pDEST-myc-Act2 as templates. pCMV-myc-CKIepsilon and pCMV-GSK3beta were  previously described (19).  F-box proteins previously cloned from cDNA pools  (14) were re-cloned into  pENTR-6, and in vitro LR clonase reactions were performed with  pDEST-27 to generate GST-fused F-box proteins. DNCul1 (residues  1-452) was previously described  (14); DNCul3 and  DNCul4 were prepared by cloning sequences encoding residues 1-418  of Cul3 and 1-440 of Cul4A into pcDNA3 (Invitrogen), respectively.  beta-TRCP1DeltaF, Fbw7DeltaF, and Skp2DeltaF plasmids were previously  described (14,  20,  21), and beta-TRCP2DeltaF  was a gift from N. Khidekel (MIT). pRetroSuper (pRS)-shbeta-TRCP and control  shGFP plasmids were previously published  (14).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5770</offset><text>HEK293T Transfections, Binding, Abundance, and Turnover  Assays:HEK293T cells were grown in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's  medium + 10% serum and seeded (1 x 106 cells/well of a 6-well  dish) 16 h before transfection with Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Cells  were typically harvested ~24-30 h post-transfection, except for RNAi  experiments where cells were harvested 96 h post-transfection after a 48-h  selection with puromycin (1 mug/ml) to enrich for a transfected population.  Treatment of transfected cells with cycloheximide (25 mug/ml) began 96 h  post-transfection.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6346</offset><text>For assays examining myc-SPAR abundance and turnover, cell pellets were  lysed in 50 mm Tris, pH 7.5, 150 mm NaCl, 1  mm EDTA, 0.5% deoxycholate, 1% Nonidet P-40, 0.1% SDS, and cleared  lysates were resolved on 4-12% gradient Tris-glycine SDS-PAGE gels. Resolved  proteins were then transferred onto nitrocellulose (250 mA, 2 h) and  immunoblotted with c-Myc 9E10 (sc-40, Santa-Cruz), HA F-7 (sc-7392, Santa  Cruz), Cdk2 M2 (sc-163, Santa Cruz), beta-TRCP1 (Cell Signaling), Cul1  (71-8700, Invitrogen/Zymed Laboratories Inc.), and Cdc25A Ab-3 (MS-640-P0,  NeoMarkers), as indicated. Promega horseradish peroxidase-conjugate anti-mouse  IgG (W402B) and anti-rabbit IgG (W401B) were used for secondary detection.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7058</offset><text>For single-cell immunofluorescence RNAi experiments, HEK293T cells were  seeded onto 18-mm glass coverslips coated with poly-d-lysine (30  mug/ml) and laminin (2 mug/ml) and transfected at 20-30% confluency using  calcium phosphate. Cells were fixed 96 h post-transfection for 10 min at room  temperature using 4% paraformaldehyde and 4% sucrose in phosphate-buffered  saline, and the GFP-SPAR signal was amplified using anti-GFP (A-11122,  Invitrogen) at 1:1000 in GDB buffer (1% gelatin, 5% Triton X-100, 50  mm phosphate buffer, pH 7.4, 2 m NaCl)  (6).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7614</offset><text>Binding and ubiquitination detection assays were performed with cleared  whole cell lysates from transfected HEK293T cells in 50 mm Tris, pH  7.5, 150 mm NaCl, 1 mm EDTA, 0.5% deoxycholate, and 1%  Nonidet P-40. In the case of ubiquitination detection assays, cells were  treated with 25 mum MG-132 before harvesting, and 10  mm N-ethylmaleimide was added to the lysis buffer.  GSH-Sepharose or c-Myc 9E10-agarose beads (10 mul per condition) were  pre-washed in lysis buffer and incubated with 400 mug of lysate for 2 h at 4   C while rocking. Beads were then washed 3-4 times in lysis buffer, and  bound protein was eluded in 2x Laemmli protein loading buffer containing  SDS. Both GSH-bound samples and crude extract were resolved on 4-12% gradient  SDS-PAGE gels. Myc-bound samples were resolved on 6% Tris-Glycine SDS-PAGE  gels. Samples were then transferred from the SDS-PAGE onto nitrocellulose and  immunoblotted with anti-Myc, anti-HA, anti-FLAG (F3165, Sigma), or anti-GST  (26H1, Cell Signaling), as indicated.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8637</offset><text>Neuron Cultures and Immunostaining:Medium-density  dissociated hippocampal cultures were prepared and cultured from E19 Long  Evans rat hippocampi as previously described  (5). Neurons were transfected  at DIV16, &quot;super-infected&quot; at DIV18, and fixed ~18 h  post-infection (DIV19) in 1% paraformaldehyde for 2 min at room temperature  followed by -20  C methanol for 10 min. Immunostaining was performed in  GDB buffer (6) using rabbit  SPAR polyclonal antibodies (5)  and anti-FLAG M2 (Sigma).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9131</offset><text>Microscopy and Quantification:Fixed neurons and HEK293T  cells were imaged with an LSM510 confocal system (Zeiss). A 40x oil  immersion lens was used for confocal microscopy, and each image was comprised  of 0.5-mum z-stacks projected into a single plane. SPAR immunostaining  analysis was performed with MetaMorph Software and carried out blinded with  respect to the experimental conditions. Quantification of SPAR puncta involved  subjecting images stained for endogenous SPAR to threshold and was carried out  from somatic and proximal dendritic regions from transfected, infected, or  transfected plus superinfected cells. All SPAR intensity measurements  represent integrated SPAR immunostaining intensity per area and are normalized  to neighboring uninfected and untransfected cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9923</offset><text>Statistical Analysis:Statistical Methods are described in  the figures legends.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>10003</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10011</offset><text>Plk2-dependent SPAR Degradation Requires a Cul1-based E3  Ub-ligase:SPAR turnover in neurons is controlled through the UPP in  a manner that requires active Plk2 protein kinase  (6). Such regulation is  reminiscent of the mechanism employed by most SCF E3 Ub-ligases, where  substrate recognition depends upon upstream kinase signaling cascades. A  central subunit of the SCF complex is the Cul1 scaffold protein. To explore  the idea that SPAR turnover is regulated by an SCF E3 Ub-ligase, we made use  of a previously reported dominant-negative version of Cul1  (DNCul1). This C-terminal-truncated protein binds substrates but  fails to associate with ubiquitin-charged E2 ubiquitin conjugating enzymes,  thereby preventing substrate turnover  (14,  19,  22).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>10773</offset><text>Plk2-induced SPAR degradation requires a Cul1-based E3 Ubligase.  A-C, dominant negative Cul1 constructs block Plk2-dependent loss of  SPAR in hippocampal neurons. Dissociated rat hippocampal neurons (DIV16) were  transfected with dominant negative Cullin plasmids (B and C)  or a control plasmid (A) and super-infected 2 days later with  FLAG-tagged Plk2 driven by Sindbis virus (Sin-Plk2). Neurons were  fixed ~18 h post-infection and immunostained for endogenous SPAR and  infected Plk2. Transfected cells were identified during image acquisition by  the presence of a co-transfected &quot;fill&quot; protein (GFP, seen in the  first column of images). SPAR (green) and Plk2 (red) were  pseudo-colored for illustrative purposes after image analysis. Arrows  point to cells that are both transfected and infected; arrowheads  point to cells that are infected only. Yellow indicates the presence  of both SPAR and Plk2 staining. D and E, quantification of  SPAR immunostaining in somatic and proximal dendritic regions as integrated  immunofluorescence intensity per area in cells transfected with indicated  plasmids and/or infected with Plk2 Sindbis virus (Sin-Plk2),  normalized to nearby untransfected (untr) cells. Values represent the  mean +- S.E., n &gt; 17 cells for all conditions,  ***, p &lt; 0.001, Mann-Whitney test (E).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12093</offset><text>Cultured hippocampal neurons (16 days in vitro (DIV16)) were  transfected with DNCul1 and then super-infected 2 days later with  Sindbis virus driving expression of FLAG-tagged Plk2 for ~18 h to promote  degradation of endogenous SPAR  (6). We infected at a titer  that resulted in ~10% infection rate of cells already transfected with  DNCul1 (Fig. 1,  A-C). The option of co-transfecting plasmids driving Plk2  expression was precluded by the low Plk2 expression achievable using this  method.6</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12590</offset><text>In the absence of Plk2 infection, transfection of control empty vector  (pcDNA3.1) or a control dominant-negative Cullin 3 (DNCul3), which  disrupts structurally related but functionally distinct Cul3-based complexes  (23), had no effect on  endogenous SPAR levels relative to nearby untransfected and uninfected cells  as assessed by quantitative immunostaining  (Fig. 1, A and  C, quantified in D). Uninfected cells  overexpressing DNCul1 displayed a trend toward increased SPAR  levels compared with nearby untransfected cells, but did not reach statistical  significance (p = 0.13; Fig.  1B, quantified in D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13204</offset><text>In Plk2-infected but otherwise untransfected neurons, endogenous SPAR  levels were close to undetectable (Fig. 1,  A-C, arrowheads; quantified in E), in  agreement with our previous findings  (6). In Plk2-infected cells  that had been previously transfected with control empty vector or  DNCul3, SPAR levels fell to the same extent as in cells only  infected with Plk2 (Fig. 1, A and  C, compare SPAR staining in cells marked by  arrowheads (infected) and arrows (transfected and infected);  quantified in E). However, in cells transfected with  DNCul1, infection with Plk2 Sindbis virus failed to reduce SPAR  levels (Fig. 1B,  notice the yellow color in cells marked by arrows,  indicating the presence of both SPAR (green) and Plk2 (red);  quantified in E). Thus, Plk2-driven SPAR degradation in neurons  depended upon a Cul1-based SCF complex but not any of the structurally related  Cul3-based Ub-ligases.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14115</offset><text>SPAR Physically Associates with the  SCFbeta-TRCP Complex:To further  explore the idea that SPAR turnover is regulated by an SCF E3 Ub-ligase, we  established a system in cultured HEK293T cells that recapitulates  Plk2-dependent SPAR degradation. This system facilitated biochemical studies  that were otherwise limited by the physical properties of dendritic spines and  allowed the use of molecular reagents previously developed for study of the  human SCF pathway (24). We  found that expression of SPAR alone (as an Myc-tagged fusion protein) led to  its accumulation in HEK293T cells (Fig.  2A, lane 3). In contrast, co-expression with  Plk2 (but not a catalytically inactive mutant Plk2D201A) promoted  the degradation of myc-SPAR (Fig. 2,  A, lane 2 compared with lanes 4-6, and  B, lanes 1 and 2). Co-expression of SPAR with wild type Plk2  correlated with the appearance of a slower mobility form of SPAR (presumably  phosphorylated) that is sensitive to Plk2-induced degradation  (Fig. 2A,  myc-SPAR-P; see also Fig. 2,  B and C). Our recapitulation of Plk2-dependent  SPAR turnover in HEK293T cells provides a convenient system in which to search  for components of the Plk2-dependent degradation pathway.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15332</offset><text>Consistent with the idea that SPAR is a target of one of the SCF complexes,  overexpression of dominant-negative Cul1 (DNCul1) in HEK293T  stabilized myc-SPAR despite cotransfection of active Plk2  (Fig. 2B, lane  3), in agreement with our findings in neurons (see  Fig. 1, B and  E). Moreover, these cells accumulated the slower  migrating form of myc-SPAR that presumably corresponds to phosphorylated SPAR.  In contrast, a dominant-negative form of the related Cullin4  (DNCul4) had no effect on SPAR turnover (lane 4),  indicating that the effect of DNCul1 was specific.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15907</offset><text>F-box proteins serve as substrate receptors in Cul1-based E3s. To uncover  candidate F-box proteins for SPAR, we performed a cell-based interaction  screen in HEK293T cells between SPAR and a panel of co-expressed GST-tagged  F-box proteins. Potential complexes between SPAR and GST-tagged F-box proteins  were isolated by incubating cell lysates with GSH-Sepharose beads. Previous  studies had indicated that the interaction of F-box proteins with substrates  can be detected in tissue culture cells that co-express the F-box protein and  substrate in the presence of DNCul1, which blocks substrate  degradation (14,  19). Among a panel of F-box  proteins individually co-transfected with myc-SPAR and HA-Plk2, we identified  an interaction between myc-SPAR and both GST-beta-TRCP1 and GST-beta-TRCP2  (Fig. 2C, lanes  3 and 4). Our ability to assay for endogenous interactions was  precluded by the unavailability of suitable antibodies for  immunoprecipitation. Although produced from different genes, beta-TRCP1 and  beta-TRCP2 are ~85% identical and are believed to have largely redundant  functions (25). Importantly,  the binding of beta-TRCP1 and beta-TRCP2 to myc-SPAR required  co-transfection of active (wild type (WT)) Plk2 and was undetectable in the  presence of catalytically defective Plk2K108M  (Fig. 2C, lanes  5 and 6). Together with the Plk2-dependent slower gel mobility  of SPAR (Fig. 2, A-C),  this suggests that SPAR associates with beta-TRCP in a  phosphorylation-dependent manner, as is the case for all other beta-TRCP  substrates identified to date  (13). SPAR did not associate  with any of 16 other F-box proteins tested  (Fig. 2C, lanes  7-22), including 5 F-box proteins, which like beta-TRCP, bind  substrates through their WD40 repeats (Fig.  2C, lanes 7-11). This indicates a high degree of  specificity in the interaction between SPAR and beta-TRCP.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>17793</offset><text>SPAR physically associates with the  SCFbeta-TRCP complex. A,  Plk2-dependent loss of SPAR. HEK293T cells were transfected with 1 mug of  pCMV-HA-Plk2 (lane 1), 1 mug of pCMV-myc-SPAR (lane 3), or  1 mug of pCMV-myc-SPAR together with either 1 mug of catalytically  inactive pCMV-HA-Plk2D201A (lane 2) or increasing amounts  of pCMV-HA-Plk2WT (0.3, 1, or 2 mug) (lanes 4-6). The  total amount of transfected DNA was kept constant among all conditions with  use of empty vector. Whole cell lysates were immunoblotted with Myc antibody  to assess myc-SPAR levels. B, dominant negative versions of Cul1 and  beta-TRCP stabilize SPAR. pCMV-myc-SPAR (0.5 mug) and  pCMV-HA-Plk2D201A/WT (1 mug) (catalytically inactive, lane  1; wild type, lanes 2-9) were co-expressed in HEK293T cells with  2.5 mug of either empty vector, dominant negative Cullins, or dominant  negative F-box proteins. Changes in the abundance of myc-SPAR were determined  by immunoblotting with anti-Myc antibody. C, F-box protein  interaction screen. pCMV-myc-SPAR (0.6 mug), pCMV-HA-Plk2WT/K108M  (0.6 mug), and pCMV-DNCul1 (2 mug) were co-expressed as shown  with pCMV-GST (lane 2) or the indicated F-box proteins as GST fusions  (0.6 mug) (lanes 3-22) in HEK293T cells seeded in 6-well plates.  After 24 h, cell extracts were used for GSH-Sepharose pull-down assays, and  proteins were immunoblotted with anti-GST and anti-Myc antibodies. Crude  lysates were blotted as an input control. D, coimmunoprecipitation of  SPAR and Plk2. Extracts of HEK293T cells transfected with  pCMV-DNCul1 and pCMV-myc-SPAR (lane 1), pCMV-HA-Plk2  (lane 2), or both (lane 3) were immunoprecipitated using  anti-Myc or anti-HA antibodies as indicated. E, formation of a  SPAR Plk2 beta-TRCP Cul1 complex with active Plk2.  Lysates from cells transfected with pCMV-myc-SPAR (0.5 mug),  pCMV-HA-Plk2WT/D201A (0.5 mug), pCMV-GST-beta-TRCP (0.5 mug),  and pCMV-FLAG-Cul11-452 (2 mug), as indicated, were incubated  with GSH-Sepharose and immunoblotted with anti-Myc, anti-HA, anti-GST, and  anti-FLAG antibodies as shown. Lanes 1-4 show lysates (6% of input of  the GSH-Sepharose binding reactions).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19939</offset><text>Consistent with previous studies that showed interaction between Plk2 and  SPAR (6), we found that Plk2  associated with SPAR in a coimmunoprecipitation assay upon co-expression of  DNCul1 (Fig.  2D), further validating our heterologous cell system.  Interestingly, we also discovered that the associations of Plk2 and  beta-TRCP with SPAR were not mutually exclusive, as we were able to detect a  ternary interaction with Plk2 that was not precluded by the beta-TRCP-SPAR  interaction (Fig. 2E,  lanes 6 and 8). GST-beta-TRCP1 (and GST-beta-TRCP2)  associated with SPAR, Plk2, and the N terminus of Cullin 1  (Cul11-452/DNCul1), whereas catalytically inactive  Plk2D201A did not support assembly of the full complex  (Fig. 2E, lanes  5-8). Moreover, the Plk2-dependent slower mobility form of SPAR was  enriched in the complex compared with the faster mobility form of SPAR  (Fig. 2E, compare  lanes 2 and 4 with 6 and 8).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>20863</offset><text>SCFbeta-TRCP regulates Plk2-dependent  SPAR abundance, turnover, and promotes its ubiquitination. A and  B, depletion of beta-TRCP by RNAi protects GFP-SPAR from  degradation in individual HEK293T cells. The indicated plasmids were  transfected with pCMV-RFP as a co-transfection marker into HEK293T cells.  After 96 h, cells were fixed and imaged for GFP-SPAR and RFP expression  (A) and quantified as the percentage of RFP expressing cells that  also expressed GFP-SPAR (B). Values represent the mean +- S.E.  from three independent experiments, derived from analysis of 400 cells per  experiment per condition (n = 1200 cells per condition).  **, p &lt; 0.01; NS, not significant; one-way  analysis of variance, compared with control condition  (pRSP+Plk2D/A). C and D, depletion of beta-TRCP  by RNAi stabilizes SPAR abundance and turnover in the presence of Plk2  activity. HEK293T cells were transfected with vectors expressing myc-SPAR (0.5  mug), WT, or catalytically inactive HA-Plk2 (D/A) (1 mug), and  the indicated shRNA vector carrying a puromycin resistance selection marker  (2.5 mug). 36 h post-transfection, cells were incubated with media  containing 1 mug/ml puromycin to enrich for shRNA expression. Extracts were  subsequently examined by immunoblotting 96 h post-transfection as indicated.  Endogenous Cdc25A was probed to control for successful knockdown of  beta-TRCP. In panel D, HEK293T cells were transfected in an  identical fashion to panel C, except that 24 h post-transfection the  transfected cells were split among 5 wells in puromycin-containing media.  After 48 h of puromycin selection, cells were treated with 25 mug/ml  cycloheximide (CHX) and harvested at the indicated times before  immunoblotting. E, expression of beta-TRCP promotes Plk2-mediated  SPAR ubiquitination. HEK293T cells were transfected with myc-SPAR (1 mug),  His-Ub (1 mug), HA-Plk2 (1.5 mug, wild type or D201A), and GST or  GST-beta-TRCP (4.5 mug). Twenty hours post-transfection cells were treated  with 25 mum MG-132 for 5 h and lysed in buffer containing 10  mm N-ethylmaleimide. Myc-SPAR was purified with c-Myc  9E10-agarose, resolved on 6% Tris-glycine SDS-PAGE gel, and immunoblotted  (IB) with anti-Myc antibodies. IP, immunoprecipitates.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23116</offset><text>SCFbeta-TRCP Regulates SPAR Abundance  and Turnover and Promotes Its Ubiquitination:To validate a role for  the SCFbeta-TRCP complex in Plk2-dependent SPAR turnover, we next  examined SPAR abundance in HEK293T cells after expression of dominant-negative  beta-TRCP (beta-TRCPDeltaF) (Fig.  2B). The DeltaF-box construct is unable to assemble  with Cul1 due to absence of the F-box motif, but it maintains its ability to  interact with substrates of both beta-TRCP1 and -2 and can thereby sequester  substrates and block their turnover  (14,  21,  24). Expression of  beta-TRCPDeltaF resulted in increased levels of SPAR, especially of the  slower migrating form of SPAR that is dependent upon Plk2 activity  (Fig. 2B, lane  5). In contrast, DeltaF-box dominant-negative versions of other F-box  proteins Fbw7alpha/beta/gamma (containing WD40 repeats) and Skp2  (containing leucine-rich repeats) failed to promote an increase in the steady  state abundance of SPAR (Fig.  2B, lanes 6-9).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24103</offset><text>To directly examine whether beta-TRCP proteins are required for  Plk2-dependent SPAR turnover, we took advantage of a shRNA vector  (shbeta-TRCP) that is capable of suppressing protein expression of both  human beta-TRCP1 and beta-TRCP2. This hairpin sequence and this particular  shRNA vector have been validated for numerous beta-TRCP substrates  (14,  19,  26). Cells were transfected  with expression constructs for GFP-SPAR and red fluorescent protein (RFP) to  mark transfected cells and simultaneously transfected with shbeta-TRCP or  control vector (pRSP) in the presence of active Plk2 or a catalytically  inactive version, Plk2D201A  (Fig. 3A). We  subsequently visualized cells for the presence of GFP-SPAR in RFP-positive  cells (Fig. 3A).  RFP-positive cells expressing Plk2, but not those expressing catalytically  inactive Plk2D201A, displayed very low levels of GFP-SPAR in the  presence of the control shRNA vector pRSP  (Fig. 3A, quantified  in B). In contrast, RFP-positive cells transfected with shbeta-TRCP  contained high levels of GFP-SPAR despite the co-transfection of active Plk2  (Fig. 3A, quantified  in B). Thus, depletion of beta-TRCP by RNAi substantially protected  GFP-SPAR from Plk2-dependent degradation. Immunoblotting of transfected cell  lysates confirmed that Plk2-induced degradation of myc-SPAR requires  beta-TRCP (Fig. 3C).  As expected, Plk2 promoted loss of myc-SPAR in cells expressing a control  shRNA that targets GFP (shGFP) (lanes 1 and 2). In contrast,  myc-SPAR was not efficiently degraded in cells depleted of beta-TRCP despite  the presence of active Plk2 (lane 4). Furthermore, depletion of  beta-TRCP led to accumulation of Cdc25A, a known target of  SCFbeta-TRCP used here as a positive control  (14,  18).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>25868</offset><text>A candidatebeta-TRCP phosphodegron in SPAR. A,  schematic representation of SPAR domains and SPAR fragments: actin-binding  domains (Act1 and Act2), RapGAP, PDZ, and guanylate kinase  binding (GKBD) domain. The candidate DSGIDT phosphodegron motif  (residues 1304-1309) identified in the Act2 domain of SPAR closely resembles  the consensus beta-TRCP phosphodegron (inset). Boundaries of  generated C-terminal fragments of SPAR are depicted; C-1, C-2, and Act2  fragments contain the putative phosphodegron motif, whereas C-3 does not.  B and C, SPAR fragments spanning the beta-TRCP  phosphodegron bind to beta-TRCP. HEK293T cells were transfected with vectors  expressing SPAR fragments C-1, C-2, C-3 (B) or Act2 (C) (0.6  mug) either alone or with pCMV-GST or pCMV-GST-beta-TRCP (0.6 mug). In  addition, pCMV-HA-Plk2WT/K108M (0.6 mug) and DNCul1 (2  mug) were co-transfected as indicated. After 24 h, cell extracts were used  for GSH-Sepharose pulldown assays, and proteins were immunoblotted with Myc  antibodies. Crude lysates were blotted as an input control. D and  E, phosphodegron-dependent binding to beta-TRCP. Constructs  expressing point mutations (S1305A, T1309A) in full-length SPAR (E)  and the Act2 fragment (D) (myc-SPARAA or  myc-Act2AA, 0.6 mug) were transfected into HEK293T cells along  with pCMV-HA-Plk2WT/D201A (0.6 mug), pCMV-DNCul1 (2  mug), and pCMV-GST or pCMV-GST-beta-TRCP (0.6 mug) as indicated. Cell  lysates were incubated with GSH-Sepharose and immunoblotted with Myc  antibodies. Crude extracts were resolved to control for input. Wild type  constructs expressing myc-SPAR and myc-Act2 were used for comparison as a  positive control for interaction with GST-beta-TRCP. F, SPAR  associates with endogenous SCFbeta-TRCP1 complex in the presence  of active Plk2 and dependent upon its phosphodegron. Constructs expressing  full-length myc-SPAR (WT or AA) were co-expressed in HEK293T cells  with active (WT) or catalytically inactive Plk2 (D201A). Before lysis and  immunoprecipitation with 9E10-agarose, cells were treated with proteasome  inhibitor MG-132 (25 mum) for 5 h. Proteins bound to 9E10-agarose  were analyzed via immunoblotting using Myc antibodies and antibodies that  recognized endogenous beta-TRCP1 and Cul1. Myc-SPAR-C3, a fragment of SPAR  that does not contain the phosphodegron served as a negative control, and  myc-Cdc25A, a known target of SCFbeta-TRCP1, served as a positive  control. G, phosphodegron-dependent degradation of SPAR by Plk2 and  beta-TRCP. Myc-SPARWT and myc-SPARAA abundance was compared by  immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies in HEK293T cells in the absence  and presence of pCMV-HA-Plk2 in the background of empty vector or  beta-TRCPDeltaF.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28597</offset><text>To directly examine whether beta-TRCP is required for SPAR turnover, we  performed a cycloheximide-chase experiment in cells expressing myc-SPAR and  Plk2 in the presence of shGFP or shbeta-TRCP  (Fig. 3D). Myc-SPAR  levels persisted after 45-60 min of cycloheximide treatment under conditions  of beta-TRCP depletion (shbeta-TRCP) but disappeared after the same time  period in control cells (shGFP) (Fig.  3D, lanes 7-8 compared with 3 and  4). Taken together, these data indicate that  SCFbeta-TRCP is critical for Plk2-dependent degradation of SPAR  in heterologous cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29174</offset><text>To explore whether the SCFbeta-TRCP complex promoted  ubiquitination of SPAR, we immunoprecipitated myc-SPAR from MG-132-treated  HEK293T cells and immunoblotted for modified myc-SPAR  (Fig. 3E). Expression  of active Plk2 resulted in detection of ubiquitinated SPAR, and the  ubiquitination reaction was further driven in cells by ectopic expression of  GST-beta-TRCP (lanes 2 and 3). Together, this suggests  that the Plk2-dependent turnover of myc-SPAR occurs through ubiquitination of  SPAR.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29670</offset><text>Plk2-dependent Recognition of SPAR by beta-TRCP Involves a  Canonical Phosphodegron:SPAR is a large protein of 1804 amino acids  containing two actin binding domains (Act1 and Act2), a RapGAP domain, a PDZ  domain, and a guanylate kinase binding domain (GKBD)  (Fig. 4A). Within the  Act2 domain, we identified a candidate beta-TRCP recognition motif (DSGIDT,  residues 1304-1309) based upon the consensus beta-TRCP recognition motif  found in many of its targets (DpSGPhiX(pS/T); Phi= hydrophobic  residue, X = any residue, pS or pS/T = phosphoserine or threonine)  (Fig. 4A). Initially,  we surveyed three fragments of SPAR spanning the C terminus (C-1, C-2, C-3,  Fig. 4A) for their  ability to interact with co-transfected GST-beta-TRCP1 in HEK293T cells in  the presence of Plk2 and DNCul1. Fragments C-1 and C-2 (which  contain the candidate phosphodegron) bound to GST-beta-TRCP, whereas the C-3  construct lacking the phosphodegron failed to do so  (Fig. 4B). N-terminal  SPAR fragments that lack the DSGIDT motif also could not bind to beta-TRCP  (data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>30744</offset><text>Regulation of SPAR degradation in hippocampal neurons through the  SCFbeta-TRCP complex. A-C,  dominant negative beta-TRCP constructs block Plk2-dependent loss of SPAR in  hippocampal neurons. As in Fig.  1, DIV16 dissociated rat hippocampal neurons were transfected with  dominant negative beta-TRCP plasmids (A and B) or control  SkpDeltaF plasmid (C) and superinfected 2 days later with  FLAG-tagged Plk2 driven by Sindbis virus (Sin-Plk2). Arrows  point to cells that are both transfected and infected; arrowheads  point to cells that are infected only. Yellow indicates the presence  of both SPAR and Plk2 staining. D and E, quantification of  SPAR immunostaining in somatic and proximal dendritic regions, as in  Fig. 1. Values represent the  mean +- S.E. n = 25-37 cells for all constructs in panel  D; *, p &lt; 0.05 indicates significant difference  from theoretical mean of 100%, Student's t test (D). For  panel E, n = 19-37 cells (infected only), n = 13-28 cells  (infected and transfected), ***, p &lt; 0.001, Mann  Whitney test.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31781</offset><text>A fourth fragment of SPAR spanning the Act2 domain was sufficient to  interact with beta-TRCP, and its association depended upon expression of  active Plk2 (Fig. 4C,  compare lanes 3 and 4 with 5 and 6).  Mutation of Ser-1305 and Thr-1309 to alanines within the Act2 domain fragment  alone (Act2AA) (Fig.  4D) or within full-length SPAR (SPARAA)  (Fig. 4E) resulted in  greatly diminished binding to beta-TRCP compared with wild type SPAR  constructs. Moreover, only in the presence of catalytically active Plk2 was  full-length SPAR able to associate with endogenous beta-TRCP and its  associated Cul1 protein (Fig.  4F, compare lanes 2 and 3).  Importantly, the C-3 fragment of SPAR that does not encompass the  phosphodegron as well as full-length SPAR that carries point mutations of  Ser-1305 and Thr-1309 did not support interaction with components of the  endogenous SCFbeta-TRCP complex  (Fig. 4F, lanes  1 and 4). If this DSGIDT motif in SPAR is important for SPAR  turnover, then mutation of this candidate phosphodegron should render SPAR  resistant to Plk2-mediated turnover. Indeed, Plk2 efficiently promoted  degradation of wild type SPAR but not the SPARAA mutant  (Fig. 4G, lanes  1-4). Importantly, the accumulation of SPARAA seen in the  presence of Plk2 was unchanged by the additional cotransfection of  beta-TRCPDeltaF (compare lanes 4 and 8), indicating that  the mutation is specifically protecting turnover via the  SCFbeta-TRCP pathway. We further noted that SPARAA  continued to migrate as multiple bands upon SDS-PAGE analysis of extracts from  cells expressing Plk2 (Fig.  4E, input lanes 1, 2, and 4,  Fig. 4G). This implies  that the mobility shift seen with Plk2 expression does not solely rely on  phosphorylation of residues Ser-1305 and Thr-1309.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33562</offset><text>SCFbeta-TRCP Controls SPAR Abundance  in Hippocampal Neurons:To investigate the role of the  SCFbeta-TRCP complex in post-mitotic neurons of the central  nervous system, we first examined whether beta-TRCP is present in the adult  rat brain. mRNAs encoding beta-TRCP1, beta-TRCP2, and Cul1 are all present  at high levels in rat brain, specifically in the CA1-CA3 regions of the  hippocampus, the dentate gyrus, and cerebral cortex (Allen Brain Atlas).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34015</offset><text>Does the SCFbeta-TRCP complex regulate turnover of SPAR in  neurons? Unlike for the human mRNAs, we have yet to identify an shRNA sequence  that can target both beta-TRCP1 and beta-TRCP2 transcripts efficiently in  rat neurons. Co-transfection of different shRNAs that individually target  beta-TRCP1 and beta-TRCP2 has not yielded satisfactory knockdown of both  proteins, possibly due to low efficiency of cotransfection of both shRNA  vectors in the same neuron. Therefore, we opted to disrupt endogenous  SCFbeta-TRCP function by overexpression of dominant-negative  beta-TRCP constructs beta-TRCP1DeltaF or beta-TRCP2DeltaF. As in  Fig. 1, DIV16 cultured  hippocampal neurons were transfected with either beta-TRCP1DeltaFor  beta-TRCP2DeltaF and then super-infected 2 days later with Sindbis virus  to drive expression of FLAG-tagged Plk2 and induce SPAR degradation  (Fig. 5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34898</offset><text>Transfection of control dominant-negative Skp2 F-box construct  (Skp2DeltaF) in the absence of Plk2 infection had no effect on endogenous  SPAR levels relative to nearby untransfected and uninfected cells  (Fig. 5C, quantified  in D). In contrast, uninfected cells overexpressing  beta-TRCP1DeltaF displayed higher levels of SPAR compared with nearby  untransfected cells (p &lt; 0.05,  Fig. 5D). In neurons  overexpressing beta-TRCP2DeltaF, SPAR levels trended upwards, but this did  not reach statistical significance (p = 0.11,  Fig. 5D). These  results suggest that there may be some SCFbeta-TRCP  complex-dependent turnover of endogenous SPAR in hippocampal neurons cultured  under basal conditions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35600</offset><text>As expected, endogenous SPAR levels were close to undetectable in  Plk2-infected neurons that were otherwise untransfected  (Fig. 5, A-C,  arrowheads, and E) as well as in Plk2-infected cells that  had been previously transfected with Skp2DeltaF  (Fig. 5C, compare SPAR  staining in cells marked by arrowheads (infected) and arrows  (transfected and infected); quantified in E). In contrast, cells  transfected with beta-TRCP1DeltaF or beta-TRCP2DeltaF showed no  reduction in SPAR levels after infection with Plk2 Sindbis virus  (Fig. 5, B and  C, quantified in E). These results are  consistent with disruption of the SCF complex through expression of  DNCul1, which also prevented Plk2-dependent loss of SPAR (see  Fig. 1), and together they  demonstrate that the SCFbeta-TRCP pathway is required for  Plk2-induced SPAR degradation in neurons.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36447</offset><text>Because changes in SPAR expression can affect spine morphology  (5) and synaptic strength  (43), we wondered if blocking  the SCFbeta-TRCP pathway might also affect these aspects of  neuronal function. Infection of DIV16 neurons with Plk2 led to a significant  decrease in the size and number of spines, consistent with previous results  (5). The additional  overexpression of beta-TRCPDeltaF in cells infected with Plk2, however,  did not prevent the decrease in size and number of spines (supplemental Fig.  S1, A-C). Similarly, blocking beta-TRCP function had no effect on  synaptic strength as assessed by recording of miniature excitatory  postsynaptic currents (mEPSCs) (supplemental Fig. S1, D and  E). These results are perhaps not surprising given that  SCFbeta-TRCP is likely to regulate additional synaptic substrates  besides SPAR. Although we have clearly established the  Plk2-SCFbeta-TRCP-SPAR degradative pathway, its function in  neurons remains to be resolved.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>37426</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37437</offset><text>The UPP has received increasing attention in neurobiology as an important  regulator of synapse development, synaptic transmission and plasticity, and  the dynamic turnover of PSD proteins  (27-31).  Aberrant UPP function has been implicated in the pathogenesis of certain  neurodegenerative disorders, e.g. Parkinson, Alzheimer, Huntington,  and prion diseases, and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis  (32,  33). To date most E3 substrate  pairs in neurobiology have been identified in Caenorhabditis elegans  and Drosophila melanogaster  (34-42),  and relatively little is known about the specific E3s that regulate synaptic  proteins in the mammalian brain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>38093</offset><text>In this study we have uncovered a role for the E3 Ub-ligase  SCFbeta-TRCP in the degradation of a key postsynaptic scaffolding  protein and enzyme (the RapGAP SPAR) that regulates the morphology of  dendritic spines and the strength of synaptic transmission in hippocampal  neurons (5,  43). Mammalian  SCFbeta-TRCP has been implicated in the ubiquitin-dependent  turnover of several cell cycle and other signaling proteins, including  IkappaBalpha, beta-catenin, Cdc25A, Emi1, and the Period protein  (14-17,  19). Moreover, it has been  connected to the differentiation of neural progenitors through its targeting  of REST transcription repressor  (44,  45). Although we have defined  the residues that are critical for SCFbeta-TRCP-mediated  degradation of SPAR, it is possible that SPAR degradation is also regulated by  additional E3s, possibly in response to other signals and involving different  determinants in the SPAR protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39031</offset><text>Previous studies have demonstrated that beta-TRCP interacts with its  substrates in a phosphorylation-dependent manner. The majority of beta-TRCP  substrates identified to date contain a DpSGPhiXpS sequence (where  pS is phosphoserine) that functions as a phosphodegron and directly binds to  the WD40 repeats of beta-TRCP  (46). A variety of kinases  have been implicated in the phosphorylation of beta-TRCP phosphodegrons, and  in many cases, multiple kinases collaborate to generate the phosphodegron,  e.g. GSK3beta/CKI (for beta-catenin), Chk1 and another unknown  kinase (for Cdc25A), and Cdc2/Plk1 (for Emi1)  (14,  15,  47). Interestingly, Emi1 is  one of several cell cycle regulators, in addition to Wee1, Emi2, and Claspin,  that is phosphorylated by Plk family member Plk1 for degradation by the  SCFbeta-TRCP complex  (47-55).  Thus, Plk family members seem to collaborate with beta-TRCP to regulate the  degradation of a variety of substrates in different cellular contexts.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40020</offset><text>We found that SPAR contains a canonical beta-TRCP phosphodegron sequence  (1304DSGIDT) in its Act2 domain. Point mutations in Ser-1305 and  Thr-1309 within SPAR inhibited Plk2-dependent SPAR degradation and its binding  to beta-TRCP, providing evidence that this sequence functions as a  phosphodegron.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40323</offset><text>Currently, the identity of the kinase that phosphorylates  1304DSGIDT in SPAR is not definitively established. A direct  demonstration that Plk2 phosphorylates Ser-1305 and Thr-1309 is currently  lacking due, in part, to difficulty in purifying modified full-length SPAR.  Thus, further studies are required to definitively correlate that these  candidate sites are phosphorylated by Plk2. Nevertheless, because Plk2  promotes the SPAR-beta-TRCP interaction and can phosphorylate SPAR in  vitro (6), we favor the  idea that Plk2 is the kinase responsible for phosphorylation of Ser-1305 and  Thr-1309 in this phosphodegron. Supporting this idea is that Plk2 also binds  to the Act2 domain of SPAR (6),  so the kinase would be recruited to the vicinity of the phosphodegron.  However, we cannot rule out the possibilities that Plk2 activity is required  but not sufficient for phosphorylation of Ser-1305 and Thr-1309, that  additional kinases are involved, or that additional phosphodegrons exist in  SPAR. Plk2 is thus far the only kinase reported to promote SPAR degradation in  neurons (6), although it is  possible that other kinases could contribute as well. During early  Xenopus and zebrafish development, casein kinase Iepsilon has been  implicated in the decrease of SPAR protein through Wnt signaling  (56).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>41641</offset><text>SPAR levels influence spine shape and size  (5,  6), and SPAR degradation is  involved in activity-dependent synaptic scaling  (43). Our results here show  that the SCFbeta-TRCP complex targets SPAR for turnover in  response to Plk2 activity. Nevertheless, blocking Plk2-dependent SPAR  degradation through overexpression of the dominant-negative beta-TRCP  construct did not prevent Plk2-dependent changes in spine morphology. This  suggests that the exact role of the Plk2-SCFbeta-TRCP-SPAR  pathway in neurons is still unclear. Plk2 may regulate the function or  expression of additional proteins besides SPAR that are unaffected by  disruption of the beta-TRCP degradation pathway. Similarly, by globally  disrupting the SCFbeta-TRCP complex in the neuron, additional  beta-TRCP substrates may accumulate that offset the effects of accumulated  SPAR protein. In C. elegans, the beta-TRCP ortholog Lin-23 targets  beta-catenin/bar-1 for destruction in the ventral nerve cord,  leading to altered glutamate receptor density  (35).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>42674</offset><text>Endogenous Plk2 expression is induced during periods of elevated neuronal  activity and causes degradation of SPAR protein as well as thinning and  elongation of spines (6). The  accumulation of SPAR in spines upon inhibition of the  SCFbeta-TRCP pathway as well as the recent report that  proteasomes redistribute into spines with synaptic stimulation  (11) is consistent with the  possibility that phosphorylation of SPAR by Plk2 leads to local interaction  with beta-TRCP and degradation of SPAR at postsynaptic sites. Because SPAR  is a large scaffolding protein in the PSD that forms complexes with  N-methyl-d-aspartate receptors and PSD-95  (5), regulation of SPAR  degradation through the SCFbeta-TRCP complex may be predicted to  play a significant role in regulating the composition of proteins in the  spine. Given the critical role of the proteasome in turning over many PSD  proteins (10), it is likely  that additional specific E3s will be identified that regulate synaptic  composition.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>43676</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43699</offset><text>   </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43703</offset><text>  </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kasai, H., Matsuzaki, M., Noguchi, J., Yasumatsu, N., and Nakahara,  H. ()    -368</infon><infon key="fpage">360</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12850432</infon><infon key="source">Trends Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43706</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tada, T., and Sheng, M. ()    -101</infon><infon key="fpage">95</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16361095</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin.  Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43707</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bonhoeffer, T., and Yuste, R. ()     -1027</infon><infon key="fpage">1019</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12354393</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">35</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>43708</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Carlisle, H. J., and Kennedy, M. B. ()     -187</infon><infon key="fpage">182</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15808352</infon><infon key="source">Trends Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">28</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43709</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pak, D. T., Yang, S., Rudolph-Correia, S., Kim, E., and Sheng, M.  ()    -303</infon><infon key="fpage">289</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11502259</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">31</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>43710</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pak, D. T., and Sheng, M. ()     -1373</infon><infon key="fpage">1368</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14576440</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">302</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43711</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kauselmann, G., Weiler, M., Wulff, P., Jessberger, S., Konietzko,  U., Scafidi, J., Staubli, U., Bereiter-Hahn, J., Strebhardt, K., and Kuhl, D.  ()     -5539</infon><infon key="fpage">5528</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10523297</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>43712</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Newton, S. S., Collier, E. F., Hunsberger, J., Adams, D.,  Terwilliger, R., Selvanayagam, E., and Duman, R. S. ()     -10851</infon><infon key="fpage">10841</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14645477</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43713</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Turrigiano, G. ()    -324</infon><infon key="fpage">318</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17451937</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin.  Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>43714</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ehlers, M. D. ()    -242</infon><infon key="fpage">231</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12577062</infon><infon key="source">Nat.  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43715</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bingol, B., and Schuman, E. M. ()     -1148</infon><infon key="fpage">1144</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16810255</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">441</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43716</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Cardozo, T., and Pagano, M. ()    -751</infon><infon key="fpage">739</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15340381</infon><infon key="source">Nat.  Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43717</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Petroski, M. D., and Deshaies, R. J. ()     -20</infon><infon key="fpage">9</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15688063</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43718</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jin, J., Shirogane, T., Xu, L., Nalepa, G., Qin, J., Elledge, S.  J., and Harper, J. W. ()     -3074</infon><infon key="fpage">3062</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14681206</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43719</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, C., Li, Y., Semenov, M., Han, C., Baeg, G. H., Tan, Y., Zhang,  Z., Lin, X., and He, X. ()     -847</infon><infon key="fpage">837</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11955436</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">108</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>43720</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Margottin-Goguet, F., Hsu, J. Y., Loktev, A., Hsieh, H. M.,  Reimann, J. D., and Jackson, P. K. ()    -826</infon><infon key="fpage">813</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12791267</infon><infon key="source">Dev.  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43721</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Winston, J. T., Strack, P., Beer-Romero, P., Chu, C. Y., Elledge,  S. J., and Harper, J. W. ()    -283</infon><infon key="fpage">270</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9990852</infon><infon key="source">Genes  Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>43722</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Busino, L., Donzelli, M., Chiesa, M., Guardavaccaro, D., Ganoth,  D., Dorrello, N. V., Hershko, A., Pagano, M., and Draetta, G. F.  ()    -91</infon><infon key="fpage">87</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14603323</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">426</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43723</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shirogane, T., Jin, J., Ang, X. L., and Harper, J. W.  ()     -26872</infon><infon key="fpage">26863</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15917222</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">280</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43724</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bashir, T., Dorrello, N. V., Amador, V., Guardavaccaro, D., and  Pagano, M. ()     -193</infon><infon key="fpage">190</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15014502</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">428</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43725</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Welcker, M., Orian, A., Jin, J., Grim, J. E., Harper, J. W.,  Eisenman, R. N., and Clurman, B. E. ()    -9090</infon><infon key="fpage">9085</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15150404</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl.  Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43726</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Piva, R., Liu, J., Chiarle, R., Podda, A., Pagano, M., and  Inghirami, G. ()     -8387</infon><infon key="fpage">8375</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12417738</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>43727</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Cullinan, S. B., Gordan, J. D., Jin, J., Harper, J. W., and Diehl,  J. A. ()     -8486</infon><infon key="fpage">8477</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15367669</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43728</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jin, J., Ang, X. L., Shirogane, T., and Wade Harper, J.  ()     -309</infon><infon key="fpage">287</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16338364</infon><infon key="source">Methods Enzymol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">399</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43729</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Guardavaccaro, D., Kudo, Y., Boulaire, J., Barchi, M., Busino, L.,  Donzelli, M., Margottin-Goguet, F., Jackson, P. K., Yamasaki, L., and Pagano,  M. ()    -812</infon><infon key="fpage">799</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12791266</infon><infon key="source">Dev. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43730</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fong, A., and Sun, S. C. ()    -22114</infon><infon key="fpage">22111</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11994270</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>43731</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Patrick, G. N. ()    -94</infon><infon key="fpage">90</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16427269</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin.  Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43732</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bingol, B., and Schuman, E. M. ()    -541</infon><infon key="fpage">536</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16150592</infon><infon key="source">Curr.  Opin. Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43733</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yi, J. J., and Ehlers, M. D. ()     -632</infon><infon key="fpage">629</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16129392</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">47</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43734</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Cline, H. ()    -516</infon><infon key="fpage">514</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43735</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jurd, R., Thornton, C., Wang, J., Luong, K., Phamluong, K.,  Kharazia, V., Gibb, S. L., and Ron, D. ()    -310</infon><infon key="fpage">301</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17962190</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>43736</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ciechanover, A., and Brundin, P. ()     -446</infon><infon key="fpage">427</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14556719</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">40</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43737</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Petrucelli, L., and Dawson, T. M. ()     -320</infon><infon key="fpage">315</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15224658</infon><infon key="source">Ann. Med.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">36</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43738</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Collins, C. A., Wairkar, Y. P., Johnson, S. L., and DiAntonio, A.  ()    -69</infon><infon key="fpage">57</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16815332</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">51</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43739</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dreier, L., Burbea, M., and Kaplan, J. M. ()     -64</infon><infon key="fpage">51</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15820693</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">46</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43740</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Juo, P., and Kaplan, J. M. ()    -2062</infon><infon key="fpage">2057</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15556870</infon><infon key="source">Curr.  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43741</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kato, A., Rouach, N., Nicoll, R. A., and Bredt, D. S.  ()     -5605</infon><infon key="fpage">5600</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15809437</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">102</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43742</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liao, E. H., Hung, W., Abrams, B., and Zhen, M. ()     -350</infon><infon key="fpage">345</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15208641</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">430</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43743</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Myat, A., Henry, P., McCabe, V., Flintoft, L., Rotin, D., and Tear,  G. ()    -459</infon><infon key="fpage">447</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12165468</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">35</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>43744</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nakata, K., Abrams, B., Grill, B., Goncharov, A., Huang, X.,  Chisholm, A. D., and Jin, Y. ()     -420</infon><infon key="fpage">407</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15707898</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">120</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43745</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Stegmuller, J., Konishi, Y., Huynh, M. A., Yuan, Z., Dibacco, S.,  and Bonni, A. ()    -400</infon><infon key="fpage">389</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16675394</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">50</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43746</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">van Roessel, P., Elliott, D. A., Robinson, I. M., Prokop, A., and  Brand, A. H. ()     -718</infon><infon key="fpage">707</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15550251</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">119</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43747</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Seeburg, D. P., Feliu-Mojer, M., Gaiottino, J., Pak, D. T., and  Sheng, M. ()    -583</infon><infon key="fpage">571</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18498738</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">58</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>43748</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Guardavaccaro, D., Frescas, D., Dorrello, N. V., Peschiaroli, A.,  Multani, A. S., Cardozo, T., Lasorella, A., Iavarone, A., Chang, S., Hernando,  E., and Pagano, M. ()     -369</infon><infon key="fpage">365</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18354482</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">452</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>43749</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Westbrook, T. F., Hu, G., Ang, X. L., Mulligan, P., Pavlova, N. N.,  Liang, A., Leng, Y., Maehr, R., Shi, Y., Harper, J. W., and Elledge, S. J.  ()     -374</infon><infon key="fpage">370</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18354483</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">452</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>43750</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wu, G., Xu, G., Schulman, B. A., Jeffrey, P. D., Harper, J. W., and  Pavletich, N. P. ()     -1456</infon><infon key="fpage">1445</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12820959</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>43751</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hansen, D. V., Loktev, A. V., Ban, K. H., and Jackson, P. K.  ()     -5634</infon><infon key="fpage">5623</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15469984</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Biol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43752</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hansen, D. V., Tung, J. J., and Jackson, P. K. ()      -613</infon><infon key="fpage">608</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16407128</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43753</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, J., and Maller, J. L. ()    -1468</infon><infon key="fpage">1458</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16040245</infon><infon key="source">Curr.  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43754</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mailand, N., Bekker-Jensen, S., Bartek, J., and Lukas, J.  ()    -318</infon><infon key="fpage">307</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16885021</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43755</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mamely, I., van Vugt, M. A., Smits, V. A., Semple, J. I., Lemmens,  B., Perrakis, A., Medema, R. H., and Freire, R. ()     -1955</infon><infon key="fpage">1950</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16934469</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43756</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Moshe, Y., Boulaire, J., Pagano, M., and Hershko, A.  ()     -7942</infon><infon key="fpage">7937</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15148369</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43757</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Peschiaroli, A., Dorrello, N. V., Guardavaccaro, D., Venere, M.,  Halazonetis, T., Sherman, N. E., and Pagano, M. ()     -329</infon><infon key="fpage">319</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16885022</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>43758</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rauh, N. R., Schmidt, A., Bormann, J., Nigg, E. A., and Mayer, T.  U. ()     -1052</infon><infon key="fpage">1048</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16127448</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">437</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>43759</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Watanabe, N., Arai, H., Nishihara, Y., Taniguchi, M., Hunter, T.,  and Osada, H. ()    -4424</infon><infon key="fpage">4419</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15070733</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>43760</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tsai, I. C., Amack, J. D., Gao, Z. H., Band, V., Yost, H. J., and  Virshup, D. M. ()    -347</infon><infon key="fpage">335</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17336901</infon><infon key="source">Dev. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>43761</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>43762</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: PSD, postsynaptic density; Ub, ubiquitin; GAP,  GTPase activating protein; SPAR, spine-associated Rap GTPase activating  protein; Plk2, Polo-like kinase 2; UPP, ubiquitin-proteasome pathway; CMV,  cytomegalovirus; HA, hemagglutinin; GFP, green fluorescent protein; SCF,  Skp1/Cul1/F-box protein; WT, wild type; RFP, red fluorescent protein; GST,  glutathione S-transferase; RNAi, RNA-mediated interference; DIV, days  in vitro; shRNA, short hairpin RNA; E3, ubiquitin-protein isopeptide  ligase; beta-TRCP, beta-transducin repeat-containing protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>44340</offset><text>D. P. Seeburg, unpublished observation.</text></passage></document></collection>
