<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>18986984</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M806256200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2615503</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">18986984</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">1917</infon><infon key="fpage">1917</infon><infon key="issue">3</infon><infon key="lpage">1929</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rousseau;given-names:Erwann</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kojima;given-names:Rieko</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hoffner;given-names:Guylaine</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Djian;given-names:Philippe</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Bertolotti;given-names:Anne</infon><infon key="p">Author's Choice:Final version full  access.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Misfolding of Proteins with a Polyglutamine Expansion Is Facilitated by  Proteasomal  Chaperones*S</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>99</offset><text>Deposition of misfolded proteins with a polyglutamine expansion is a  hallmark of Huntington disease and other neurodegenerative disorders.  Impairment of the proteolytic function of the proteasome has been reported to  be both a cause and a consequence of polyglutamine accumulation. Here we found  that the proteasomal chaperones that unfold proteins to be degraded by the  proteasome but also have non-proteolytic functions co-localized with  huntingtin inclusions both in primary neurons and in Huntington disease  patients and formed a complex independently of the proteolytic particle.  Overexpression of Rpt4 or Rpt6 facilitated aggregation of mutant huntingtin  and ataxin-3 without affecting proteasomal degradation. Conversely, reducing  Rpt6 or Rpt4 levels decreased the number of inclusions in primary neurons,  indicating that endogenous Rpt4 and Rpt6 facilitate inclusion formation.  In vitro reconstitution experiments revealed that purified 19S  particles promote mutant huntingtin aggregation. When fused to the ornithine  decarboxylase destabilizing sequence, proteins with expanded polyglutamine  were efficiently degraded and did not aggregate. We propose that aggregation  of proteins with expanded polyglutamine is not a consequence of a proteolytic  failure of the 20S proteasome. Rather, aggregation is elicited by chaperone  subunits of the 19S particle independently of proteolysis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1508</offset><text>Huntington disease  (HD)4 is an autosomal  dominantly inherited disease caused by the expansion of a polyglutamine  (poly(Q)) stretch in the amino-terminal region of huntingtin (Htt)  (1). Proteolysis of Htt is an  early event in the pathogenesis of HD generating amino-terminal products  encompassing the poly(Q) expansion that accumulate in neurons where they form  nuclear and cytoplasmic aggregates and somehow cause neurodegeneration  (2-4).  The observation that poly(Q) are ubiquitinated has suggested that deficient  clearance of mutant Htt by the proteasome causes their accumulation  (5). In support of this idea,  inhibitors of the proteolytic activity of the proteasome augment aggregation  of proteins with a poly(Q) expansion  (6-8).  Yet conflicting studies question whether or not the proteasome degrades  extended poly(Q) stretches  (9-13).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2366</offset><text>The proteasome is a barrel-shaped proteolytic complex composed of the 20S  catalytic core particle (CP) and 11S or 19S regulatory particles (RP) flanking  one or both ends of the CP  (14). The 19S recognizes  polyubiquitinated substrates and removes the polyubiquitin chains, and the six  ATPases (Rpt1-6) of the 19S particle unfold protein substrates, delivering  unfolded and degradation competent proteins to the narrow catalytic chamber of  the CP (15). The 26S  proteasome is considered to be the most prominent species and is composed of  one 20S and one 19S particle. Alternative RPs have been isolated  (16), and the assembly of one  or two of the various RPs with the CP generates a dynamic repertoire of  proteasome complexes, exchanging RPs  (17). During proteolysis, ATP  hydrolysis dissociates 19S and 20S particles, further highlighting the  plasticity of proteasome complexes  (18). The 19S ATPases also  function non-proteolytically in transcription, DNA repair, and chromatin  remodeling  (19-25).  Altogether, these studies reveal that the proteasome is not a static complex.  Rather, individual proteasome components play important roles in a variety of  cellular processes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3560</offset><text>Deposition of proteins of aberrant conformation is the generic feature of  many neurodegenerative diseases, including Alzheimer disease, Parkinson  disease, prion disorders, and polyglutamine expansion disorders. In affected  neurons the disease-specific proteins accumulate in an amyloid or amyloid-like  state characterized by a common cross-beta structure in which beta-strands  run perpendicular to the axis of the fibril. The common structure of the  pathogenic conformer of the disease-related proteins is in sharp contrast to  the fact that the amyloidogenic proteins do not exhibit any sequence  similarities or common structural motifs in their native state  (26). Thus, a structural  transition must occur to convert the different native structures into the  common cross-beta-sheet structure  (27-29).  This transition between the folded native and the amyloidogenic conformation  is prevented by a large thermodynamic barrier  (30). Thus, it is unlikely  that such a transition occurs spontaneously under physiological conditions.  The aggregation of poly(Q) has been well described in vitro using  small synthetic peptides and occurs by nucleated growth polymerization  (2,  31). However, in inclusions of  HD patients, Htt amino-terminal fragments contain sequences additional to the  poly(Q) stretch (32),  including a proline-rich region, which strongly antagonizes aggregation  (33-36).  Thus, to elicit Htt aggregation, some trigger ought to be required to  alleviate the inhibition of the proline-rich region and to convert the soluble  protein into an aggregate. In vitro the rate-limiting and  thermodynamically unfavorable step in aggregation of pure poly(Q) peptides is  the nucleation reaction, consisting of the structural transition of a monomer  into an amyloidogenic conformation. Nucleation of poly(Q) aggregates is viewed  as an unfavorable folding reaction  (31). What triggers poly(Q)  nucleation in neurons of HD patients is unknown, but in cells conformational  rearrangements are assisted by chaperones  (37). Here we report the  finding that Rpt6 (PSMC5) and Rpt4 (PSMC6) facilitate the conversion of  soluble mutant Htt amino-terminal fragments to their aggregated state.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>5769</offset><text>Rpt subunits co-localize with Htt inclusions. A,  micrographs of primary neurons either mock-transfected or transfected with  Htt73-GFP and labeled with Rpt antibodies or alpha7 (20S subunit) antibody  and with H33258 dye. B, immunohistochemical analysis of cortical  sections from juvenile HD patients with indicated antibodies and  4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI). About 200 inclusions from 2  patients were scored. 100% of inclusions were labeled with Rpt6, whereas a  light labeling for alpha7 was found in 13% of inclusions in both patients.  Representative micrographs are shown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>6359</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6383</offset><text>Cell Culture and Reagents:293T cells were maintained in  Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum  and transfected in 6- or 12-well plates by using the calcium phosphate method  leading usually to &gt;70% transfection efficiency. Routinely, 45,000 cells/ml  were plated before transfection. For analytical experiments 0.25 mug of  Htt73 encoding plasmid were transfected together with 0.125, 0.25, and 0.5  mug of plasmid encoding 19S subunits except when indicated otherwise. Where  indicated, cells were treated with epoxomycin (Calbiochem).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6959</offset><text>Primary cultures of rat hippocampal neurons were prepared from E18 rats.  Transfections were performed after 8 days of culture in 6-well plates with 0.5  mug of Htt73-GFP plasmid with or without 0.5 mug of Rpt6 plasmid and  Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7216</offset><text>Plasmid Constructs:Htt17 encodes the first 163 amino acids  of Htt. Htt73 encodes a similar protein with 73 glutamines. Rpt6 was kindly  provided by R. Losson and subcloned in the HindIII and XhoI restriction sites  of pXJ41. Rpt680-406 was generated by PCR and cloned HindIII and  XhoI restriction sites of pXJ41. The cDNAs encoding Rpt4 was amplified by  reverse transcription-PCR from HeLa cell total RNA flanked with EcoRI and XhoI  sites and cloned into pXJ41. To generate GFP fusion, Htt73 was PCR-amplified,  flanked with BamHI and KpnI sites, and cloned in the BglII and KpnI sites of  pEGFP-N2 (BD Biosciences). To produce GST fusions, Rpt6 and  Rpt680-406 were subcloned into the BamHI and XhoI restriction sites  of pGEX-4T3 vector in-frame with GST (GE Healthcare). The cDNA sequence coding  for the last 52 amino acids of ornithine decarboxylase (ODC) was PCR-amplified  using pZS Proteasome Sensor (Clontech) as a template, flanked with XhoI and  XbaI restriction sites, and cloned in pCDNA1/Amp vector (Invitrogen)  containing Htt73 to produce Htt73ODC. In the ODC-encoding sequence, cysteine  441 was mutated in alanine to generate Htt73ODCC441A. The cDNA  encoding the first 108 amino acids of huntingtin with an expansion of 50 CAG  was cloned in pGEX-4T vector in-frame with GST (GE Healthcare) generating  GST-Htt50Delta, similar to GST-HD51 described in Scherzinger et al.  (38). Expression of  recombinant proteins was performed as described in Scherzinger et al.  (38). All constructs were  verified by DNA sequencing.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8758</offset><text>Small Interfering RNAs:80 pmol of double-stranded RNA  oligonucleotides directed against the target rat Rpt6 (Rpt6 siRNA_1,  ggattgacaggaaaattga; Rpt6 siRNA_2, ggagatcaaagaagtgatt) or Rpt4 (Rpt4 siRNA_1,  tggacagattgtaggcgaa; Rpt4 siRNA_2, tgaggtatctgccgagaga) or control siRNA  Silencer Negative Control #1 (Ambion) were transfected in primary  hippocampal neurons 8 days after their plating in a 6-well plate using  Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Neurons were fixed 24 h after  transfection.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9254</offset><text>Immunocytochemistry and Fluorescence Microscopy:Transfected  cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde and labeled with indicated  antibodies. Micrographs were taken at 100x magnification on a Leica TCS  SP2AOBS confocal microscope or Leica DMRB Fluorescence microscope.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9525</offset><text>Human HD Tissue:Frozen brain samples (parietal cortex,  Brodmann area number 7) from two individuals with juvenile HD were obtained  from the Harvard Brain Tissue Resource Center. The two cases were a  14-year-old, grade 3 female with 97 CAG repeats and a 18-year-old grade 4  female with 75 CAG repeats, previously described in Hoffner et al.  (39). Sections were fixed with  4% paraformaldehyde and labeled with a polyclonal antibody directed against  the first 17 amino acids of human Htt (1:400 dilution)  (39), alpha7 (PW8110 BIOMOL,  1:1000 dilution), and Rpt6 antibody (SUG-1b8, Euromedex, 1:5000 dilution). 100  inclusions were examined, 50 nuclear and 50 cytoplasmic, in the two tissues.  Micrographs were taken at 63x magnification combined with digital  zooming on a Zeiss confocal microscope (Carl Zeiss, Inc., Thornwood, NY).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10364</offset><text>Immunoblotting and Filter Retardation Assay:Routinely, 70%  confluent cells from a well of a 12-well plate were lysed in 140 mul of  boiling Laemmli buffer (25 mm Tris-HCl, pH 6.8, 1% SDS, 25  mm dithiothreitol, 7.5% glycerol, 0.05% bromphenol blue) for  immunoblot analysis or 140 mul of ice-cold Nonidet P-40 buffer (25  mm Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 1% Nonidet P-40, 300 mm NaCl, 5  mm EDTA, 1 mm phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 5 mug/ml  pepstatin, leupeptin, and aprotinin) for fractionation experiments. 18 mul  of protein extracts were loaded on 10% SDS-PAGE and transferred to Optitran  BA-S 83 reinforced nitrocellulose membrane (Whatman and Schleicher &amp;  Schuell). Equal loading of protein extracts analyzed by immunoblot was  controlled by Ponceau Red staining (data not shown) and vimentin. Filter  retardation assays were performed as described in Wanker et al.  (40). Membranes were saturated  in 5% dried skimmed milk in phosphate-buffered saline and probed with Htt 2b4  antibody unless specified. The appropriate secondary antibody coupled to  peroxidase was revealed using the SuperSignal West Pico Chemiluminescent kit  (Pierce). Chemiluminescent images were acquired using the Chemi-Smart 5000  (Vilber-Lourmat) allowing quantitative detection of chemiluminescence. Signals  of interest were quantified using Bio-1d software (Vilber-Lourmat).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11716</offset><text>Antibodies:For immunocytochemistry, primary antibodies were  diluted as follows: 1:1000 dilution for Tau-1 antibody (Chemicon), alpha7  (PW8110 BIOMOL), Rpt1 (ab3322, Abcam), Rpt2 (ab3317), Rpt3 (ab22634), and Rpt5  (ab22635); 1:5000 dilution for Rpt6 antibody (SUG-1b8, Euromedex) or Rpt4  (ab22639). For immunoblots, antibodies were used as follows: 1:5000 for Htt  2b4 antibody and 1:1000 for antibodies against proteasome subunits. Vimentin  antibody V 6630 (Sigma) was used at a 1:500 dilution, p21 antibody (BD  Pharmingen 556431) at a 1:500 dilution, and E2F-1 (Santa Cruz) sc-251 at a  1:200 dilution. GFP antiserum (BD Biosciences) was used as a control  antibody.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12390</offset><text>Immunoprecipitation:293T cells were plated 24 h before  transfection in 10-cm dishes at a density of 80000 cells/ml. Transfection were  performed with 2.5 mug of Htt73 alone or with 5 mug of Rpt6-FLAG-encoding  plasmid. 48 h post-transfection, cells were washed with ice-cold  phosphate-buffered saline, lysed in 1 ml of 0.2% Nonidet P-40 buffer (0.2%  Nonidet P-40, 50 mm Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 300 mm NaCl, 5  mm EDTA, 1 mm phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 5 mug/ml  pepstatin, leupeptin, and aprotinin), left 10 min on ice, and clarified by  centrifugation at 16,000 x g for 10 min. Soluble proteins were  immunoprecipitated with 2 mul of the anti-Rpt6, anti-GFP, or anti-Htt  monoclonal antibodies together with 10 mul of protein G-Sepharose overnight  at 4  C. Beads were then washed 3 times in 0.2% Nonidet P-40 buffer and  resolved by 10% SDS-PAGE under reducing conditions, transferred to  nitrocellulose membranes, and revealed with corresponding antibodies.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13351</offset><text>GST Pulldown Assay:GST, GST-Rpt6, and  GST-Rpt680-406 were expressed in Escherichia coli strain  BL21 (DE3) pLysS and purified by glutathione-Sepharose chromatography. For  each pulldown experiment, about 0.1 mug of GST or GST-Rpt6 fusion protein  was incubated with Htt73 produced in 293T cells and extracted in 1% Nonidet  P-40 buffer. After 3 h of incubation at room temperature, beads were washed 3  times for 5 min in 1% Nonidet P-40 buffer, and complexes were analyzed by  SDS-PAGE followed by immunoblots.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>13864</offset><text>Overexpressed and endogenous Rpts are subunits of two distinct  complexes, the 26 S proteasome and APIS. A-C, lysates of  mock-transfected cells or cells overexpressing Rpt6-FLAG or Rpt4-FLAG were  analyzed by glycerol gradients sedimentation. An aliquot of each fraction was  analyzed by immunoblots and for peptidase activity with  N-Succinyl-Leu-Leu-Val-Tyr-aminomethylcoumarin as indicated below the  immunoblots (41).  APIS, ATPase proteins independent of 20S  (22). D, fractions  2-4 (APIS) and 8-9 (26 S) of glycerol gradients similar to those shown in  (A and C) were pooled, immunoprecipitated, and revealed with  indicated antibodies. Horseradish peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-mouse  kappa were used to reveal the immunoblots, as Rpts co-migrate with the heavy  chain of the immunoglobulins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14668</offset><text>Glycerol-gradient Sedimentation:225000 cells were plated in  a 5-cm dish and transfected with empty vector or the indicated constructs 24 h  after plating. Cells were lysed 40 h post-transfection in 200 mul of  proteasome lysis buffer (50 mm Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 1% Triton X-100, 1  mm EDTA, 1.5 mm MgCl2, 1 mm  dithiothreitol, and 5 mm ATP). Extracts were clarified by  centrifugation and fractionated through linear 20-40% glycerol gradients in  polyallomer tubes of 11 x 60 mm for 13 h at 40,000 rpm in a SW60 rotor  (Beckman Coulter). Each 4-ml gradient was collected into 14 equal fractions of  300 mul. Aliquots of each fraction were subjected to immunoblots and  peptidase assay. Note that all the proteasome complexes sedimented below their  expected molecular weights, as previously reported  (25).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15473</offset><text>Proteasome Activity:Assays for proteasome activity were  performed using the substrate  N-Succinyl-Leu-Leu-Val-Tyr-aminomethylcoumarin as described in  Kisselev and Goldberg  (41).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15654</offset><text>Aggregation Assays:GST-Htt50Delta (0.5 mum)  was incubated with or without purified 19S proteasome (70 nm;  Boston Biochem) in the presence of 10 units of thrombin (Amersham Biosciences)  at 37  C with 300 rpm shaking in 50 mm Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150  mm NaCl, 10% glycerol, 20 mm MgCl2 with or  without 5 mm ATP or 15 mm ATPgammaS. Reactions were  stopped at the indicated times by adding an equal volume of Laemmli buffer and  boiling for 5 min. Aliquots corresponding to 50 ng of GST fusion protein were  analyzed by SDS-PAGE stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue, and filter  retardation assays revealed with Htt antibody.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>16279</offset><text>Htt73 misfolding is facilitated by proteasomal chaperones.  A, lysates of cells expressing increasing amounts of Htt73 were  either boiled in 1% SDS or fractionated into NP40 supernatant and pellet and  analyzed by immunoblotting with Htt antibody. B-D, Htt73 was  co-expressed with increasing amounts of Rpt4 or Rpt6, and whole cell lysates  or supernatants and pellets were analyzed by immunoblotting with Htt, Rpt6, or  Rpt4 antibodies. E, micrographs of cells expressing Htt17-GFP alone  or together with Rpt6. Confocal micrographs of cells expressing Htt73-GFP  either alone or together with Rpt6 or Rpt4 are shown. Nuclei were stained with  H33258. Arrows show cells with small inclusions, and  asterisks show cells with large inclusions. F, micrographs  of primary neurons expressing Htt17-GFP and Htt73-GFP alone or together with  Rpt6. Neuronal identity was confirmed by staining with TAU-1 antibody, and  nuclei are revealed with H33258.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>17227</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17235</offset><text>Aggregation of peptides with a long poly(Q) stretch can occur spontaneously  in vitro, but in yeast aggregation of the amino-terminal fragment of  Htt requires the presence of the chaperone Hsp104  (42). Although chaperones are  widely conserved throughout evolution, there is no mammalian orthologue of  Hsp104. The typical feature of Hsp104 and the bacterial ATPase ClpB proteins  is the presence of two AAA domains and a middle region or M-domain, adopting a  coiled-coil structure essential for the Hsp104/ClpB protein remodeling  function (43,  44). AAA ATPases in available  databases were examined aiming to identify human proteins containing both a  coiled-coil and an AAA domain. We found that only the ATPase subunits of the  19S proteasome, Rpt6, Rpt4, Rpt3, Rpt2, and Rpt1, exhibit these specific  features. Interestingly, an immunohistochemical study of brain tissue from  patients with spinocerebellar ataxia type 3 (SCA-3) has revealed that poly(Q)  inclusions co-localize with subunits of the 19S proteasome but rarely of the  20S catalytic particle (45).  These observations together with the unfoldase function of the 19S ATPases in  protein degradation prompted us to investigate whether Rpts contribute to  inclusion formation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18483</offset><text>To determine whether co-localization of regulatory subunits of the  proteasome with poly(Q) inclusions was a generic feature of distinct poly(Q)  disorders, we analyzed the localization of several proteasome subunits in  nerve cells containing mutant Htt inclusions. In primary neurons, Rpt6  staining was extremely intense around poly(Q) aggregates, in contrast to its  diffuse and mostly nuclear localization in untransfected cells  (Fig. 1A). Similarly,  Rpt4 and Rpt3 co-localize with poly(Q) inclusions. The other 19S ATPases were  also enriched around poly(Q) inclusions  (Fig. 1A). In  contrast, the 20S proteasome was not enriched around the poly(Q) inclusions,  as revealed by immunostaining with antibodies directed against the 20S  subunit, alpha7. These observations reveal that Rpt subunits co-localize  with mutant Htt inclusions in neuronal cells independently of the 20S  proteasome. To determine whether these observations were relevant to HD, we  stained cortical sections of post-mortem HD brains with Htt and Rpt6 or  alpha7 (20S) antibodies. We performed this analysis on brain tissue from two  juvenile HD patients to examine a large number of cytoplasmic and nuclear  inclusions. Like primary neurons expressing mutant Htt, all the inclusions  from both HD patients were intensely labeled with Rpt6 regardless of their  subcellular localization (Fig.  1B and data not shown). In contrast, only a small  fraction of Htt inclusions (13%) exhibited a light staining for the 20S  subunit (Fig. 1B).  These results indicate that the chaperone subunits co-localize with HD  inclusions largely independently of the 20S subunits.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>20128</offset><text>The coiled-coil region is essential for the activity of Rpt6 on  Htt73. A, schematic representation of Rpt6 domain organization  and coiled-coil mutant analyzed in this study. B, lysates of cells  expressing Htt73 alone or together with increasing amounts of Rpt6 wild type  or Rpt680-456 deletion mutant were analyzed by immunoblots and  filter retardation assays.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20494</offset><text>Seeking further evidence for the existence of Rpt subunits independently of  the proteasome, we analyzed the distribution of proteasome subunits from cell  lysates by glycerol gradient fractionation. 19S and 20S subunits as well as  the proteolytic activity of the proteasome were localized in high molecular  weight fractions 8 and 9, indicating that these fractions contained the 26S  proteasome (Fig. 2A).  In addition to the 26S proteasome, 19S subunits were also found in lower  molecular weight fractions devoid of 20S subunits and proteolytic activity  (Fig. 2A, fractions  2-4). This sedimentation profile is reminiscent of the gel filtration profile  of the free 19S-like complex  (25), also called APIS complex  (ATPase proteins independent of 20S)  (22). Thus, in mammalian cells  Rpts are subunits of 2 distinct complexes, the 26S proteasome and APIS or free  19S-like complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21384</offset><text>The observation that inclusions of expanded poly(Q)-containing proteins  co-localize with Rpts independently of the proteasome  (Fig. 1 and  (45) suggested that APIS could  be involved in inclusion formation. We, therefore, attempted to increase the  abundance of this complex by overexpressing some of its subunits. The  sedimentation profile of overexpressed Rpt4 and Rpt6 was similar to the  sedimentation profile of the endogenous subunits. In fractions 8 and 9 of the  glycerol gradients, Rpt6 antibody revealed 2 bands corresponding to the  endogenous protein and the overexpressed FLAG-tagged Rpt6, indicating that  overexpressed Rpt6 was a subunit of the 26S proteasome complex  (Fig. 2B). A large  fraction of overexpressed Rpt6 was detected in fractions 2-4 of the gradient  together with the APIS complex. Similarly, a fraction of overexpressed Rpt4  entered the 26S proteasome, whereas most of the protein was found in the  smaller APIS complex (Fig.  2C). Note that overexpression of Rpt4 or Rpt6 did not  alter the sedimentation of the endogenous proteasome nor its proteolytic  activity (Fig. 2, A-C,  and data not shown). To confirm these observations, immunoprecipitations were  carried out with Rpt6 antibodies on glycerol gradient fractions containing  either APIS (fractions 2-4) or the 26S complex (fractions 8-9). Both  endogenous and overexpressed Rpt4 were detected in Rpt6 immunoprecipitates  performed on fractions 2-4 as well as fractions 8-9 of the glycerol gradients  (Fig. 2D). Rpt3 was  also detected in both complexes but only when Rpt4 was overexpressed. The  amounts of Rpt3 immunoprecipitated in the endogenous complexes were probably  below the detection limit of the Rpt3 antibody. Altogether, these findings  establish that endogenous and overexpressed Rpt4 and Rpt6 are engaged in two  complexes, the 26S proteasome and APIS. Most of the overexpressed Rpt6 and  Rpt4 co-sedimented with APIS and recruit other subunits of the complex. We,  thus, used this experimental setting to analyze whether Rpts modulated Htt  misfolding and aggregation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>23466</offset><text>Rpt6, but not Rpt6 lacking the coiled-coil region, binds to Htt73.  A, lysates of cells transfected with empty vector and Htt73 alone or  together with Rpt6 analyzed by immunoblot (left panel) or  immunoprecipitated (IP) with Htt or GFP antibody followed by Rpt6  immunoblot. B, GST, GST-Rpt6, and GST-Rpt680-406 fusion  proteins were expressed in E. coli, purified on glutathione-Sepharose  beads, separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred onto nitrocellulose, and stained  with Ponceau Red. C, Htt73 containing cell lysates (Input) were  incubated on beads containing GST, GST-Rpt6, or GST-Rpt680-406 and  washed, and complexes bound to beads were revealed with Htt antibody.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24137</offset><text>Nucleation is the rate-limiting step of poly(Q) aggregation in  vitro (31). To determine  whether similar features could be observed in cells, we expressed large  amounts of Htt73 and performed biochemical fractionation. We found that a  10-25-fold increase in the SDS-soluble protein leads to a very modest increase  of Nonidet P-40-insoluble, presumably misfolded Htt73  (Fig. 3A). Thus, cells  can accumulate a large amount of Nonidet P-40-soluble Htt73, suggesting that  aggregation requires not only a high protein concentration but also additional  events. Because the function of Rpts is to unfold proteins and because they  co-localize with poly(Q) inclusions, we asked whether these unfoldases might  assist the conversion from soluble to aggregated mutant Htt. Increasing the  levels of Rpt6 or Rpt4 led to a remarkable and dose-dependent increase of  Htt73 when low amounts of Htt73 were co-transfected with Rpt6 or Rpt4  (Fig. 3, B-D,  lanes 1, 4, and 8, compared with  Fig. 3A, lanes 3,  6, and 9). Biochemical fractionation studies revealed that  nearly all the SDS-soluble Htt73 that accumulated upon Rpt6 or Rpt4  overexpression was Nonidet P-40-insoluble, suggesting that it was in a  pre-aggregated misfolded state (Fig. 3,  B-D). In contrast, when large amounts of Htt73 were  transfected alone, cells contained very high levels of soluble Htt73  (Fig. 3A). These  experiments revealed that Rpt6 and Rpt4 convert soluble Htt into an insoluble  species. To further characterize the effect of Rpt6 and Rpt4 on Htt73, Htt73  fused to GFP was overexpressed either alone or together with Rpt6 or Rpt4  (Fig. 3E). Although  cells expressing Htt73-GFP alone contained either diffuse fluorescence or  small fluorescent foci, cells co-expressing Htt73-GFP and Rpt6 or Rpt4  contained large inclusions (Fig.  3E). This was also observed in primary neuronal cells  expressing Htt73-GFP alone or together with Rpt6, 3F). Htt17-GFP  expressed alone or together with Rpt6 never formed inclusions  (Fig. 3E and data not  shown). Northern blot analyses were carried out with cells co-expressing Rpt6  with Htt73 and revealed that the effects of Rpt6 overexpression on Htt  accumulation were not due to changes at the level of Htt mRNA (supplemental  Fig. 1). Previous studies have indicated that Rpt subunits of the 19S have  distinct functions (46). To  determine whether the effect on mutant Htt aggregation was a general property  of all Rpts or was restricted to Rpt6 and Rpt4, Htt 73 was overexpressed with  the other Rpts. Increasing the levels of Rpt6 or Rpt4 led to a remarkable and  dose-dependent increase of aggregated Htt73, as revealed by immunoblots and  filter retardation assays (supplemental Fig. 2). Overexpression of Rpt3  modestly enhanced aggregation of Htt73, in contrast to Rpt2, Rpt1, and Rpt5,  which had no significant effect (supplemental Fig. 2). This indicated that  overexpression of an individual Rpt was not sufficient to trigger Htt  aggregation but, rather, that the effects of Rpt6 and Rpt4 on Htt73 were  specific. Because cellular protein concentration varies with cell density and  equal cell numbers were seeded in each experiment, the fact that the levels of  the cellular protein vimentin did not vary in the different conditions  revealed that none of the transfected constructs elicited cell death  (supplemental Fig. 2). This is in agreement with previously studies that  established that mutant Htt is not toxic 2 days post-expression  (47,  48). We next sought to  determine which domains were important for the activity of Rpt6. The amino  terminus of Rpt6 contains a coiled-coil domain, a region which was found  important for the chaperone function of other AAAs  (43). Therefore, the  amino-terminal 79 amino acids of Rpt6 containing the coiled-coil region were  deleted, generating a protein fragment, Rpt680-406. Overexpression  of increasing doses of Rpt6 together with Htt73 augmented the levels of Htt73,  detected on immunoblots, by 1.3-, 3-, and 7-fold and the levels of aggregated  Htt73, detected on filter retardation assays by 2-, 5-, and 7-fold. These  -fold increases correspond to the mean values of four independent experiments.  In contrast, Rpt6 lacking the coiled-coil region, expressed at a level similar  to the full-length protein, was devoid of any activity on Htt73  (Fig. 4). This result reveals  that the coiled-coil region of Rpt6 is essential for its function on Htt  aggregation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>28598</offset><text>Rpt6 and Rpt4 enhance misfolding of proteins containing expanded poly(Q)  independently of proteolysis. A, immunoblots and filter  retardation assays of cells overexpressing SCA3 22Q or 82Q alone or together  with Rpt6 and either left untreated or treated with 1 mum  epoxomycin (Epoxo) for 14 h. B, 293 T cells were transfected  with Htt73 alone or together with Rpt6 and Rpt4 encoding plasmids and either  left untreated or treated with 0.5 or 1 mum epoxomycin for 14 h  and analyzed by immunoblots and filter retardation assays.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29130</offset><text>The results presented so far indicate that Rpt6 and Rpt4 assist mutant Htt  misfolding and aggregation. We next tested whether this effect involved a  direct interaction between Rpt6 and Htt73, as suggested by co-localization  studies (Fig. 1).  Coimmunoprecipitation experiments were carried out using cells expressing  Htt73 alone or together with Rpt6. Htt coprecipitated Rpt6, whereas a control  antibody did not (Fig.  5A). To determine whether Rpt6 and Htt73 interact  directly, recombinant Rpt6, either wild type or lacking the coiled-coil  region, was produced in E. coli as a fusion with GST and immobilized  on glutathione beads. Nonidet P-40 lysates containing Htt73 produced in 293T  cells were then incubated with GST and GST-Rpt6. Htt73 was selectively  retained by GST-Rpt6 (Fig.  5B). Deleting Rpt6 coiled-coil region abolished its  ability to bind Htt. These interaction data suggest that the effect of Rpt6 on  Htt aggregation is mediated through a direct interaction and requires the  coiled-coil region.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30154</offset><text>Because a fraction of Rpts were found independently of the proteasome in  SCA-3 (45), we tested whether  overexpressing Rpt6 affected accumulation of ataxin-3, a protein unrelated to  Htt, which contains a poly(Q) expansion in SCA-3. Rpt6 overexpression  dramatically enhanced mutant ataxin-3 aggregation but had no effect on  wild-type ataxin (Fig.  6A). Previous studies have reported that proteasome  inhibition increases accumulation and aggregation of Htt  (6-8).  Therefore, we next analyzed whether Rpt6 or Rpt4 overexpression generally  impaired proteasomal degradation, thereby enhancing accumulation of expanded  poly(Q). Epoxomycin, which blocks the catalytic activity of the 20S  proteasome, provoked accumulation of both SDS-soluble and aggregated Htt73 or  aggregated mutant ataxin-3 (Fig. 6.  A and B). Similarly to epoxomycin treatment,  Rpt6 or Rpt4 overexpression enhanced Htt73 accumulation and aggregation  (Fig. 6B). In  contrast, we found that overexpressing these 19S subunits did not stabilize  the short-lived proteins E2F-1 and p21  (Fig. 6B), whereas  inhibition of the proteolytic activity of the proteasome markedly stabilize  these two short-lived proteins (Fig.  6B). These results indicate that Rpt6 or Rpt4  overexpression does not impair proteasomal degradation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31451</offset><text>Having shown that increasing the levels of Rpt4 and Rpt6 promotes mutant  Htt misfolding, we next tested whether we could interfere with the endogenous  proteins in primary neurons. Two siRNAs targeting Rpt6 were found to  significantly reduce the levels of Rpt6 by 25 and 40%, respectively.  Similarly, two siRNAs designed against Rpt4 reduced the levels of the protein  by ~50% (Fig. 7A).  We found that reducing the levels of Rpt6 or Rpt4 substantially reduced the  number of cells containing poly(Q) inclusions when we examined cells  expressing mutant Htt together with siRNA targeted against Rpt6 or Rpt4  (Fig. 7, B and  C). 70% of neurons expressing mutant Htt contained  inclusions, and 30% of cells exhibited diffuse fluorescence. This ratio was  inverted in cells transfected with Rpt4 or Rpt6 siRNAs  (Fig. 7C). The number  of cells expressing mutant Htt was very similar when the levels of Rpt4 and  Rpt6 were reduced and in control cells, indicating that the siRNAs were not  toxic under our experimental conditions (data not shown). This analysis  demonstrates that reducing the levels of Rpt4 or Rpt6 in primary neurons  significantly decrease inclusion formation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>32632</offset><text>Endogenous Rpt6 and Rpt4 are required for inclusion formation in primary  neurons. A, immunoblots showing Rpt6, Rpt4, and vimentin in  extracts of primary neurons transfected with control, Rpt6, or Rpt4 siRNAs.  Ratio of Rpt6 and Rpt4 proteins, normalized to vimentin, in protein extracts  of primary neurons transfected with control, Rpt6, or Rpt4 siRNAs.  Quantifications were performed on three independent experiments. B,  primary neurons were transfected with control, Rpt6 siRNA_1, or Rpt6 siRNA_2  together with Htt73-GFP, fixed 24 h post-transfection, and labeled with TAU-1  antibody. Micrographs of neurons containing diffuse fluorescence or inclusions  are shown. C, ratio of primary neurons transfected with control,  Rpt6, or Rpt4 siRNAs together with Htt73-GFP, expressed as percentage of  transfected cells. Data were scored from 10 independent experiments  corresponding to more than 4000 cells in total. **, p &lt;  0.01; *, p &lt; 0.02.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33581</offset><text>Overexpressed Rpt6 and Rpt4 recruited other Rpts  (Fig. 2D), suggesting  that their stimulatory activity on Htt misfolding was mediated by a complex  containing Rpts. To directly examine this hypothesis, we next tested whether  purified 19S proteasome could modulate Htt aggregation in vitro.  Aggregation of mutant Htt was monitored by filter retardation assay as  described in Scherzinger et al.  (38). Cleavage of GST-Htt  released the GST moiety and initiated Htt aggregation  (Fig. 8, A and  B). The addition of substoichiometric amounts of purified  19S proteasome and ATP strongly enhanced aggregation of mutant Htt  (Fig. 8B). The  stimulatory effect of 19S proteasome on mutant Htt aggregation in  vitro was significantly decreased by ATP-gammaS, a non-hydrolysable ATP  analogue (Fig. 8B).  The addition of 19S proteasome with or without ATPgammaS did not affect the  cleavage of GST-Htt (Fig.  8A). This suggests that the stimulatory activity of the  19S proteasome on Htt aggregation is mediated by its unfoldase function.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34616</offset><text>Altogether, the results presented here reveal that ATPases of the 19S  proteasome function non-proteolytically in facilitating misfolding and  aggregation of proteins with a poly(Q) expansion. Because Htt inclusions are  ubiquitinated, Htt is likely to be addressed to the proteasome by a  ubiquitin-dependent pathway (3,  4). We next investigated what  would be its fate if targeted to the proteasome by the degradation pathway  utilized by the evanescent protein ODC  (49). The 37 carboxyl-terminal  amino acids of ODC have been found to be an efficient and autonomous  destabilizing sequence when fused to heterologous proteins  (49). We tested whether fusing  ODC destabilizing sequence to Htt73 could enhance its degradation. Htt73 and  Htt73ODC were expressed in 293T cells. Although both soluble and aggregated  Htt73 were readily detected by immunoblots and filter retardation assays,  Htt73ODC was hardly detectable, even when large amounts of DNA encoding this  protein were transfected, suggesting that the protein was very rapidly and  efficiently degraded (Fig.  9A). We confirmed that Htt73ODC was fully degraded and  did not escape our detection (supplemental Fig. 3). When the proteolytic  capacity of the proteasome was compromised, Htt73ODC was stabilized,  confirming that Htt73ODC is a proteasome substrate  (Fig. 9B, right  panel). However, Rpt6 overexpression had virtually no effect on Htt73ODC  (Fig. 9B, right  panel). The fact that Htt73ODC is insensitive to Rpt6 overexpression but  is stabilized by inhibition of the catalytic activity of the proteasome  further supports the conclusion that Rpt6 overexpression does not perturb  proteasomal degradation. When the ability of the proteasome to degrade  proteins is compromised, small but detectable amounts of Htt73ODC aggregates  were found by means of their retention on a cellulose acetate filter  (Fig. 9B). These  observations suggest that, when the catalytic activity of the proteasome is  compromised, a small amount of Htt73ODC recovers its ability to aggregate. To  obtain further insight into the mechanism by which the ODC carboxyl terminus  destabilizes mutant Htt, we mutated cysteine 441 to alanine, as this point  mutation has been shown to stabilize ODC  (49). In contrast to Htt73ODC,  Htt73ODCC441A was readily detectable, and its aggregation increased  upon Rpt6 overexpression (Fig. 9,  C and D). The finding that the ODC destabilizing  sequence converts Htt73 into an evanescent protein indicates that the  proteolytic capacity of the proteasome is not the limiting factor for mutant  Htt degradation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>37216</offset><text>The 19S enhances mutant Htt aggregation in vitro.  A, time course of proteolysis of GST-Htt50DeltaC with or without  19S and ATPgammaS. 0.5 mum GST-Htt50Delta was cleaved with 10  units of thrombin in the absence or presence of 70 nm 19S and 15  mm ATPgammaS. Aliquots of the reaction were analyzed after 3.5,  6, or 8 h at 37  C by SDS-PAGE stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue. Note  that GST and Htt50Delta co-migrate. B, samples shown in A  were analyzed by filter retardation assays and revealed with Htt  antibodies.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>37740</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37751</offset><text>In this study we report on the finding that in cells aggregation of Htt  amino-terminal fragments with a pathogenic poly(Q) expansion is dependent on a  remodeling event mediated by Rpt6 and Rpt4. Proteasomal chaperones are  subunits of 2 complexes, the 26S proteasome and the previously reported APIS  or 19S-like complex (this study and Refs.  22 and  25). Although the function of  the proteasome in protein degradation is well recognized, there is also  growing evidence indicating that 19S ATPases, in particular Rpt6, function  independently of degradation  (50). In HD patients,  inclusions are often found in the nucleus, where a non-proteolytic function of  the 19S ATPases has been extensively reported. A remodeling activity of Rpts  independently of degradation provides a unifying mechanism to reconcile their  diverse functions. Conditions provoking the dissociation of the 19S from the  20S have been reported previously. The 19S RP disassembles during the  catalytic cycle (18). Binding  of alternative RP such as PA28 to the CP also provokes dissociation of the  ATPases (17). Intriguingly,  pharmacological inhibition of the catalytic function of the proteasome  stimulates binding of PA28 to the proteasome  (17), suggesting that free 19S  particles may be released by this treatment. What precisely modulates the  relative abundance of 26S proteasome and APIS (or free 19S-like complex)  remains to be determined. However, it is noteworthy that aging was reported to  promote proteasome disassembly in flies  (51).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39286</offset><text>In neurons of HD (this study) and SCA-3  (45) brains as well as in  primary neurons expressing mutant Htt and Rpts, but not 20S subunits,  co-localize with poly(Q) inclusions, indicating that Rpts are not associated  with the catalytic particles in poly(Q) inclusions. This suggests that Rpts  may be involved in inclusion formation independently of the proteolytic  function of the proteasome. In support of this hypothesis, we found that  overexpression of Rpt6, Rpt4, and more modestly Rpt3 enhance mutant Htt and  SCA-3 aggregation. Because the majority of overexpressed Rpt4 and Rpt6  co-sediment with APIS, we propose that Rpt4 and Rpt6 remodel proteins with a  poly(Q) expansion and thereby elicit their aggregation independently of  degradation. Overexpressing Rpt6 or Rpt4 has no effect on the levels of  vimentin or the short-lived E2F-1, p21, and Htt7ODC, showing unambiguously  that Rpt6 or Rpt4 overexpression does not impair proteasome degradation. More  importantly, reducing the levels of Rpt6 or Rpt4 in primary neurons decreases  inclusion formation. Together, these results indicate that endogenous Rpt6 and  Rpt4 enhance Htt misfolding, and this effect is likely mediated through an  unfoldase function of these proteins. In vitro reconstitution  experiments support this model; substoichiometric amounts of 19S complex  promote mutant Htt aggregation, and this activity is markedly attenuated by  ATPgammaS. Htt supplied in the in vitro aggregation assay is not  ubiquitinated, suggesting that the 19S does not required ubiquitination of Htt  to recognize and remodel Htt. Thus, ubiquitination does not seem to be  required for the aggregation process per se. However, it is possible  that in cells ubiquitination of Htt plays a role in targeting Htt to the  proteasome. This is in agreement with previous in vitro studies on  the chaperone function of the proteasome  (52). When the domain  composition of Rpts was carefully examined, we found that the three ATPases  enhancing poly(Q) aggregation, Rpt6, Rpt4, and Rpt3, possess a coiled-coil  domain of nearly 50 amino acids. In contrast, the 19 S ATPases unable to  enhance poly(Q) aggregation have either no coiled-coil region (Rpt5) or only a  short one (Rpt1, Rpt2) according to domain predictions with the web-based tool  SMART. The importance of the equivalent M-region of the bacterial  ATPase ClpB and the yeast Hsp104 suggested that this finding might not be  fortuitous. We, thus, deleted the coiled-coil region in Rpt6 and found that  although Rpt680-406 was expressed at levels similar to the  full-length protein, this mutant lacking the coiled-coil domain was inactive  toward poly(Q) aggregation (Fig.  4). In agreement with this result, Rpt6 lacking the coiled-coil  region was no longer able to bind mutant Htt  (Fig. 5). Because Htt  misfolding is an early event in HD, our findings suggest that in the disease  process, the formation of misfolded and presumably toxic species may be  assisted by Rpt6 and Rpt4. A recent study has revealed that tau inclusions,  the pathological hallmark of Alzheimer disease, Pick disease, and other  tauopathies, are immunoreactive for Rpt3, raising the question of whether the  findings reported here for Htt and SCA-3 may be a generic feature of many  neurodegenerative diseases  (53).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>42600</offset><text>The degradation signal of ODC converts Htt73 into a highly unstable  protein. A, lysates of cells transfected with increasing amounts  of Htt73 or Htt73ODC encoding plasmids analyzed by immunoblots. B,  cells were transfected with Htt73 (left panel) or Htt73ODC (right  panel) alone or together with increasing amounts of Rpt6 encoding plasmid  and left untreated or treated with 0.25, 0.5 and 1 mum epoxomycin  (Epoxo) for 14 h. Lysates were analyzed by immunoblots or by filter  retardation assays. C, cells transfected with increasing amounts of  Htt73ODC or Htt73ODCC441A were analyzed by immunoblots. D,  cells were transfected with Htt73ODCC441A alone or together with  increasing amounts of Rpt6 encoding plasmid and left untreated or treated with  0.25, 0.5, and 1 mum epoxomycin for 14 h. Lysates were analyzed  by immunoblots or by filter retardation assays revealed with Htt antibody.  E, possible routes followed by Htt: degradation by a proteasome  complex (this study and Ref.  13) or misfolding and  aggregation by APIS or 19 S-like complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43657</offset><text>Monomeric pure poly(Q) peptides are in a random coil conformation  (54), but the addition of the  polyproline domain present in the carboxyl terminus of the poly(Q) stretch in  Htt imposes structural constrain to the protein, which adopts a proline type  II helical conformation (36).  This explains why the proline-rich region of Htt antagonizes the toxicity of  the poly(Q) expansion (34,  35). Thus, a remodeling event  ought to be required to alleviate the inhibitory function of the proline-rich  region and to elicit the conformational transition into the beta-sheet  conformation. In agreement with biophysical data, we found that in cells large  amounts of Htt fragments with expanded poly(Q) can be expressed in a soluble  state (this study and Ref.  55). This implies that  aggregation is not just a consequence of an increase in concentration but is  dependent in the cellular milieu on additional events. The data presented here  indicate that proteasomal chaperones facilitate the transition from soluble to  aggregated proteins with a poly(Q) expansion.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44725</offset><text>Because inhibition of the proteolytic activity of the proteasome increases  Htt aggregation, it has been proposed that aggregates form as a consequence of  an impairment of the proteolytic function of the proteasome. However, two  conflicting studies question whether purified proteasomes can degrade poly(Q)  peptides in vitro (9,  13). Here we show that the  addition of wild type but not mutant ODC destabilizing sequence to Htt with a  poly(Q) expansion profoundly destabilizes this aggregation-prone protein. It  is noteworthy that under certain conditions ODC can be degraded by the 20S  proteasome (56). Although the  mechanism by which wild-type but not mutant ODC carboxyl terminus destabilizes  Htt remains to be determined, it is likely that Htt-ODC is degraded by the  same ubiquitin-independent pathway as ODC. Thus, the route by which Htt is  targeted to the proteasome determines its fate  (Fig. 9E).  Furthermore, the fact that the addition of the ODC destabilizing sequence  converts mutant Htt into a short-lived protein shows unambiguously that, in  cells, the proteolytic capacity of the 20S proteasome is not a factor limiting  mutant Htt degradation. We propose that misfolding and aggregation of proteins  with poly(Q) expansion arise as a consequence of a remodeling event elicited  by a non-proteolytic function of proteasomal chaperones.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46089</offset><text>In conclusion, the data presented here reveal that aggregation of proteins  with poly(Q) expansion requires a transition from a benign to an  aggregation-prone conformation, a process which in cells is facilitated by  proteasomal chaperones. Aggregation of proteins with a poly(Q) expansion is,  thus, reminiscent of a typical folding reaction, requiring the assistance of  chaperones.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>46475</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46498</offset><text>   </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46502</offset><text>  </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zoghbi, H. Y., and Orr, H. T. ()    -247</infon><infon key="fpage">217</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10845064</infon><infon key="source">Annu.  Rev. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>46505</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Perutz, M. F., Johnson, T., Suzuki, M., and Finch, J. T.  ()     -5358</infon><infon key="fpage">5355</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8202492</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>46506</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Davies, S. W., Turmaine, M., Cozens, B. A., DiFiglia, M., Sharp, A.  H., Ross, C. A., Scherzinger, E., Wanker, E. E., Mangiarini, L., and Bates, G.  P. ()    -548</infon><infon key="fpage">537</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9267033</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">90</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>46507</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DiFiglia, M., Sapp, E., Chase, K. O., Davies, S. W., Bates, G. P.,  Vonsattel, J. P., and Aronin, N. ()     -1993</infon><infon key="fpage">1990</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9302293</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>46508</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ciechanover, A., and Brundin, P. ()     -446</infon><infon key="fpage">427</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14556719</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">40</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>46509</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wyttenbach, A., Carmichael, J., Swartz, J., Furlong, R. A., Narain,  Y., Rankin, J., and Rubinsztein, D. C. ()    -2903</infon><infon key="fpage">2898</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10717003</infon><infon key="source">Proc.  Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>46510</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jana, N. R., Zemskov, E. A., Wang, G., and Nukina, N.  ()     -1059</infon><infon key="fpage">1049</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11331615</infon><infon key="source">Hum. Mol. Genet.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>46511</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Waelter, S., Boeddrich, A., Lurz, R., Scherzinger, E., Lueder, G.,  Lehrach, H., and Wanker, E. E. ()    -1407</infon><infon key="fpage">1393</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11359930</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Biol.  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>46512</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Venkatraman, P., Wetzel, R., Tanaka, M., Nukina, N., and Goldberg,  A. L. ()    -104</infon><infon key="fpage">95</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15068806</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46513</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Holmberg, C. I., Staniszewski, K. E., Mensah, K. N., Matouschek,  A., and Morimoto, R. I. ()     -4318</infon><infon key="fpage">4307</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15470501</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46514</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Michalik, A., and Van Broeckhoven, C. ()     -211</infon><infon key="fpage">202</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15207277</infon><infon key="source">Neurobiol. Dis.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46515</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kaytor, M. D., Wilkinson, K. D., and Warren, S. T.  ()    -973</infon><infon key="fpage">962</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15140195</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">89</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46516</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pratt, G., and Rechsteiner, M. ()    -12925</infon><infon key="fpage">12919</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18343811</infon><infon key="source">J.  Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>46517</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wolf, D. H., and Hilt, W. ()    -31</infon><infon key="fpage">19</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15571806</infon><infon key="source">Biochim.  Biophys. Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1695</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46518</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Inobe, T., and Matouschek, A. ()    -51</infon><infon key="fpage">43</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18276129</infon><infon key="source">Curr.  Opin. Struct. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>46519</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rechsteiner, M., and Hill, C. P. ()     -33</infon><infon key="fpage">27</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15653075</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46520</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shibatani, T., Carlson, E. J., Larabee, F., McCormack, A. L., Fruh,  K., and Skach, W. R. ()    -4971</infon><infon key="fpage">4962</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16987959</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Biol.  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>46521</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Babbitt, S. E., Kiss, A., Deffenbaugh, A. E., Chang, Y. H., Bailly,  E., Erdjument-Bromage, H., Tempst, P., Buranda, T., Sklar, L. A., Baumler, J.,  Gogol, E., and Skowyra, D. ()     -565</infon><infon key="fpage">553</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15907469</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">121</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46522</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Swaffield, J. C., Bromberg, J. F., and Johnston, S. A.  ()     -700</infon><infon key="fpage">698</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1614516</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">357</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>46523</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Swaffield, J. C., Melcher, K., and Johnston, S. A.  ()    -91</infon><infon key="fpage">88</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7870180</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">374</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>46524</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ferdous, A., Gonzalez, F., Sun, L., Kodadek, T., and Johnston, S.  A. ()    -991</infon><infon key="fpage">981</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11389845</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>46525</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gonzalez, F., Delahodde, A., Kodadek, T., and Johnston, S. A.  ()     -550</infon><infon key="fpage">548</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11964484</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">296</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>46526</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lee, D., Ezhkova, E., Li, B., Pattenden, S. G., Tansey, W. P., and  Workman, J. L. ()     -436</infon><infon key="fpage">423</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16269334</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">123</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46527</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ferdous, A., Sikder, D., Gillette, T., Nalley, K., Kodadek, T., and  Johnston, S. A. ()    -123</infon><infon key="fpage">112</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17167105</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>46528</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lassot, I., Latreille, D., Rousset, E., Sourisseau, M., Linares, L.  K., Chable-Bessia, C., Coux, O., Benkirane, M., and Kiernan, R. E.  ()    -383</infon><infon key="fpage">369</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17289585</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">25</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>46529</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Temussi, P. A., Masino, L., and Pastore, A. ()     -361</infon><infon key="fpage">355</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12554637</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>46530</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kelly, J. W. ()    -106</infon><infon key="fpage">101</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9519302</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Struct.  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>46531</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Uversky, V. N., and Fink, A. L. ()      -153</infon><infon key="fpage">131</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15134647</infon><infon key="source">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1698</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46532</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chiti, F., and Dobson, C. M. ()    -366</infon><infon key="fpage">333</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16756495</infon><infon key="source">Annu.  Rev. Biochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">75</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>46533</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Cohen, F. E., and Kelly, J. W. ()     -909</infon><infon key="fpage">905</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14685252</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">426</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>46534</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chen, S., Ferrone, F. A., and Wetzel, R. ()      -11889</infon><infon key="fpage">11884</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12186976</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">99</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>46535</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lunkes, A., Lindenberg, K. S., Ben-Haiem, L., Weber, C., Devys, D.,  Landwehrmeyer, G. B., Mandel, J. L., and Trottier, Y. ()     -269</infon><infon key="fpage">259</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12191472</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>46536</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bhattacharyya, A., Thakur, A. K., Chellgren, V. M., Thiagarajan,  G., Williams, A. D., Chellgren, B. W., Creamer, T. P., and Wetzel, R.  ()     -535</infon><infon key="fpage">524</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16321399</infon><infon key="source">J. Mol. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">355</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>46537</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dehay, B., and Bertolotti, A. ()    -35615</infon><infon key="fpage">35608</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16973603</infon><infon key="source">J.  Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>46538</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Duennwald, M. L., Jagadish, S., Muchowski, P. J., and Lindquist, S.  ()     -11050</infon><infon key="fpage">11045</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16832050</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>46539</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Darnell, G., Orgel, J. P., Pahl, R., and Meredith, S. C.  ()     -704</infon><infon key="fpage">688</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17945257</infon><infon key="source">J. Mol. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">374</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>46540</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Young, J. C., Agashe, V. R., Siegers, K., and Hartl, F. U.  ()    -791</infon><infon key="fpage">781</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15459659</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46541</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Scherzinger, E., Lurz, R., Turmaine, M., Mangiarini, L.,  Hollenbach, B., Hasenbank, R., Bates, G. P., Davies, S. W., Lehrach, H., and  Wanker, E. E. ()    -558</infon><infon key="fpage">549</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9267034</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">90</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>46542</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hoffner, G., Kahlem, P., and Djian, P. ()     -948</infon><infon key="fpage">941</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11870213</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">115</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>46543</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wanker, E. E., Scherzinger, E., Heiser, V., Sittler, A., Eickhoff,  H., and Lehrach, H. ()    -386</infon><infon key="fpage">375</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10507036</infon><infon key="source">Methods  Enzymol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">309</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>46544</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kisselev, A. F., and Goldberg, A. L. ()     -378</infon><infon key="fpage">364</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16275343</infon><infon key="source">Methods Enzymol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">398</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46545</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Krobitsch, S., and Lindquist, S. ()      -1594</infon><infon key="fpage">1589</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10677504</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>46546</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Martin, J., Gruber, M., and Lupas, A. N. ()     -458</infon><infon key="fpage">455</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15337117</infon><infon key="source">Trends Biochem. Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">29</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46547</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Schirmer, E. C., Homann, O. R., Kowal, A. S., and Lindquist, S.  ()     -2072</infon><infon key="fpage">2061</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14978213</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Biol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46548</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Schmidt, T., Lindenberg, K. S., Krebs, A., Schols, L., Laccone, F.,  Herms, J., Rechsteiner, M., Riess, O., and Landwehrmeyer, G. B.  ()    -310</infon><infon key="fpage">302</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11891825</infon><infon key="source">Ann. Neurol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">51</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>46549</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rubin, D. M., Glickman, M. H., Larsen, C. N., Dhruvakumar, S., and  Finley, D. ()     -4919</infon><infon key="fpage">4909</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9724628</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>46550</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Igarashi, S., Morita, H., Bennett, K. M., Tanaka, Y., Engelender,  S., Peters, M. F., Cooper, J. K., Wood, J. D., Sawa, A., and Ross, C. A.  ()    -568</infon><infon key="fpage">565</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12657886</infon><infon key="source">Neuroreport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>46551</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lunkes, A., and Mandel, J. L. ()    -1361</infon><infon key="fpage">1355</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9700187</infon><infon key="source">Hum.  Mol. Genet.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>46552</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hoyt, M. A., Zhang, M., and Coffino, P. ()     -413</infon><infon key="fpage">399</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16275346</infon><infon key="source">Methods Enzymol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">398</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46553</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Baker, S. P., and Grant, P. A. ()     -363</infon><infon key="fpage">361</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16269325</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">123</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46554</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Vernace, V. A., Arnaud, L., Schmidt-Glenewinkel, T., and  Figueiredo-Pereira, M. E. ()     -2682</infon><infon key="fpage">2672</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17413001</infon><infon key="source">FASEB J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>46555</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Braun, B. C., Glickman, M., Kraft, R., Dahlmann, B., Kloetzel, P.  M., Finley, D., and Schmidt, M. ()    -226</infon><infon key="fpage">221</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10559920</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Cell  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>46556</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zouambia, M., Fischer, D. F., Hobo, B., De Vos, R. A., Hol, E. M.,  Varndell, I. M., Sheppard, P. W., and Van Leeuwen, F. W. ()     -1236</infon><infon key="fpage">1221</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18283660</infon><infon key="source">Proteomics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>46557</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Masino, L., Kelly, G., Leonard, K., Trottier, Y., and Pastore, A.  ()     -272</infon><infon key="fpage">267</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11904162</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">513</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>46558</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rousseau, E., Dehay, B., Ben-Haiem, L., Trottier, Y., Morange, M.,  and Bertolotti, A. ()    -9653</infon><infon key="fpage">9648</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15210964</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>46559</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Asher, G., Bercovich, Z., Tsvetkov, P., Shaul, Y., and Kahana, C.  ()    -655</infon><infon key="fpage">645</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15749015</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>46560</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>46561</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: HD, Huntington disease; Htt, huntingtin;  ATPgammaS, adenosine 5'-O-(thiotriphosphate); SCA-3,  spinocerebellar ataxia type 3; CP, core particle; RP, regulatory particles;  GFP, green fluorescent protein; GST, glutathione S-transferase; ODC,  ornithine decarboxylase; siRNA, small interfering RNA.</text></passage></document></collection>
