<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19074149</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M805302200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2640969</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19074149</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">4689</infon><infon key="fpage">4689</infon><infon key="issue">7</infon><infon key="lpage">4694</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Li;given-names:Tianbo</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Yang;given-names:Youshan</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Canessa;given-names:Cecilia M.</infon><infon key="p">Author's Choice:Final version full  access.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Interaction of the Aromatics Tyr-72/Trp-288 in the Interface of the  Extracellular and Transmembrane Domains Is Essential for Proton Gating of  Acid-sensing Ion  Channels*</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>172</offset><text>Acid-sensing ion channels are proton-activated ion channels expressed in  the nervous system. They belong to the family of ENaC/Degenerins whose members  share a conserved structure but are activated by widely diverse stimuli. We  show that interaction of two aromatic residues, Tyr-72, located immediately  after the first transmembrane segment, and Trp-288, located at the tip of a  loop of the extracellular domain directed toward the first transmembrane  segment, is essential for proton activation of the acid-sensing ion channels.  The subdomain containing Trp-288 is a module tethered to the rest of the  extracellular domain by short linkers and intrasubunit interactions between  residues in the putative &quot;proton sensor.&quot; Mutations in these two  areas shift the apparent affinity of protons toward a more acidic range and  change the kinetics of activation and desensitization. These results are  consisting with displacement of the module relative to the rest of the  extracellular domain to allow interaction of Trp-288 with Tyr-72 during  gating. We propose that such interaction may provide functional coupling  between the extracellular domain and the pore domain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1351</offset><text>The acid-sensing ion channels  (ASICs)2 are  voltage-insensitive sodium channels turned on and off by extracellular  protons. Four ASIC genes in the human genome, ASIC1 to ASIC4, give rise to at  least six isoforms that associate in various combinations to form channels  with different functional properties  (1,  2). The ASICs constitute a  distinct group in the large family of channels known as Degenerins  characterized by a common structure but widely diverse gating stimuli:  mechanical forces (3),  neuropeptides (4,  5), protons  (6), or no stimulus at all,  such as ENaC, which exhibits constitutive activity  (7). The structure shared by  all Degenerins consists of two transmembrane segments, TM1 and TM2, a large  extracellular domain, and short cytoplasmic amino and carboxyl termini. The  recently published crystal structure of a truncated chicken ASIC1 (cASIC1) at  a resolution of 1.9 A (8)  shows that ASIC1 is a trimer, and it provides detailed structure of the large  extracellular domain that is crucial for understanding the gating mechanism of  the ASICs. A feature revealed by the atomic structure is a cluster of  negatively and one positively charged residue in the interface of subdomain D  (Arg-191), subdomain E (Asp-238 and Glu-239), and subdomain F (Asp-346 and  Asp-350) (see Fig. 1A)  that was hypothesized to constitute the proton sensor. Furthermore, it was  proposed that binding of protons to this site displaces subdomain F toward TM1  to open the pore (8).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2848</offset><text>Although the solved atomic structure of cASIC1 provides a valuable tool to  advance the understanding of how external protons activate the ASICs, it  represents only a snapshot of the gating process thereby additional  experimental evidence is needed to elucidate the gating mechanism. The general  idea that conformational changes triggered by binding of the specific agonist  to the extracellular domain of a ligand activated channel need to be  transmitted to the transmembrane domain, where the pore gate is located, draws  attention to the pair of closely located residues, Tyr-72 and Trp-288, as they  provide a potential contact site between the extracellular and the  transmembrane domains.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3547</offset><text>This study examines the functional role of the conserved residues, Tyr-72  and Trp-288, that are located distantly in the primary sequence but are  brought to close proximity (~3.7 A) by the folding of the  extracellular domain (ECD). This arrangement could provide a contact site  between the ECD and TM1 whereby a conformation change of the ECD is  transmitted to the pore gate in the transmembrane domain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>3956</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3980</offset><text>Electrophysiology and Two-electrode Voltage Clamp of  Oocytes:Xenopus laevis oocytes were injected with 5 ng of  cRNA in a volume of 50 nl and used after 2-4 days of incubation at 16  C.  For two-electrode voltage clamp experiments, oocytes were placed in a  recording chamber (400 mul) perfused by gravity at a rate of 4 ml/min.  Oocytes were impaled with two glass microelectrodes filled with 3 m  KCl having a resistance lower than 1 megaohm. Membrane potential was held at  -60 mV, and whole-cell currents were recorded with a Clamp OC-725B (Warner  Instrument Corp., Hamden, CT) and digitized at a sampling rate of 2 kHz  (PowerLab/200, ADInstruments). Composition of the standard bath solution was  120 mm NaCl, 3 mm KCl, 2 mm CaCl2,  10 mm HEPES-MES adjusted to pH 7.4. Activating solutions were  administered by a perfusion system positioned directly in front of the oocyte.  Composition of activating solutions was 120 mm NaCl, 2  mm KCl, 1 mm CaCl2, 10 mm  HEPES-MES or 10 mm MES adjusted to pH 7.2-4.0.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>4994</offset><text>Ribbon representation of chicken ASIC1 structure. a, a  single subunit is shown for simplicity with subdomains, A to F, indicated in  different colors. The arrow points to the putative proton sensor with  side chains of charged residues represented as sticks. Amino acids  important for ASIC1 gating that were mutated in this study are also shown. The  image was obtained with the molecular graphics program Chimera. b,  amino acid sequence of subdomain F loop. Residues conserved in all ASIC  proteins are in red.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5509</offset><text>Patch Clamp:Currents from outside-out patches were recorded  with an EPC-9 amplifier and the Pulse acquisition program (HEKA Electronic).  Patch pipettes were pulled from PG150T glass (Warner Instruments) to tip  diameters of 2-5 mum after heat polishing. Bath solution for patch clamp  recording was 120 mm NaCl, 3 mm KCl, 2 mm  CaCl2, and 10 mm HEPES adjusted to pH 7.4. The pipette  solution was of identical composition as the bath, but it did not contain  CaCl2. Activating solutions were buffered with MES to pH 7.2, 7.0.  6.5, 6.0, 5.0, or 4.0. Application of activation solutions was performed using  the SF 77A Perfusion Fast-Step device (Warner Instruments) under control of  the program Pulse.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6214</offset><text>Calculation of Apparent pH50:Oocytes were exposed  sequentially to solutions of decreasing pH from 7.2 to 4.0. Between test  applications, oocytes were perfused with solution of pH 7.4 for at least 30 s  to recover from desensitization. If possible, each oocyte was tested twice  with the whole range of pH solutions. The average of the peak currents from  each pH was normalized to the value of pH that produced maximal current. The  mean and standard deviation were obtained, and the pH50 was  calculated according to the equation I = 1/(1 +  (EC50/[H])n), where I is the  normalized value for the test pH, EC50 is the concentration of  protons that induces half-maximal currents, and n is the Hill  coefficient. KaleidaGraph (Synergy Software) was used to draw graphs and for  curve-fitting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7009</offset><text>Desensitization Rates:The desensitization rate was  calculated by fitting the decay of proton-activated currents from outside-out  patches to a single exponential.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7173</offset><text>DNA Constructs and Site-directed Mutagenesis:Rat ASIC1a cDNA  was modified by the addition of a V5 tag at the carboxyl terminus. Mutations  were introduced in the sequence of rASIC1a, ASIC2a, and ASIC3 and rat alpha,  beta, and gamma ENaC subunits using QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis  kit (Stratagene). All cDNAs were sequenced to confirm the presence of the  mutations.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7551</offset><text>Surface Biotinylation and Western Blotting:Oocytes injected  with wild type or mutant rASIC1 cRNAs were surface-biotinylated as previously  described (9). Cells were  homogenized in 1% Triton X-100 and cleared by centrifugation, and the  biotinylated proteins were recovered with streptavidin beads (Pierce).  Proteins were resolved by electrophoresis on 10% SDS-PAGE, transferred to  Immobilon membranes, and processed for Western blotting with anti-V5  monoclonal antibody (Invitrogen).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>8040</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8048</offset><text>Residues Tyr-72 and Trp-288 Are Essential for ASIC  Function:The residue Tyr-72, located in the tether after TM1, and  Trp-288, at the tip of the loop of subdomain F  (Fig. 1a), are in  close proximity in the crystal structure of cASIC1. Substitution of any of  them by Gly in rat ASIC1 makes channels unresponsive to pH as low as 4.0. The  same positions were subsequently replaced by amino acids with different side  chains as indicated in Table 1.  Aromatic amino acids, Y, F, W, or H and swapping of the residues to Trp-72 and  Tyr-288 produced functional channels (Fig.  2A). By contrast, small or large aliphatic side chains,  proline, or negatively charged residues eliminated proton-induced currents.  Histidine substitutions in 72 and 288 and arginine in position 72 (Y72R), but  not in position 288 (W288R), retained channel function. However, all these  functional mutant channels expressed lower proton sensitivity and faster  desensitization rate than WT ASIC1 (Table  1 and Fig. 2).  Lysine, another positively charged residue, introduced in position 72 or 288  produced channels unresponsive to pH 4.0.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>9166</offset><text>The numbers represent the mean +- S.D. whole-cell currents  elicited by pH 6.0 of at least 10 independent oocytes</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>9280</offset><text>   Mutant Current Mutant Current     muA   muA   WT    13 +- 5       Y72F    15 +- 4    W288F    14 +- 3     Y72W    11 +- 6    W288Y    10 +- 5     Y72H    4 +-  0.6a  W288H    18 +- 5     Y72R    8 +- 3    W288R    0     Y72K    0    W288K    0     Y72G    0    W288G    0     Y72A    0    W288A    0     Y72L    0    W288L    0     Y72V    0    W288V    0     Y72T    0    W288T    0     Y72P    0    W288P    0     Y72E    0    W288E    0     Y72C    0    Y72C/W288H    0     Y72Q    0    W288Q    0     L284A    15 +- 4.5    Y72W/W288Y    17 +- 6     L284P    0    Y72H/W288H    0.9 +-  0.3a   P285Q/A    14 +- 5    Y72R/W288H    0.7 +-  0.2a    P287Q/A     0     P365A     2.6 +-  1.5a</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_footnote</infon><offset>9972</offset><text>p &lt; 0.001, statistically significant difference compared to  WT.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10037</offset><text>The absence of ASIC1 current induced by the former mutations was not  explained by intracellular retention of the mutant channels because  biotinylation of surface proteins revealed equal amounts of rASIC1 protein in  the plasma membrane of cells expressing wild type or mutants Gly-72 or Gly-288  as indicated by Western blotting (Fig.  2D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10380</offset><text>As aromatic amino acids at positions corresponding to 72 and 288 in ASIC1  are present in other Degenerins, from Caenorhabditis elegans to  humans, we examined whether those residues are also essential for function in  other channels. Substitution of either one the aromatic residues by Ala or Gly  in rat ASIC2a and ASIC3 also produced non-functional channels.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>10742</offset><text>Functional effect of mutations in rat ASIC1. A, whole-cell  currents of oocytes expressing wild type or mutant rASIC1 with aromatic  residues in positions 72 and 288 stimulated with solution of pH 6.0. Bars  above current traces indicate the duration of the test pH. B,  family of currents elicited by changes in external pH of ASIC1 WT and mutant  Y72R. C, table showing average values for the time constant of  desensitization (taud) of wild type and mutants Y72R and  Y72H obtained at various values of external pH (pHo).  D, Western blot analysis of surface-biotinylated and total ASIC1  proteins of wild type and nonfunctional mutants. E, representative  current trace of ENaC mutant channels carrying Ala in the corresponding  positions 72 and 288 of ASIC1. The dotted line indicates the zero  current level, and the bars above the current trace represent  application to the bath of the specific blocker amiloride. Membrane holding  potential was -60 mV. Bath solution contained 120 mm NaCl, pH 7.4.  F, currents of mutant ASIC1-P365A show decreased in the magnitude of  the peak current, slow rates of activation and desensitization, and impaired  recovery from desensitization. Time and current scales are shown with the  bars below each trace.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11996</offset><text>The epithelial sodium channel, ENaC, is another member of the Degenerins  and is closely related in structure to the ASICs, although it differs in means  of activation as ENaC is not gated by protons but is instead constitutively  open. Additionally, ENaC is a heterotrimer of three different subunits  alpha, betam and gamma; each of the subunits has aromatic residues in  the following positions that correspond to Tyr-72 and Trp-288 in the ASICs:  alphaTyr-138 and alphaTyr-418, betaTrp-77 and betaTyr-356, and  gammaTyr-79 and gammaTyr-370. Substitution for alanine of all six aromatic  residues and expression in oocytes of the double mutants alpha, beta, and  gamma produced large non-desensitizing inward currents completely blocked by  the specific inhibitor amiloride, wild type 22 +- 6 (n = 12),  and mutant 26 +- 8 (n = 12)  (Fig. 2E).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12843</offset><text>These results indicate that aromatic residues or arginine must occupy  position 72, and only aromatic residues must be in position 288 to maintain  proton sensitivity of the ASICs. The same pair of aromatic residues in the  structurally related ENaC channel is not essential for function.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13132</offset><text>Functional Channels with Histidine or Arginine  Substitutions:As indicated, all the aromatic residues Tyr, Phe,  Trp, including His, at positions 72 and 288 produced channels responsive to  protons, but only Tyr, Phe, and Trp maintained the functional properties of  ASIC1 wild type. Substitutions by His shifted the sensitivity to protons  toward more acidic pH and decreased the magnitude of the peak currents, in  particular Y72H and the double mutant Y72H/W288H. The average magnitude of the  peak current at pH 5.0 was 18 +- 5, 4 +- 0.6, and 0.9 +- 0.3  muA/oocyte for mutant channels W288H, Y72H, and Y72H/W288H, respectively  (Table 1). Rates of  desensitization were in average 3-fold faster in the mutant Y72H than in WT  channels. Fig. 2C  shows the calculated time constant of desensitization  (taud) obtained from multichannel patches in the  outside-out configuration. The apparent pH50 was 5.2 for Y72R  compared with 6.6 for WT ASIC1 (Fig.  2B). We also observed a 3-fold faster desensitization  rate in ASIC1-Y72R for all tested pH values  (Fig. 2C).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14199</offset><text>These findings show that the imidazole ring can substitute at least in part  for other canonical aromatic rings but at the expense of decreasing proton  sensitivity. Also significant is the no-additive effects of His in positions  72 and 288, suggesting that these two residues may interact functionally.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14504</offset><text>Functional Interaction of Histidine Residues in Positions 72 and  288:Functional interaction between two residues can be measured by  quantitatively comparing the properties of the two singly substituted proteins  with that of the protein containing both mutations. If the sum of the effects  of two single substitutions equals the change seen in the double mutant, then  the residues at these two positions do not interact. If the effects are not  additive, the two amino acids must interact either directly or indirectly  (10,  11).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>15039</offset><text>Double mutant cycle analysis of rASIC1 His mutants in positions 72 and  288. A, thermodynamic mutant cycle where X1, X2, Y1, and  Y2 represent change in apparent proton affinity along the arrow.  B, family of currents induced by lowering the external pH for mutant  channels Y72H and W288H. C, proton activation curves for the channels  comprising the thermodynamic mutant cycle shown in A. D, coupling  coefficient Omega calculated from the apparent EC50 corresponding  to wild type and the single and double His mutants.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15562</offset><text>Double-mutant cycle analysis is a formal way of quantifying the  independence of two mutations in their effects on the function of a protein  (12). The square in  Fig. 3 describes the double  mutant cycle relating wild type, single mutants (Y72H or W288H), and double  mutant (Y72H/W288H) channels. Each arrow number represents the factor  by which proton affinity changes along the direction of the arrow. For  instance, X1 equals EC50WT/EC50Y72H. The  affinity change in going from WT to double mutant must be the same regardless  of the pathway; hence, X1Y1 = X2Y2. Following the same  approach previously used to examine the interaction of a scorpion toxin with  the Shaker potassium channel  (13), we define the coupling  coefficient, Omega, as    If the two mutated residues are independent of one another, then Omega will  be unity. If the resides interact and the mutations alter their interaction,  then Omega will deviate from unity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16506</offset><text>The concentrations of protons to achieve half-maximal activation, expressed  in mol, were 2.19 x 10-7 for WT, 3.72 x 10-6  for Y72H, 2.06 x 10-6 for W288H, and 3.72 x  10-6 for the double mutant Y72H/W288H. Introducing these numbers in  the above equation gives a value for Omega of 0.1, significantly different  from unity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16831</offset><text>We could not apply double-mutant cycle analysis to the pair of mutations  Y72R and W288R because the latter did not respond to pH as low as 4.0,  suggesting that the mutation markedly decreased proton sensitivity of  ASIC1-W288R, shifting the pH50 into a more acidic range.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17105</offset><text>Proline 287 in the Loop Containing Trp-288 Is Essential for ASIC1  Function:The tip of subdomain F forms a sharp loop that directs  Trp-288 downward and toward Tyr-72. Most residues in this loop are conserved  in all ASIC, specifically Leu-284, Pro-285, and Pro-287 (indicated in  red, Fig.  1b). The functional effect of mutations of each of these  conserved residues is shown in Table  1. Substitution of Leu-284 by alanine was functional, but proline  in the same position abolished current. Substitutions of Pro-287 by Ala or Gln  also abolished proton-activated currents despite good levels of expression at  the cell surface (Fig.  2D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17748</offset><text>The high sensitivity to mutagenesis of this loop is unexpected given that  the side chains of these residues, with the exception of Trp-288, are not  engaged in interactions with other amino acids but are mostly surrounded by  water. This observation rather suggests that the importance of the proline  rests on correctly positioning the aromatic 288 in order to interact with the  one in position 72. This occurs by the unique property of proline to bend the  backbone of the protein, thereby changing the curvature of the loop or by  cis-trans isomerization  (14). In either case the  orientation of the aromatic ring in position 288 would be altered by the  absence of proline in 287.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18436</offset><text>The Linker Tethering Subdomain F to the Body of the Extracellular  Domain Decreases Proton-activated Currents and Slows Activation of  ASIC1:Residue Pro-365 is conserved in all the ASIC channels. It is  located in the short linker connecting subdomain F to the rest of the  extracellular domain (Fig.  1a); thereby it is poised to sense conformational changes  that may displace subdomain F during the gating process. ASIC1 channels  bearing the mutation P365A were functional but exhibited marked changes in  properties; peak currents elicited by protons were small (wild type 12  +- 5 versus 1.5 +- 0.4 muA/oocyte), and kinetics of  activation were slow (wild type 20 +- 5.4 versus 2.75 +-  1.2 s-1) as well as the desensitization rate (wild type 0.50  +- 0.05 versus 0.18 +- 0.08 s-1). Last, the  rate of recovery from desensitization was slower than in wild type channels  (Fig. 2C); indeed,  recovery from desensitization was never complete but declined progressively  until the currents disappeared even after increasing the interval between  stimuli for a period as long as 5 min (Fig.  2F). These changes in kinetics are consistent with  subdomain F being part of the transduction mechanism that translates binding  of protons to opening and closure of the pore.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19707</offset><text>Negatively Charged Residues in the Putative Proton Sensor Change the  pH50 and Desensitization Rate of ASIC1:The residues  Glu-346 and Asp-350 in subdomain F directly face Asp-238 and Glu-239 in  subdomain E and together with Arg-191 in subdomain D form a cluster of charges  at the surface of each subunit that was originally proposed to constitute the  proton sensor (Fig.  1a). Substitutions of Glu-346 and Asp-350 by Ala  maintained functional channels, but the rates of desensitization became faster  (wild type 0.48 +- 0.08 s-1 versus D350A 2.3  +- 0.07 s-1), and the apparent affinity for protons decreased  (wild type pH50 6.8 +- 0.5 versus D350A  pH50 5.5 +- 0.6) (Fig. 4,  A and B). Removal of the remaining charged  residues, Asp-238, Glu-239, and Arg-191, further shifted the apparent  pH50 of activation toward more acidic pH, but mutant channels still  retained the property of being activated by protons. Together these results  indicate that protonation of residues in the intrasubunit interface of  subdomains F and D affects the conformational changes of activation and,  therefore, contributes to the apparent affinity for protons. Although each of  these residues plays a role in defining the functional properties of wild type  ASIC1, none singly nor all five together are sufficient to confer proton  sensitivity to the channel (8,  15); other residues must  participate in making the &quot;proton sensor.&quot;</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>21131</offset><text>Functional effects of amino acid substitutions in putative proton  sensor. A, representative current traces of channels with  additive substitutions of charged residues in the proton sensor for alanine  elicited by pH 6.0. Rates of desensitization lambdad  (-s) at pH 6.0 were: WT = 0.45 +- 0.08; R191A = 0.47 +-  0.11; D237A/E238A = 0.50 +- 0.09; E346A/D350A = 2.5 +- 0.1;  D237A/E238A/E346A/D350A = 2.43 +- 0.1; D237/E238/E346A/D350A/R191A = 2.8  +- 0.1. B, pH response curves. Lines are fits to the Hill  function. n = 6-8 oocytes per data point.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>21681</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21692</offset><text>This study shows that residues Tyr-72 and Trp-288 are essential for proton  gating of the ASICs. As any combination of aromatic residues (Trp, Tyr, Phe,  or His) when present in these two positions was able to keep ASIC responsive  to protons, it is reasonable to conclude that the aromatic side chains in  positions 72 and 288 interact and that the interaction is essential to  preserve functional channels. All other mutants carrying nonaromatic residues,  with the exception of Arg in position 72, did not open with a pH as low as  4.0, consistent with the notion that an aromatic-aromatic interaction, also  termed pi-pi interaction, provides the lowest energy barrier between two  functional states. Further evidence comes from double cycle mutant analysis  conducted with channels having His in positions 72 and 288. These channels  were functional but had reduced apparent affinity for protons. Of  significance, the effect of the mutations on the apparent pH50 was  not additive, consistent with functional interaction between residues 72 and  288. The finding that His mutants exhibited lower affinity for protons  indicates that the pi-pi interaction comprising imidazole rings is not as  favorable as when it occurs between Tyr-, Phe, or Trp. We, therefore,  interpret the absence of current when other residues occupy positions 72 or  288 to be the result of a shift in the apparent pH50 toward a very  acidic range (lower than pH 4.0) because of a high energy barrier between  states. Such a shift prevented reaching enough low pH to open the mutant  channels without damaging the oocytes. This interpretation is favored over  disruption of channel structure or misfolding induced by the mutations because  of robust surface expression of mutant channels, functional channels carrying  arginine (Y72R) despite marked differences in properties between the side  chain of arginine and aromatic amino acids, and because the corresponding  mutations in ENaC, a channel structurally related to ASIC but not gated by  protons, retained function.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23745</offset><text>Aromatic-aromatic interactions contribute to maintaining tertiary and  quaternary structure of proteins by stabilizing contacts between subdomains  and between proteins within a complex. Aromatic-aromatic interactions are  characterized by a competition between the stacked and the T-shaped  geometries, the latter being more frequent in proteins  (16). In the T-shape structure  the planes of the ring are perpendicular to each other, and in the  intermediate stacked, &quot;edge-displaced,&quot; the ring planes are  parallel-displaced. This competition is strongly affected by polarity of the  environment and the ability of the surrounding solvent to form hydrogen bonds.  In the crystal structure of cASIC1, Tyr-72 and Trp-288 adopt a T-shape  structure; whether this geometry changes in the open, closed, and desensitized  states is not known, although the binding energy differences for Tyr/Trp pair  would be in the order of 1 kcal/mol going from T-shaped to intermediate  stacked and 1.6 kcal/mol to the staked geometry according to previous  calculations (17). These  values are in the range of energy change between the open and close  conformations of ASIC1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24906</offset><text>The observation that pH solutions in the range of 6.0 to 4.0 open the  mutant Y72R, but not Y72K or W288R, indicates that Arg in position 72 can  functionally replace one of the aromatic rings in the pair. An explanation for  such an unexpected finding is that the positively charged side chain of Arg  can interact with the aromatic ring in 288, replacing the pi-pi  interaction for a cation-pi interaction  (18). In the cation-pi  interaction, side chains of aromatic amino acids provide a surface of negative  electrostatic potential that can bind to cations through a predominantly  electrostatic interaction. This is possible only when arginine is in position  72 because here the arginine side chain would point to the aromatic ring,  whereas arginine in position 288 would point its side chain away from Tyr-72  (Fig. 5). The preference of  arginine over lysine can be explained by the fact that the face of the  guanidinium ion of arginine is to some extent hydrophobic, thereby preferred  by the innately hydrophobic aromatic  (19).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>25948</offset><text>Representation of Arg in positions 72 and 288 in ASIC1. The figure  was obtained by substituting Tyr-72 and Trp-288 in the crystal structure of  chicken ASIC1 by Arg to illustrate the relative position of the positively  charged side chain with respect to the opposite aromatic residue.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26235</offset><text>Additional evidence for the importance of correct positioning of the  aromatic rings in the Tyr-72/Trp-28 pair was provided by mutations in the loop  holding Trp-288. This loop exhibits a tight bend in the crystal structure  because of the presence of several conserved prolines that when mutated also  abolish current, suggesting that the curvature of the loop or  cis-trans isomerization of the prolines  (14) positions the aromatic  ring of amino acid 288 to allow interaction with the aromatic at position  72.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26750</offset><text>The prediction that Trp-288 may move together with subdomain F during the  gating process was supported indirectly by changes in apparent pH50  and kinetics induced by point mutations in sites of contact of subdomain F  with the rest of the ECD; i.e. the interface of subdomains F and E;  the first through carbonyl-carboxylate interactions of residues Asp-346 with  Asp-238 and Asp-350 with Glu-239 and the second through Pro-365, in a  hinge-like structure connecting subdomain F to the rest of the ECD.  Furthermore, our findings are in agreement with the recently published  molecular dynamic analysis of cASIC1  (20). A simulation in which  Ca2+ ions bound to the proton sensor were displaced by protons  unveil conformational changes in subdomain F (thumb domain) that were largest  in the loop containing Trp-288. Our results are somewhat reminiscent of the  Cys-loop ligand-activated receptors, where the importance of the interface of  the extracellular with the transmembrane domain in communicating  conformational changes initiated in the ligand binding site to the gate of the  pore has been demonstrated  (21).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27875</offset><text>We conclude that an aromatic interaction between Tyr-72 and Trp-288 is  required for conferring proton sensitivity to the ASICs, most likely by  stabilizing a conformation that promotes channel opening. Residues in the  putative proton sensor and in the tethers that connect subdomain F to the rest  of the body of the extracellular domain contribute to move subdomain F;  thereby the aromatic ring of Trp-288 is placed in a position that allows it to  interact with Tyr-72. Together these findings provide experimental support for  the proposal that subdomain F is involved in ASIC1 gating.</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wemmie, J. A., Price, M. P., and Welsh, M. J. ()     -586</infon><infon key="fpage">578</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16891000</infon><infon key="source">Trends Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">29</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>28467</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhang, P., and Canessa, C. M. ()    -566</infon><infon key="fpage">553</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12356856</infon><infon key="source">J.  Gen. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">120</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>28468</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">O'Hagan, R., Chalfie, M., and Goodman, M. B. ()     -50</infon><infon key="fpage">43</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15580270</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>28469</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lingueglia, E., Champigny, G., Lazdunski, M., and Barbry, P.  ()     -733</infon><infon key="fpage">730</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7501021</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">378</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>28470</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Golubovic, A., Kuhn, A., Williamson, M., Kalbacher, H., Holstein,  T. W., Grimmelikhuijzen, C. J., and Grunder, S. ()     -35103</infon><infon key="fpage">35098</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17911098</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">282</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>28471</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Waldmann, R., Champigny, G., Bassilana, F., Heurteaux, C., and  Lazdunski, M. ()     -177</infon><infon key="fpage">173</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9062189</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">386</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>28472</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Canessa, C. M., Schild, L., Buell, G., Thorens, B., Gautschi, I.,  Horisberger, J. D., and Rossier, B. C. ()     -467</infon><infon key="fpage">463</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8107805</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">367</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>28473</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jasti, J., Furukawa, H., Gonzales, E. B., and Gouaux, E.  ()     -323</infon><infon key="fpage">316</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17882215</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">449</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>28474</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Coric, T., Zheng, D., Gerstein, M., and Canessa, C. M.  ()     -735</infon><infon key="fpage">725</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16002453</infon><infon key="source">J. Physiol. (Lond.)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">568</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>28475</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hurle, M. R., Tweedy, N. B., and Matthews, C. R.  ()     -6360</infon><infon key="fpage">6356</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3539187</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">25</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>28476</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Perry, K. M., Onuffer, J. J., Gittelman, M. S., Barmat, L., and  Matthews, C. R. ()     -7968</infon><infon key="fpage">7961</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2692706</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">28</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>28477</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Horovitz, A., and Fersht, A. R. ()    -617</infon><infon key="fpage">613</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2388258</infon><infon key="source">J.  Mol. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">214</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>28478</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hidalgo, P., and MacKinnon, R. ()     -310</infon><infon key="fpage">307</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7716527</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">268</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>28479</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lummis, S. C. R., Beene, D. L., Lee, L. W., Lester, H. A.,  Broadhurst, R. W., and Dougherty, D. A. ()     -252</infon><infon key="fpage">248</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16281040</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">438</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>28480</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Paukert, M., Chen, X., Polleichtner, G., Schindelin, H., and  Grunder, S. ()     -581</infon><infon key="fpage">572</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17981796</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>28481</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Burley, S. K., and Petsko, G. A. ()     -28</infon><infon key="fpage">23</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3892686</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">229</infon><infon key="year">1985</infon><offset>28482</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gervasio, F. L., Chelli, R., Procacci, P., and Schettino, V.  ()    -125</infon><infon key="fpage">117</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12012343</infon><infon key="source">Proteins</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">48</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>28483</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dougherty, D. A. ()     -168</infon><infon key="fpage">163</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8539615</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>28484</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dougherty, D. A. ()   Suppl 1,  -1508</infon><infon key="fpage">1504</infon><infon key="source">J.  Nutr.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">137</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>28485</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shaikh, S. A., and Tajkhorshid, E. ()     -5164</infon><infon key="fpage">5153</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18790845</infon><infon key="source">Biophys. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">95</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>28486</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bouzat, C., Gumilar, F., Spitzmaul, G., Wang, H. L., Rayes, D.,  Hansen, S. B., Taylor, P., and Sine, S. M. ()     -900</infon><infon key="fpage">896</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15318223</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">430</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>28487</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>28488</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: ASIC, acid-sensing ion channel; cASIC, chicken  ASIC; rASIC, rat ASIC; ECD, extracellular domain; MES,  4-morpholineethanesulfonic acid; WT, wild type.</text></passage></document></collection>
