<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19116207</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M805587200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2643496</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19116207</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">5186</infon><infon key="fpage">5186</infon><infon key="issue">8</infon><infon key="lpage">5194</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rosker;given-names:Christian</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Meur;given-names:Gargi</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Taylor;given-names:Emily J. A.</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Taylor;given-names:Colin W.</infon><infon key="p">Author's Choice:Final version full  access.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Functional Ryanodine Receptors in the Plasma Membrane of RINm5F  Pancreatic  beta-Cells*S</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>90</offset><text>Ryanodine receptors (RyR) are Ca2+ channels that mediate  Ca2+ release from intracellular stores in response to diverse  intracellular signals. In RINm5F insulinoma cells, caffeine, and  4-chloro-m-cresol (4CmC), agonists of RyR, stimulated Ca2+  entry that was independent of store-operated Ca2+ entry, and  blocked by prior incubation with a concentration of ryanodine that inactivates  RyR. Patch-clamp recording identified small numbers of large-conductance  (gammaK = 169 pS) cation channels that were activated by  caffeine, 4CmC or low concentrations of ryanodine. Similar channels were  detected in rat pancreatic beta-cells. In RINm5F cells, the channels were  blocked by cytosolic, but not extracellular, ruthenium red. Subcellular  fractionation showed that type 3 IP3 receptors (IP3R3)  were expressed predominantly in endoplasmic reticulum, whereas RyR2 were  present also in plasma membrane fractions. Using RNAi selectively to reduce  expression of RyR1, RyR2, or IP3R3, we showed that RyR2 mediates  both the Ca2+ entry and the plasma membrane currents evoked by  agonists of RyR. We conclude that small numbers of RyR2 are selectively  expressed in the plasma membrane of RINm5F pancreatic beta-cells, where they  mediate Ca2+ entry.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1341</offset><text>Ryanodine receptors  (RyR)3 and inositol  1,4,5-trisphosphate receptors (IP3R)  (1,  2) are the archetypal  intracellular Ca2+ channels. Both are widely expressed, although  RyR are more restricted in their expression than IP3R  (3,  4). In common with many cells,  pancreatic beta-cells and insulin-secreting cell lines express both  IP3R (predominantly IP3R3)  (5,  6) and RyR (predominantly RyR2)  (7). Both RyR and  IP3R are expressed mostly within membranes of the endoplasmic (ER),  where they mediate release of Ca2+. Functional RyR are also  expressed in the secretory vesicles  (8,  9) or, and perhaps more likely,  in the endosomes of beta-cells  (10). Despite earlier  suggestions (11),  IP3R are probably not present in the secretory vesicles of  beta-cells (8,  12,  13).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2126</offset><text>All three subtypes of IP3R are stimulated by IP3 with  Ca2+ (1), and the  three subtypes of RyR are each directly regulated by Ca2+. However,  RyR differ in whether their most important physiological stimulus is  depolarization of the plasma membrane (RyR1), Ca2+ (RyR2) or  additional intracellular messengers like cyclic ADP-ribose. The latter  stimulates both Ca2+ release and insulin secretion in beta-cells  (8,  14). The activities of both  families of intracellular Ca2+ channels are also modulated by many  additional signals that act directly or via phosphorylation  (15,  16). Although they commonly  mediate release of Ca2+ from the ER, both IP3R and RyR  select rather poorly between Ca2+ and other cations (permeability  ratio, PCa/PK ~7)  (1,  17). This may allow  electrogenic Ca2+ release from the ER to be rapidly compensated by  uptake of K+ (18),  and where RyR or IP3R are expressed in other membranes it may allow  them to affect membrane potential.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3097</offset><text>Both Ca2+ entry and release of Ca2+ from  intracellular stores contribute to the oscillatory increases in cytosolic  Ca2+ concentration ([Ca2+]i) that  stimulate exocytosis of insulin-containing vesicles in pancreatic beta-cells  (7). Glucose rapidly  equilibrates across the plasma membrane (PM) of beta-cells and its oxidative  metabolism by mitochondria increases the cytosolic ATP/ADP ratio, causing  KATP channels to close  (19). This allows an  unidentified leak current to depolarize the PM  (20) and activate  voltage-gated Ca2+ channels, predominantly L-type Ca2+  channels (21). The resulting  Ca2+ entry is amplified by Ca2+-induced Ca2+  release from intracellular stores  (7), triggering exocytotic  release of insulin-containing dense-core vesicles  (22). The importance of this  sequence is clear from the widespread use of sulfonylurea drugs, which close  KATP channels, in the treatment of type 2 diabetes. Ca2+  uptake by mitochondria beneath the PM further stimulates ATP production,  amplifying the initial response to glucose and perhaps thereby contributing to  the sustained phase of insulin release  (23). However, neither the  increase in [Ca2+]i nor the insulin release  evoked by glucose or other nutrients is entirely dependent on Ca2+  entry (7,  24) or closure of  KATP channels (25).  This suggests that glucose metabolism may also more directly activate RyR  (7,  26) and/or IP3R  (27) to cause release of  Ca2+ from intracellular stores. A change in the ATP/ADP ratio is  one means whereby nutrient metabolism may be linked to opening of  intracellular Ca2+ channels because both RyR  (28) and IP3R  (1) are stimulated by ATP.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4757</offset><text>The other major physiological regulators of insulin release are the  incretins: glucagon-like peptide-1 and glucose-dependent insulinotropic  hormone (29). These hormones,  released by cells in the small intestine, stimulate synthesis of cAMP in  beta-cells and thereby potentiate glucose-evoked insulin release  (30). These pathways are also  targets of drugs used successfully to treat type 2 diabetes  (29). The responses of  beta-cells to cAMP involve both cAMP-dependent protein kinase and epacs  (exchange factors activated by cAMP)  (31,  32). The effects of the latter  are, at least partly, due to release of Ca2+ from intracellular  stores via RyR  (33-35)  and perhaps also via IP3R  (36). The interplays between  Ca2+ and cAMP signaling generate oscillatory changes in the  concentrations of both messengers  (37). RyR and IP3R  are thus implicated in mediating responses to each of the major physiological  regulators of insulin secretion: glucose and incretins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5733</offset><text>Here we report that in addition to expression in intracellular stores,  which probably include both the ER and secretory vesicles and/or endosomes,  functional RyR2 are also expressed in small numbers in the PM of RINm5F  insulinoma cells and rat pancreatic beta-cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>6003</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6027</offset><text>Cell Culture:RINm5F cells were cultured at 37  C in  humidified air containing 5% CO2 in RPMI 1640 medium containing  l-glutamine (2 mm), fetal calf serum (10%), Hepes (1  mm), and 2-mercaptoethanol (50 mum). Cells were  passaged every 3-4 days when confluent.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6288</offset><text>Isolation of Rat Pancreatic beta-Cells:Pancreatic  beta-cells were isolated from 3-week-old, male Wistar rats by Dr. Noel Smith  (Department of Clinical Biochemistry)  (38). Briefly, the pancreas  was perfused with Hank's balanced salt solution (HBSS, Sigma) containing  collagenase P (1 mg/ml, Roche), excised and incubated at 37  C for 15 min.  The islets were then washed in cold HBSS (600 x g, 5 min) and  purified using a Histopaque discontinuous gradient (Histopaque, 1.077 g/ml;  Histopaque 1, 1.119 g/ml; Sigma). Dispersed cells were resuspended in RPMI  medium and allowed to attach to poly-d-ornithine-coated Petri  dishes for patch-clamp recordings from isolated cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6969</offset><text>Subcellular Fractionation:Confluent cells (1.2 x  106 cells) were washed twice with ice-cold phosphate-buffered  saline (PBS: 136.9 mm NaCl, 2.7 mm KCl, 1.5  mm KH2PO4, 7.7 mm  Na2HPO4, pH 7.4), scraped into 5 ml of the same medium,  centrifuged (650 x g, 5 min) and resuspended in 850 mul of  0.3 m sucrose supplemented with Hepes (10 mm, pH 7.4),  benzamidine (1 mm), NaN3 (2 mm), protease  inhibitors (1 Roche Applied Science complete protease inhibitor mini-tablet/10  ml) and dithiothreitol (5 mm). After homogenization (15 strokes in  a Dounce homogenizer) and then passage through a 25-gauge needle (30 times),  the homogenate was centrifuged (1000 x g, 10 min, to give  pellet (P1) and supernatant (S1) fractions). The supernatant was then  re-centrifuged (12,000 x g, 10 min, to give P2 and S2). Sucrose  media were prepared in 100 mm KCl, 5 mm  MgCl2, 100 mm imidazole, pH 6.8. Layers of 8.5% (1 ml),  40% (1.5 ml) and 60% (1.5 ml) sucrose were successively layered beneath 750  mul of the S2 supernatant fraction. The gradient was centrifuged (100,000  x g, 2 h, Beckman Coulter SW55T rotor), and fractions (0.25 ml,  1-19) were collected from the top of the gradient.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8149</offset><text>RNAi-mediated Knockdown of RyR1, RyR2, and  IP3R3:Cells (5 x 105 cells/well) grown  in 6-well plates for 2 days were transfected using Lipofectamine RNAimax with  a mixture of two RNAi for either RyR1, RyR2 (10 nm each,  Invitrogen), or IP3R3 (10 nm, Qiagen). After 36-48  h, cells were re-seeded (5 x 105 cells/well) and after a  further 48 h transfected again with the same RNAi mixture. Cells were used  48-60 h after the second transfection. The RNAi used are listed in  supplemental Table S1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8647</offset><text>Immunoblotting and Protein Assays:Cells (3 x 35-mm  dishes) were washed twice in PBS and lysed (PBS with 1% Triton X-100). Protein  concentrations were measured using the Quant-iT protein assay kit  (Invitrogen). After SDS-PAGE (3-8%, Invitrogen NuPAGE), proteins were  transferred to a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane using an iBLOT apparatus  (Invitrogen) and incubated with primary antibody. The antibodies used were:  monoclonal IP3R3 (Transduction Laboratories, 1:1000), RyR2  (Calbiochem, 1:1000), rabbit RyR1  (39) (1:1000), plasma membrane  Ca2+-ATPase (Alexis, 1:1000) and rabbit polyclonal calnexin (Santa  Cruz Biotechnology, 1:500). The blots were then incubated with horseradish  peroxidase-conjugated donkey anti-rabbit (AbCam, 1:5000) or goat anti-mouse  (Promega, 1:5000) secondary antiserum and visualized with SuperSignal West  Pico chemiluminescent substrate (Pierce). Bands were quantified using  GeneTools software (Syngene).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9597</offset><text>Quantitative PCR:Total RNA was isolated from cell lysates  and reverse transcribed into cDNA (20 mul) using a fast lane cDNA direct kit  (Qiagen). QPCR was performed on a Rotor-Gene 6000 (Corbett Research) in a  final volume of 15 mul using Sensimix Plus SYBR master mix (Quantace), 0.5  mum actin primer or Quantitect primers for  IP3R1-3 and RyR1-3, and 0.4 mul cDNA. Primers are  listed in supplemental Table S2. QPCR conditions were: initial denaturation at  95  C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles at 95  C for 10 s and 60   C for 30 s. After the last cycle, a melting curve was performed to  confirm the identity of the amplified product. Data were analyzed using  quantification software supplied with Rotorgene 6000  (40).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10328</offset><text>Single Channel Recording:Cells attached to uncoated plastic  Petri dishes were rinsed with, and then incubated in, bath solution (BS)  containing 140 mm cesium methanesulfonate, 10 mm Hepes,  500 mum BAPTA, 270 mum CaCl2 (free  [Ca2+] = 246 nm), pH 7.1. Where indicated, cesium  methanesulfonate was iso-osomotically replaced by KCl, NaCl, Tris-HCl or  N-methyl d-glucamine-HCl. Pipettes were pulled from  borosilicate glass and had resistances of 10-30 MOmega when filled  with pipette solution (PS). Most recordings were performed with symmetrical  solutions. Currents were recorded with an Axopatch 200B amplifier using pClamp  9.0, digitized at 10 kHz and filtered at 1 kHz. Capacitative currents were  cancelled before recording. Single channel currents were recorded in the  cell-attached or inside-out configuration of the patch-clamp technique. All  recordings were performed at room temperature. Currents were analyzed using  pClamp 9.0 software.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11284</offset><text>Measurements of [Ca2+]i and  Mn2+ Entry:Cells cultured on 22-mm  round glass coverslips were incubated with Fura 2AM (2 mum  prepared in anhydrous DMSO) in HBS supplemented with probenecid (2.5  mm) and Pluronic F127 (0.02%) for 45 min at 20  C, followed by  a further 45-min incubation to allow de-esterification of the indicator. HBS  had the following composition: 135 mm NaCl, 5.9 mm KCl,  1.2 mm MgCl2, 11.6 mm Hepes, 11.5  mm glucose, and 1.5 mm CaCl2 (replaced by 1  mm EGTA in Ca2+-free HBS), pH 7.3. Fluorescence ratios  (excitation at 340 and 380 nm; emission at 510 nm) from single cells were  collected at 20  C at 5-s intervals. After correction for autofluorescence  (by addition of 1 mum ionomycin with 10 mm  MnCl2), fluorescence ratios were calibrated to  [Ca2+]i using a look-up table created from standard  Ca2+ solutions (Molecular Probes).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>12145</offset><text>Ca2+ entry evoked by agonists of RyR. A,  Ca2+ signals evoked by 4CmC (1 mm) in HBS with or  without extracellular Ca2+ and after pretreatment with ryanodine  (400 mum, 30 min). Traces (here and in subsequent panels) show  the responses from ~50 individual cells taken from at least three  independent experiments (means +- S.E., but with many error bars smaller  than the symbols). B, responses to caffeine (1 mm) in  normal HBS. C, Ca2+ signals evoked by 4CmC (1  mm) in Ca2+-free medium alone or after pretreatment with  thapsigargin (TG, 1 mum). D, peak (after  ~30 s) and sustained (after 200 s) changes in  [Ca2+]i evoked by 4CmC in the absence (open  bars) and presence of extracellular Ca2+, and the latter after  pretreatment (2 min) with nifedipine (Nif, 10 mum) or  thapsigargin (1 mum). E, Mn2+ entry (0.5  mm) was measured by quenching of Fura 2 fluorescence in control  cells (Q1). Mn2+ was then removed and the cells incubated  with thapsigargin (1 mum) for 5 min (during the break between the  traces) before again measuring Mn2+ entry (Q2) in the  presence of thapsigargin alone (black) or with 4CmC (1 mm,  red). Typical traces are shown. Summary data show the slope of the  fluorescence change during the second addition of Mn2+ (Q2, with  the stimulus) as a % (Q2/Q1) of the slope recorded during the first addition  (Q1, without stimulus). Results are means +- S.E., n =  30-61. F, restoration of extracellular Ca2+ (1.5  mm) to cells pretreated with thapsigargin (1 mum) in  Ca2+-free HBS fails to evoke Ca2+ entry.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13683</offset><text>Quenching of fura 2 fluorescence by Mn2+ entry was measured in  similarly loaded cells bathed in Ca2+-free HBS supplemented with  0.5 mm MnCl2 and with fluorescence recorded after  excitation at 360 nm. For all experiments, a basal rate of quench (Q1) was  measured before stimulation, and the rate was again measured after stimulation  (Q2). The duration of the exposure to MnCl2 (100 s) was chosen to  ensure that rates of Fura 2 quenching were linear during both assay periods.  The effects of stimuli on rates of Mn2+ entry are reported as a  Q2/Q1 ratio, with the ratio uniquely determined for each single cell (see  Fig. 1E).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14315</offset><text>Materials:Fura 2AM and all culture media, except serum  (Sigma), were from Invitrogen. All other reagents, including ryanodine,  caffeine, 4CmC, and ruthenium red, were from Sigma.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>14496</offset><text>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14519</offset><text>Ca2+ Entry Evoked by Agonists of  RyR:In single cell measurements of  [Ca2+]i in RINmF5 insulinoma cells, most cells  responded to caffeine (1 mm) or 4-chloro-m-cresol (4CmC, 1  mm) with a substantial increase in  [Ca2+]i  (Fig. 1, A and  B). A lower concentration of 4CmC (0.5 mm),  sufficient to activate RyR1 and RyR2, but not RyR3  (41), evoked a similar  sustained Ca2+ signal  (Delta[Ca2+]i = 275 +- 18 and 176  +- 11 nm, for 1 mm and 0.5 mm 4CmC,  respectively). Treatment with a high, inactivating concentration of ryanodine  (400 mum) evoked no Ca2+ signal itself, but abolished  the subsequent response to 4CmC (Fig.  1A). Although each stimulus was effective in the absence  of extracellular Ca2+, both the peak amplitude and sustained  responses were substantially attenuated in Ca2+-free medium  (Fig. 1,  A-D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15344</offset><text>Pretreatment of cells in Ca2+-free medium with thapsigargin (1  mum, 2 min) to empty the intracellular Ca2+ stores  that express the SR/ER Ca2+-ATPase (SERCA) massively reduced the  4CmC-evoked increase in [Ca2+]i, but without  abolishing it (Fig.  1C). The small residual Ca2+ release is  probably mediated by RyR in either secretory vesicles  (8,  9) or endosomes  (10), both of which can  accumulate Ca2+ by mechanisms that do not require SERCA  (8,  9). Quenching of fura 2  fluorescence evoked by unidirectional Mn2+ entry across the PM was  also stimulated by 4CmC (Fig.  1E). These results establish that in RINm5F cells,  agonists of RyR stimulate both release of intracellular Ca2+ stores  (from both ER and secretory vesicles or endosomes) and Ca2+ entry.  Others have also reported that agonists of RyR evoke Ca2+ release  and Ca2+ entry in both beta-cells and insulinoma cells  (20,  42).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16245</offset><text>In most cells, emptying of intracellular Ca2+ stores evokes  store-operated Ca2+ entry (SOCE) across the PM, although SOCE is  perhaps less widely expressed in electrically excitable cells  (43). Thapsigargin (1  mum) did not cause a substantial increase in  [Ca2+]i, but it clearly emptied intracellular  stores because it almost abolished the Ca2+ release evoked by 4CmC  (Fig. 1C). However,  thapsigargin caused no detectable Ca2+ entry. The small responses  to thapsigargin were similar in the presence and absence of extracellular  Ca2+ (not shown), and restoration of extracellular Ca2+  to thapsigargin-treated cells failed to evoke a Ca2+ signal  (Fig. 1F). Under  similar conditions, the same stocks of thapsigargin stimulated both  Ca2+ release and SOCE in HEK cells (not shown). Furthermore,  prior-treatment of RINm5F cells with thapsigargin neither evoked  unidirectional Mn2+ entry nor affected the Mn2+ entry  evoked by 4CmC (Fig.  1E). We conclude that depletion of intracellular  Ca2+ stores fails to evoke significant SOCE in RINm5F cells. The  lack of detectable SOCE is consistent with reports from insulinoma  (44) and beta-cells  (20,  27,  45-47)  where SOCE was either very small or undetectable.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17466</offset><text>Although agonists of RyR evoke Ca2+ release  (Fig. 1, B and  C) and SOCE is apparently absent from RINm5F cells  (Fig. 1, E and  F), both the initial and sustained responses to caffeine  (not shown) or 4CmC (Fig.  1D) were substantially reduced in the absence of  extracellular Ca2+. Blocking voltage-gated L-type Ca2+  channels with nifedipine (10 mum) had no significant effect on  either the peak or sustained responses to 4CmC, and nor had thapsigargin any  effect on the sustained Ca2+ signals evoked by 4CmC  (Fig. 1D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17992</offset><text>Depolarization with 25 mm KCl (by replacement of NaCl) caused an  increase in [Ca2+]i (by 291 +- 12  nm, n = 48) that was substantially blocked (~60%) by  10 mum nifedipine (not shown). Under these depolarizing  conditions and with nifedipine (10 mum) present, 4CmC (1  mm) evoked a further increase in  [Ca2+]i of 169 +- 21 nm  (n = 46). The latter suggests that although 4CmC may lead to some  activation of L-type Ca2+ channels (note the small, but  statistically insignificant, inhibition of the peak 4CmC-evoked  Ca2+ signal by nifedepine in  Fig. 1D), these  channels can mediate no more than a very small component of the 4CmC-evoked  Ca2+ signal.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18647</offset><text>The results so far establish that agonists of RyR evoke Ca2+ (or  Mn2+) entry that is independent of SOCE or voltage-gated  Ca2+ channels. Another study also showed that a RyR-selective  agonist stimulates Ca2+ entry via a SOCE-independent pathway in  beta-cells, although it speculated that it resulted from RyR-mediated  release of Ca2+ from a non-ER store causing activation of  Ca2+-permeable TRP (transient receptor potential) channels in the  PM (20). Our subsequent  experiments show that the Ca2+ entry is mediated directly by RyR in  the PM.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19198</offset><text>Differential Distributions of RyR and IP3R:The  quantitative PCR (QPCR) analysis shown in supplemental Table S3 and the  immunoblots shown in Fig.  2A, establish that RyR2 and IP3R3 are the  major intracellular Ca2+ channels in RINm5F cells. These results  are consistent with previous reports demonstrating that IP3R3  (5,  14,  48) and RyR2  (7,  9,  14,  33,  49) are the major subtypes of  intracellular Ca2+ channels in pancreatic beta-cells  (5,  14,  33,  48,  49) and RINm5F cells  (5,  6,  14,  48). Our results are also  consistent with evidence showing low-level expression of RyR1  (9,  14,  33) and with the lack of  evidence that beta-cells or insulinoma cells express RyR3  (9).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>19892</offset><text>Expression of RyR2 in RINm5F cells. A, Western blots (60  mug protein/lane) from RINm5F cells stained with the indicated antibodies  (typical of at least 3 blots). B, homogenate of RINm5F cells (see  &quot;Experimental Procedures&quot;) was subjected to two centrifugation  steps (as shown) and from each supernatant (S) and pellet  (P), material equivalent to the same number of cells was analyzed by  Western blotting. The distribution of each protein within the supernatant  fraction is shown beneath each gel (mean +- S.E., n =  3). The low level of expression of RyR1 (supplemental Table S3) prevented  reliable quantification of its distribution after the first centrifugation  step. The S2 supernatant was further analyzed on a discontinuous sucrose  gradient, and fractions (0.25 ml, 1-19) were analyzed by Western  blotting. A typical blot is shown. C, The distribution of proteins  between fractions (means +- S.E., n = 3-6) is shown as a  percentage of that detected in fractions 6-15 (none of the proteins were  detected in the other fractions).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20940</offset><text>IP3R3 and RyR2 were similarly distributed between the  supernatant and pellet fractions after crude fractionation  (Fig. 2B). Although  these simple analyses failed to separate PM and ER membranes, the results are  consistent with the substantial presence of IP3R3 and RyR2 within  intracellular Ca2+ stores. However, sucrose-gradient centrifugation  of a fraction (S2 in Fig.  2B) that included 20% of all IP3R3 and RyR2,  clearly separated PM from ER, and IP3R3 from RyR2. IP3R3  appeared in the same fractions as calnexin, an integral ER protein, whereas  RyR2 was concentrated in the same fractions as the plasma membrane  Ca2+-ATPase (PMCA, Fig. 2,  B and C). These results do not prove that RyR2  are expressed in the PM, but they strongly suggest that at least some RyR2 are  expressed in a different membrane compartment to IP3R3.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>21779</offset><text>Caffeine and 4CmC activate the same large-conductance channels in the  plasma membrane of RINm5F cells and pancreatic beta-cells. A  and B, cell-attached (A) and excised patch (B)  recordings from RINm5F cells with cesium methanesulfonate in both BS and PS at  a holding potential of -100 mV. Caffeine (1 mm) or 4CmC (1  mm) were included in BS as indicated. In the bottom trace  of each panel, cells were preincubated with ryanodine (400 mum,  30 min) before stimulating with caffeine. Traces are representative of &gt;=  5(n = 2 for ryanodine) independent experiments (see &quot;Results  and Discussion&quot;). Arrows denote closed state. For each  recording, the boxed area is shown on an expanded timescale on the  right. C, current-voltage relationship for channels activated by  caffeine and 4CmC. Results are means +- S.E. n = 6-9  (most error bars are smaller than the symbols). D, typical excised  patch recording from a rat pancreatic beta-cell with cesium methanesulfonate  in both BS and PS, at a holding potential of -40 mV, and with 4CmC (1  mm) included in BS as indicated. The boxed area is shown  on an expanded timescale on the right. E, corresponding  current-voltage relationship for beta-cells (means +- S.E., n  = 5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23006</offset><text>Plasma Membrane Channels Activated by Agonists of RyR:In  cell-attached patch-clamp recordings from RINm5F cells with cesium  methansulphonate in both the bathing solution (BS) and pipette solution (PS),  concentrations of 4CmC (1 mm) or caffeine (1 mm) typical  of those used to activate RyR  (41) stimulated channel  activity (Fig. 3A).  Pre-incubation (30 min) with a high concentration (400 mum) of  ryanodine, sufficient to inhibit all RyR subtypes  (50), abolished responses to  both stimuli (Fig.  3A). Similar results were obtained with excised patches  (Fig. 3B). In both  sets of recordings, GOmega seals were obtained in about 50% of attempts. The  frequency with which channels were detected varied between 20 and 80% in  different cell preparations. It is difficult to estimate reliably the average  number of channels in a patch: too many large-conductance channels may prevent  formation of a GOmega seal, and patches with undetected channels will  include those that failed to respond for a variety of experimental reasons.  However, most active patches included one or two active channels, and very few  had 3-4 channels: the average number of channels per excised patch was  1.8 +- 0.2. An analysis that assumes a random distribution of channels  between patches likewise suggests the presence of ~2 channels/patch  (supplemental Table S4). Assuming that our patch-clamp recordings are from  ~20% of the total PM, these results suggest the presence of fewer than  ~10 of these channels in the PM of each RINm5F cell. It proved impossible  to achieve reliable whole cell recordings.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24606</offset><text>In symmetrical cesium methane sulfonate, the single channel slope  conductance (gamma) measured in cell-attached patches was the same whether  they were stimulated with caffeine (gamma = 147.7 +- 4.5 pS,  n = 6) or 4CmC (gamma = 148.3 +- 4.2 pS, n = 9)  (Fig. 3C). We conclude  that caffeine and 4CmC stimulate the same ryanodine-sensitive  large-conductance cation channels in the PM of RINm5F cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25008</offset><text>Under similar recording conditions (symmetrical cesium methanesulphonate),  4CmC (1 mm) also activated channels in the PM of freshly isolated  rat pancreatic beta-cells (Fig.  3D). The slope conductance of the major conductance of  these channels (gamma = 151.5 +- 6.3 pS, n = 5,  Fig. 3E) was similar  to that in RIN cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>25333</offset><text>Properties of ryanodine-activated channels in the plasma membrane.  A, ryanodine (4 nm) stimulates channel activity in excised  patches, which is unaffected by clotrimazole (50 mum). Results  show recordings in symmetrical cesium methane sulfonate at holding potentials  of +80 mV (upper trace of each pair) and -80 mV (lower),  each typical of &gt;=4 recordings. Arrows denote closed state.  B, current-voltage relationship for the major conductance of the  ryanodine-stimulated channels (means +- S.E., n &gt;= 5).  C, current amplitude histogram for ryanodine-evoked currents taken  from a trace similar to that shown in A at -80 mV. Arrow  denotes the current level equivalent to the major single channel conductance  (gamma = 148 pS). D, E, Po and mean open time  (tauo) for channels activated by ryanodine, 4CmC, and caffeine  (means +- S.E., n &gt;= 5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26185</offset><text>Properties of Ryanodine-activated Channels in the Plasma  Membrane:In excised inside-out patches, a low concentration of  ryanodine (4 nm) activated channels that were unaffected by  nifedipine (10 mum, not shown) or clotrimazole  (Fig. 4A); the latter  at a concentration (50 mum) sufficient to inhibit KATP  and Ca2+-activated K+ channels  (51,  52). The major conductance of  the ryanodine-activated channels (gammaCs = 147.8 +- 3.7  pS, n = 7) was the same as that of the channels activated by caffeine  and 4CmC (Fig. 4B).  The current-amplitude histograms consistently suggested the presence of minor  sub-conductance states with amplitudes of ~30-50% that of the main  conductance (Fig. 4C).  Such subconductance states are common features of RyR activated by ryanodine  (53). From patches with a  single channel, the maximal open probability (Po =  0.2-0.3) was similar for caffeine (1 mm), 4CmC (1  mm) and ryanodine (4 nm)  (Fig. 4D), although  the mean channel open time (tauo) was significantly longer for  ryanodine (Fig. 4E).  The latter is consistent with the established ability of low concentrations of  ryanodine to cause long-lasting openings of RyR  (50).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>27361</offset><text>Properties of 4CmC-activated channels in the plasma membrane.  A, cell-attached recordings were stimulated with 4CmC (1  mm) before excision into BS alone (lower) or supplemented  with ruthenium red (10 mum, upper). Recordings were in  symmetrical K+ at +100 mV. Arrows denote closed state.  B, typical recordings from excised patches held at -50 mV and  stimulated with 4CmC (1 mm) in symmetrical media containing the  indicated cations. C, current-voltage relationships from B  (means +- S.E., n &gt;= 6, most error bars are smaller than the  symbols).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27913</offset><text>Ruthenium red is an antagonist of RyR, but it is membrane-impermeant. By  first activating channels with 4CmC in the cell-attached configuration and  then excising the patch into BS containing ruthenium red (100  mum), we demonstrated that cytosolic ruthenium red rapidly  inhibits channel activity. Po in the cell-attached  configuration was 0.25 +- 0.02 (n = 20), and remained at 0.24  +- 0.04 after excision into normal BS, but fell within a few seconds to  0.005 +- 0.01 after excision into BS containing ruthenium red  (Fig. 5A). These  results provide substantial further evidence that the 4CmC-activated cation  channels in the PM have the properties expected of RyR.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>28588</offset><text>Activation of plasma membrane cation channels and cytosolic  Ca2+ signals requires RyR2. A, Western blots showing  expression of RyR2, IP3R3, and calnexin in RINm5F cells after  transfection with RNAi for RyR1, RyR2, or IP3R3, or after mock  transfection (control). The antibody to RyR1 cannot reliably detect changes in  expression of endogenous RyR1, which is expressed at ~10% that of RyR2  (supplemental Table S6). B, summary results show expression of RyR2  and IP3R3 derived from Western blots from four independent RNAi  transfections (means +- S.E.). C, typical recordings (at -50  mV) from patches excised from cells after transfection with RNAi for RyR2 or  mock transfection. Arrows denote the closed state. D,  percentage of cells in which 4CmC (1 mm) activated channels after  successful formation of a GOmega seal in cells treated with RNAi for RyR1  (n = 21), RyR2 (n = 32) or after mock transfection (control,  n = 38). E, Mn2+ entry evoked by 1 mm  4CmC (with Q2/Q1 measured as in Fig.  1E) for cells treated with RNAi for RyR2 or  IP3R3, or after mock transfection (control). Results are means  +- S.E. for 35-40 cells from two independent transfections.  F, Ca2+ signals evoked by 4CmC (1 mm) in cells  transfected with RNAi for RyR2 or after mock transfection (control). Results  are means +- S.E., n = 47 and 32 cells, respectively.  G, peak Ca2+ signals evoked by 4CmC (1 mm) in  cells treated with RNAi for RyR1, RyR2, or IP3R3, or after mock  transfection (control). Means +- S.E., n = 30-76  cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30112</offset><text>In excised patches stimulated with 4CmC (1 mm) under symmetrical  ionic conditions, the channels were permeable not only to Cs+  (gammaCs = 148.3 +- 4.2 pS, n = 9), but also to  K+ (gammaK = 169.0 +- 4.8 pS, n = 5)  and Na+ (gammaNa = 130.2 +- 2.1 pS, n =  4) (Fig. 5, B and  C). A similar number of channels and with similar  Po was detected under each of these conditions (not  shown). The channels were impermeable to  N-methyl-d-glucamine (NMDG) chloride  (Fig. 5B). Our  attempts to measure Ba2+ and Ca2+ conductances were  frustrated by resealing of membrane around the patch-pipette. We were,  therefore, unable to determine the relative permeability of the PM channels  for monovalent and bivalent cations. Comparison of gamma for the PM channels  with analyses of RyR2 reconstituted into lipid bilayers  (54,  55) shows that after  correction for the different ionic conditions, gamma of the PM channels is  consistently 3-4-fold lower than for RyR2 in bilayers (supplemental  Table S5). Our previous analysis of IP3R expressed in the PM or  nuclear envelope also suggested that exactly the same channel can have very  different gamma when expressed in different membranes  (56). We have no definitive  explanation for these disparities, but for IP3R we suggested that  different membranes may selectively stabilize different sub-conductance states  (56). A similar explanation  may account for the different gamma of RyR2 in the PM and bilayers.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31568</offset><text>We have shown that RyR2 are expressed in RINm5F cells  (Fig. 2A) and that  their distribution is consistent with a presence in the PM  (Fig. 2, B and  C). A variety of agonists of RyR (caffeine, 4CmC,  ryanodine) activate both Ca2+ entry in intact cells and poorly  selective large-conductance cation channels in the PM. The responses are  blocked by antagonists of RyR (ryanodine, ruthenium red), but not by  antagonists of other cation channels. Our final experiments use RNAi to  confirm that RyR2 directly mediate these responses.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32103</offset><text>Inhibition of RyR2 Expression Inhibits Responses:Using RNAi,  we selectively reduced expression of RyR1, RyR2 or IP3R3 by  &gt;50%, without reducing expression of the non-targeted proteins  (Fig. 6, A and  B, and supplemental Table S6).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32337</offset><text>In excised patch-clamp recordings from mock-transfected cells or cells  transfected with RNAi to RyR1, 4CmC-activated cation channels were detected in  ~70% of recordings that achieved a GOmega seal, but the success rate  fell to 21 +- 6% for cells treated with RNAi to RyR2  (Fig. 6, C and  D). The peak Ca2+ signals evoked by 4CmC,  which depend largely on Ca2+ entry  (Fig. 1D), were also  selectively attenuated by treatment with RNAi to RyR2  (Fig. 6, F and  G). Likewise, the effect of 4CmC on Mn2+ entry  was almost abolished in cells treated with RNAi to RyR2, whereas RNAi to  IP3R3 had no effect (Fig.  6E). We conclude that RyR2 are expressed in the PM and  directly mediate Ca2+ entry.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33035</offset><text>Expression of Functional RyR2 in the Plasma Membrane of RINm5F  Cells:We have demonstrated the expression of small numbers (~10  channels/cell) of functional RyR2 in the PM of RINm5F cells and provided more  limited evidence for functional RyR in the PM of rat pancreatic beta-cells.  Although RyR and IP3R are widely expressed intracellular  Ca2+ channels, accumulating evidence suggests that the same  channels may also be expressed within the PM of some cells. In B-lymphocytes,  for example, very small numbers of functional IP3R (2-3  IP3R/cell) are reliably expressed in the PM, where they mediate  about half the Ca2+ entry evoked by activation of the B-cell  receptor (56,  57). IP3R, possibly  distinct from those in the ER, are also expressed in the PM of olfactory  neurones (58) and ciliated  epithelia (59).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33856</offset><text>Several studies have detected cation channels with large, although rather  variable, conductances that are activated by agonists of RyR in the PM of  different cell types. These include osteoblasts, where RyR2 are proposed to  mediate extracellular Ca2+-sensing  (60); cardiac myocytes  (61) and smooth muscle  (62,  63). In each case, the density  of the PM channels was very low, typically no more than ~10 channels/cell,  and often just 2-3 channels/cell. None of these reports established the  molecular identity of the channel and several were reluctant to conclude that  it was a RyR (20,  61-63),  but together they provide evidence that small numbers of RyR may be expressed  in the PM of several different electrically excitable cells. Our results  extend these observations to RINm5F cells and pancreatic beta-cells and,  more importantly, they unequivocally establish that RyR2 expressed in the PM  can directly mediate Ca2+ entry.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34799</offset><text>These results indicate that in some cells, small numbers of IP3R  or RyR can be expressed in the PM and mediate Ca2+ entry. The small  number of these channels is significant because both RyR and IP3R  have such large conductances (Figs.  3C,  4B, and  5C) that very few  channels can mediate substantial Ca2+ entry  (56).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35122</offset><text>RyR are implicated in the responses of pancreatic beta-cells to glucose  and incretins (see Introduction); many diabetic states are associated with a  loss of RyR from beta-cells  (10); and the  immunosuppressant, FK-506, which interacts with RyR via FKBP  (64), is a major cause of  post-transplantation diabetes mellitus  (65). But the specific roles  of RyR in beta-cells are incompletely resolved  (7,  10,  66). It is, however, clear  that whereas both IP3R and RyR are expressed in the ER of  insulinoma cells, only RyR are expressed in secretory vesicles  (8) or endosomes  (10). Selective targeting of  RyR (and not IP3R) to the secretory vesicles of beta-cells might  therefore be one step that contributes to selective expression of small  numbers of RyR in the PM.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35898</offset><text>Abundant evidence implicates RyR in mediating physiological responses of  beta-cells to glucose and incretins (see Introduction). Our results suggest  that their involvement in these responses is likely to involve RyR within both  intracellular stores and the PM, and within the latter it is likely that RyR  may directly mediate Ca2+ entry and contribute to regulation of  membrane potential. It remains unclear whether the non-ER RyR reside  predominantly in endosomes or secretory vesicles  (8,  10), but it is significant  that their presence in either organelle suggests a dynamic relationship  between exocytosis of insulin-containing vesicles and trafficking of RyR2  between intracellular organelles and the PM.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36618</offset><text>We have shown that small numbers of functional RyR2 are expressed in the PM  of RINm5F insulinoma cells and rat pancreatic beta-cells, where they  directly mediate Ca2+ entry and may also regulate membrane  potential. We suggest that exocytosis of insulin-containing vesicles and the  subsequent retrieval of membrane by endocytosis  (67) may allow dynamic  regulation of RyR expression in the PM.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>37016</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37039</offset><text>   </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37043</offset><text>  </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Foskett, J. K., White, C., Cheung, K. H., and Mak, D. O.  ()    -658</infon><infon key="fpage">593</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17429043</infon><infon key="source">Physiol. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">87</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37046</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hamilton, S. L. ()    -260</infon><infon key="fpage">253</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16115682</infon><infon key="source">Cell  Calcium</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">38</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>37047</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Taylor, C. W., Genazzani, A. A., and Morris, S. A.  ()    -251</infon><infon key="fpage">237</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10668562</infon><infon key="source">Cell Calcium</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>37048</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sutko, J. L., and Airey, J. A. ()     -1071</infon><infon key="fpage">1027</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8874493</infon><infon key="source">Physiol. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">76</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>37049</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Blondel, O., Takeda, J., Janssen, H., Seino, S., and Bell, G. I.  ()     -11363</infon><infon key="fpage">11356</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8388391</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">268</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>37050</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Swatton, J. E., Morris, S. A., Cardy, T. J. A., and Taylor, C. W.  ()    -60</infon><infon key="fpage">55</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10548533</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">344</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>37051</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Islam, M. S. ()     -1309</infon><infon key="fpage">1299</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11978625</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">51</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37052</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mitchell, K. J., Pinton, P., Varadi, A., Tacchetti, C., Ainscow, E.  K., Pozzan, T., Rizzuto, R., and Rutter, G. A. ()     -51</infon><infon key="fpage">41</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11571310</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">155</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>37053</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mitchell, K. J., Lai, F. A., and Rutter, G. A. ()     -11064</infon><infon key="fpage">11057</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12538591</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>37054</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Johnson, J. D., Kuang, S., Misler, S., and Polonsky, K. S.  ()    -880</infon><infon key="fpage">878</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15033925</infon><infon key="source">FASEB J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37055</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Blondel, O., Bell, G. I., Moody, M., Miller, R. J., and Gibbons, S.  J. ()     -27170</infon><infon key="fpage">27167</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7961623</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">269</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>37056</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ravazzola, M., Halban, P. A., and Orci, L. ()      -2748</infon><infon key="fpage">2745</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8610112</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">93</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>37057</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Prentki, M., Biden, T. J., Janjic, D., Irvine, R. F., Berridge, M.  J., and Wollheim, C. B. ()     -564</infon><infon key="fpage">562</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6328320</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">309</infon><infon key="year">1984</infon><offset>37058</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Takasawa, S., Akiyama, T., Nata, K., Kuroki, M., Tohgo, A.,  Noguchi, N., Kobayashi, S., Kato, I., Katada, T., and Okamoto, H.  ()     -2500</infon><infon key="fpage">2497</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9446548</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">273</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>37059</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Patterson, R. L., Boehning, D., and Snyder, S. H.  ()    -465</infon><infon key="fpage">437</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15189149</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Biochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">73</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37060</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bers, D. M. ()    -429</infon><infon key="fpage">417</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15276012</infon><infon key="source">J. Mol. Cell.  Cardiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">37</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37061</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Williams, A. J. ()    -8</infon><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="source">Front.  Biosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37062</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gillespie, D., and Fill, M. ()    -3714</infon><infon key="fpage">3706</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18621826</infon><infon key="source">Biophys.  J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">95</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37063</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nichols, C. G. ()     -476</infon><infon key="fpage">470</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16554807</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">440</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37064</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gustafsson, A. J., Ingelman-Sundberg, H., Dzabic, M., Awasum, J.,  Nguyen, K. H., Ostenson, C. G., Pierro, C., Tedeschi, P., Woolcott, O.,  Chiounan, S., Lund, P. E., Larsson, O., and Islam, M. S. ()     -303</infon><infon key="fpage">301</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15572434</infon><infon key="source">FASEB J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>37065</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ashcroft, F. M., Proks, P., Smith, P. A., Ammala, C., Bokvist, K.,  and Rorsman, P. ()    (suppl.),  -65</infon><infon key="fpage">54</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7929618</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell. Biochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">55</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>37066</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bokvist, K., Eliasson, L., Ammala, C., Renstrom, E., and Rorsman,  P. ()    -57</infon><infon key="fpage">50</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7828595</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>37067</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wiederkehr, A., and Wollheim, C. B. ()     -2649</infon><infon key="fpage">2643</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16556766</infon><infon key="source">Endocrinology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">147</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37068</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rojas, E., Carroll, P. B., Ricordi, C., Boschero, A. C.,  Stojilkovic, S. S., and Atwater, I. ()     -1781</infon><infon key="fpage">1771</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8137742</infon><infon key="source">Endocrinology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">134</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>37069</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Henquin, J. C. ()     -1760</infon><infon key="fpage">1751</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11078440</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">49</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>37070</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shigeto, M., Katsura, M., Matsuda, M., Ohkuma, S., and Kaku, K.  ()    -7</infon><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17409272</infon><infon key="source">J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">322</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37071</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dyachok, O., and Gylfe, E. ()    -45461</infon><infon key="fpage">45455</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15316011</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37072</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kermode, H., Williams, A. J., and Sitsapesan, R.  ()     -1304</infon><infon key="fpage">1296</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9512027</infon><infon key="source">Biophys. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">74</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>37073</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Drucker, D. J. ()    -165</infon><infon key="fpage">153</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16517403</infon><infon key="source">Cell  Metab.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37074</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Holst, J. J. ()    -1439</infon><infon key="fpage">1409</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17928588</infon><infon key="source">Physiol.  Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">87</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37075</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Holz, G. G. ()    -13</infon><infon key="fpage">5</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14693691</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">53</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37076</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Szaszak, M., Christian, F., Rosenthal, W., and Klussmann, E.  ()    -601</infon><infon key="fpage">590</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18061403</infon><infon key="source">Cell. Signal.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37077</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Holz, G. G., Leech, C. A., Heller, R. S., Castonguay, M., and  Habener, J. F. ()     -14156</infon><infon key="fpage">14147</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10318832</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>37078</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tsuboi, T., da Silva Xavier, G., Holz, G. G., Jouaville, L. S.,  Thomas, A. P., and Rutter, G. A. ()    -299</infon><infon key="fpage">287</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12410638</infon><infon key="source">Biochem.  J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">369</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>37079</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kang, G., Chepurny, O. G., and Holz, G. G. ()     -385</infon><infon key="fpage">375</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11600673</infon><infon key="source">J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">536</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>37080</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gromada, J., Dissing, S., Bokvist, K., Renstrom, E.,  Frokjaer-Jensen, J., Wulff, B. S., and Rorsman, P. ()     -774</infon><infon key="fpage">767</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7789644</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">44</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>37081</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dyachok, O., Isakov, Y., Sagetorp, J., and Tengholm, A.  ()     -352</infon><infon key="fpage">349</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16421574</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">439</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37082</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lacy, P. E., and Kostianovsky, M. ()     -39</infon><infon key="fpage">35</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">5333500</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1967</infon><offset>37083</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Meissner, G., Rousseau, E., and Lai, F. A. ()     -1722</infon><infon key="fpage">1715</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2536370</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">264</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>37084</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Warton, K., Foster, N. C., Gold, W. A., and Stanley, K. K.  ()    -95</infon><infon key="fpage">85</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15527968</infon><infon key="source">Gene</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">342</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37085</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fessenden, J. D., Perez, C. F., Goth, S., Pessah, I. N., and Allen,  P. D. ()     -28735</infon><infon key="fpage">28727</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12761215</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>37086</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Woolcott, O. O., Gustafsson, A. J., Dzabic, M., Pierro, C.,  Tedeschi, P., Sandgren, J., Bari, M. R., Nguyen, K. H., Bianchi, M., Rakonjac,  M., Radmark, O., Ostenson, C. G., and Islam, M. S. ()     -537</infon><infon key="fpage">529</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16620964</infon><infon key="source">Cell Calcium</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">39</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37087</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Parekh, A. B., and Putney, J. W. ()     -810</infon><infon key="fpage">757</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15788710</infon><infon key="source">Physiol. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">85</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>37088</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yamasaki, M., Masgrau, R., Morgan, A. J., Churchill, G. C., Patel,  S., Ashcroft, S. J., and Galione, A. ()    -7240</infon><infon key="fpage">7234</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14660554</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37089</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, Y. J., and Gylfe, E. ()    -286</infon><infon key="fpage">277</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9481478</infon><infon key="source">Cell  Calcium</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>37090</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Miura, Y., Henquin, J. C., and Gilon, P. ()     -398</infon><infon key="fpage">387</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9306280</infon><infon key="source">J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">503</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>37091</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mears, D., Leighton, X., Atwater, I., and Rojas, E.  ()    -68</infon><infon key="fpage">59</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10191960</infon><infon key="source">Cell Calcium</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">25</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>37092</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lee, B., Bradford, P. G., and Laychock, S. G. ()     -39</infon><infon key="fpage">31</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9723861</infon><infon key="source">J. Mol. Endocrinol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>37093</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Johnson, J. D., Han, Z., Otani, K., Ye, H., Zhang, Y., Wu, H.,  Horikawa, Y., Misler, S., Bell, G. I., and Polonsky, K. S. ()     -24802</infon><infon key="fpage">24794</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15044459</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37094</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Santonastasi, M., and Wehrens, X. H. ()     -944</infon><infon key="fpage">937</infon><infon key="source">Acta Pharma. Sin.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">28</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37095</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tian, M., Dong, M. Q., Chiu, S. W., Lau, C. P., and Li, G. R.  ()     -297</infon><infon key="fpage">289</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16341233</infon><infon key="source">Br. J. Pharmacol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">147</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37096</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Welker, S., and Drews, G. ()      -550</infon><infon key="fpage">543</infon><infon key="source">Naunyn-Shmiedeberg's Arch. Pharmacol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">356</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>37097</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fill, M., and Copello, J. A. ()     -922</infon><infon key="fpage">893</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12270947</infon><infon key="source">Physiol. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">82</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37098</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lindsay, A. R. G., Manning, S. D., and Williams, A. J.  ()     -480</infon><infon key="fpage">463</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1716676</infon><infon key="source">J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">439</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>37099</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Williams, A. J., West, D. J., and Sitsapesan, R.  ()    -104</infon><infon key="fpage">61</infon><infon key="source">Quart. Rev. Biophys.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">34</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>37100</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dellis, O., Dedos, S., Tovey, S. C., Rahman, T.-U., Dubel, S. J.,  and Taylor, C. W. ()     -233</infon><infon key="fpage">229</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16840702</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">313</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37101</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dellis, O., Rossi, A. M., Dedos, S. G., and Taylor, C. W.  ()     -755</infon><infon key="fpage">751</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17999955</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37102</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fadool, D. A., and Ache, B. W. ()     -918</infon><infon key="fpage">907</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1384577</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>37103</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Barrera, N. P., Morales, B., and Villalon, M. ()      -821</infon><infon key="fpage">815</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18163243</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">364</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37104</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Huang, C. L., Sun, L., Fraser, J. A., Grace, A. A., and Zaidi, M.  ()     -270</infon><infon key="fpage">255</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18083933</infon><infon key="source">Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1116</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37105</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhang, Y. A., Tuft, R. A., Lifshitz, L. M., Fogarty, K. E., Singer,  J. J., and Zou, H. ()     -H2461</infon><infon key="fpage">H2448</infon><infon key="source">Am. J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">293</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37106</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Guerrero, A., Fay, F. S., and Singer, J. J. ()     -394</infon><infon key="fpage">375</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7807054</infon><infon key="source">J. Gen. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">104</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>37107</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Loirand, G., Pacaud, P., Baron, A., Mironneau, C., and Mironneau,  J. ()     -475</infon><infon key="fpage">461</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1716314</infon><infon key="source">J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">437</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>37108</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Samso, M., Shen, X., and Allen, P. D. ()     -927</infon><infon key="fpage">917</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16405911</infon><infon key="source">J. Mol. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">356</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37109</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Penfornis, A., and Kury-Paulin, S. ()     -546</infon><infon key="fpage">539</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17130815</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes Metab.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">32</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37110</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhan, X., Yang, L., Yi, M., and Jia, Y. ()     -782</infon><infon key="fpage">773</infon><infon key="source">Eur. J. Biophys.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">37</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37111</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">MacDonald, P. E., and Rorsman, P. ()     -121</infon><infon key="fpage">113</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17420302</infon><infon key="source">Physiology (Bethesda)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37112</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>37113</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: RyR, ryanodine receptor; BS, bath solution;  [Ca2+]i, free intracellular Ca2+  concentration; 4CmC, 4-chloro-m-cresol; ER, endoplasmic reticulum;  gamma, single channel slope conductance; HBS, Hepes-buffered saline;  IP3R, inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor; PBS,  phosphate-buffered saline; PM, plasma membrane; Po, single  channel open probability; PS, pipette solution.</text></passage></document></collection>
