<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19171933</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M808463200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2659243</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19171933</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">8855</infon><infon key="fpage">8855</infon><infon key="issue">13</infon><infon key="lpage">8865</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ahn;given-names:Seungkirl</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kim;given-names:Jihee</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hara;given-names:Makoto R.</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ren;given-names:Xiu-Rong</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lefkowitz;given-names:Robert J.</infon><infon key="p">Author's Choice:Final version full  access.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-2 Mediates Anti-apoptotic Signaling through Regulation of  BAD  Phosphorylation*S</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>96</offset><text>beta-Arrestins, originally discovered as terminators of G protein-coupled  receptor signaling, have more recently been appreciated to also function as  signal transducers in their own right, although the consequences for cellular  physiology have not been well understood. Here we demonstrate that  beta-arrestin-2 mediates anti-apoptotic cytoprotective signaling stimulated  by a typical 7-transmembrane receptor the angiotensin ATII 1A receptor,  expressed endogenously in rat vascular smooth muscle cells or by transfection  in HEK-293 cells. Receptor stimulation leads to concerted activation of two  pathways, ERK/p90RSK and PI3K/AKT, which converge to phosphorylate and  inactivate the pro-apoptotic protein BAD. Anti-apoptotic effects as well as  pathway activities can be stimulated by an angiotensin analog (SII), which has  been previously shown to activate beta-arrestin but not G protein-dependent  signaling, and are abrogated by beta-arrestin-2 small interfering RNA. These  findings establish a key role for beta-arrestin-2 in mediating cellular  cytoprotective functions by a 7-transmembrane receptor and define the  biochemical pathways involved.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1260</offset><text>beta-Arrestins 1 and 2 were originally identified as signal terminators  for G protein-dependent 7-transmembrane receptor  (7TMR)2 signaling.  Their binding to the receptor sterically inhibits receptor coupling to G  protein leading to inactivation of effectors such as second messenger  generating enzymes (1). Besides  this classical function, recently accumulating evidence has revealed novel  functions of beta-arrestins as signal transducers in various signaling  pathways (2). Among other  processes, beta-arrestins have been suggested to play a role in regulation  of cell death, but this area has been controversial and largely devoid of  mechanistic insight. There have been reports implicating beta-arrestins in  both pro- and anti-apoptotic responses as well as in non-apoptotic cell death  (3-10).  For example, it has been shown that stimulation of a number of 7TMRs including  the N-formyl peptide receptor induces apoptosis in beta-arrestin  1/2 double knock-out mouse embryonic fibroblasts, and that reintroduction of  either beta-arrestin-1 or -2 completely prevents this apoptosis  (5). Conversely,  beta-arrestins also have been reported to mediate cell death.  beta-Arrestin-2, particularly a dephosphorylated form, has been shown to  facilitate inhibition of NF-kappaB activation in response to UV, leading to  promotion of UV-induced cell death  (8).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2633</offset><text>Bcl-2 family proteins are known to determine the outcome of an intrinsic  apoptotic process initiated by release of cytochrome c and apoptotic  factors from the mitochondria  (11). BAD, a BH3-only protein  is one of the &quot;death-promoting&quot; members of the Bcl-2 family and  its pro-apoptotic activity is regulated primarily by phosphorylation at  several sites (12,  13). Survival factors induce  BAD phosphorylation via several protein kinase signaling pathways  (13) including activation of  mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)-ribosomal S6 kinase (RSK)  (14-16)  and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K)-AKT  (17,  18). Phosphorylated BAD  associates with 14-3-3 proteins in the cytoplasm, preventing translocation of  BAD to the mitochondria (19)  and its interaction with the anti-apoptotic proteins Bcl-xL and Bcl-2  (13,  20). These proteins, freed  from BAD, in turn associate with two other pro-apoptotic proteins, BAX and  BAK. Such association prevents aggregation of these pro-apoptotic proteins on  the mitochondrial membrane, stopping cytochrome c release and  consequently inhibiting apoptosis  (11,  20).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3755</offset><text>Recently several 7TMRs have been shown to activate the extracellular  signal-regulated kinase (ERK) MAPK cascade and PI3K-AKT pathways in a  beta-arrestin-dependent manner  (2). In particular, it has been  demonstrated that beta-arrestin-mediated ERK activation by angiotensin II  type 1A (AT1A) (21,  22), vasopressin V2  (23), parathyroid hormone  (24), and  beta2-adrenergic receptors  (25) is G protein-independent.  Furthermore, we have previously found that beta-arrestin-mediated ERK  activation is quite distinct in its temporal  (22-25)  and spatial (22,  26) patterns from  ERK-activated via G protein-dependent stimulation. In the case of  AT1AR-mediated ERK activation in receptor-transfected human  embryonic kidney (HEK)-293 cells, for example, the G protein-dependent  activation is rapid, quite transient (peak at 2-5 min), and leads to nuclear  translocation of the activated ERK. In contrast, beta-arrestin-2-dependent  ERK activation is slower, quite persistent, and entirely confined to the  cytoplasm, particularly to endosomal vesicles  (22). Such differences in ERK  activation strongly imply that there must be subsets of ERK targets and  physiological outcomes differentially regulated through beta-arrestin  versus G protein-dependent mechanisms. In the case of AKT activation,  stimulation of 7TM protease-activated receptors with thrombin has been shown  to activate AKT in a beta-arrestin-1-dependent manner  (27). Stimulation of the  AT1 receptor also has been shown to activate AKT in several cell  types including vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs)  (28,  29) although it has not been  determined whether beta-arrestins are involved in this signaling.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5441</offset><text>Accordingly, the studies reported here were undertaken to examine the role  of beta-arrestin in 7TMR-regulated apoptosis and to determine the downstream  pathways mediating this regulation in a physiologically relevant  non-transfected cellular receptor system. For this purpose, we chose the  AT1 receptor in rat VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>5762</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5786</offset><text>Materials:[Sar1,Ile4,Ile8]AngII  (Sar-Arg-Val-Ile-Ile-His-Pro-Ile) (SII) was synthesized as described  (21,  30). GF109203X (GFX),  Ro-31-8425, U0126, and Z-VAD-fmk were purchased from Calbiochem. SL0101 was  from Toronto Research Chemicals (North York, Ontario, Canada). All other  reagents were purchased from Sigma, unless otherwise described. Plasmids  expressing hemagglutinin-tagged wild-type, S112A and S136A mutant BAD were a  generous gift from Dr. Michael E. Greenberg (Harvard Medical School).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6291</offset><text>Antibodies:Rabbit polyclonal phospho-AKT (Ser473)  (used in an 1:1,000 dilution for immunoblotting), AKT (1:2,000), phospho-BAD  (Ser112) (1:500-1,000), BAD (1:1,000 for human BAD), Bcl-xL  (1:1,000), caspase-3 (1:1,000), cleaved caspase-3 (Asp175)  (1:1,000), phospho-ERK1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204) (1:2,000), and  phospho-p90RSK (Thr359/Ser363) (1:500-1,000) antibodies  were purchased from Cell Signaling (Danvers, MA). Polyclonal 14-3-3beta  (C-20) (1:1,000), RSK-1 (C-21) (1:1,000), and mouse monoclonal BAD (C-7)  (1:1,000 for human BAD) antibodies were from Santa Cruz (Santa Cruz, CA).  Monoclonal BAD (1:2,000 for rat BAD) and polyclonal ERK1/2 (1:10,000)  antibodies were from BD Transduction Laboratories (Franklin Lakes, NJ) and  Millipore (Billerica, MA), respectively. Human and rat beta-arrestins were  detected by A1CT and A2CT antibodies, respectively  (31).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7159</offset><text>Synthesis of Small Interfering RNAs (siRNAs):Chemically  synthesized, double-stranded siRNAs, with 19-nucleotide duplex RNA and  2-nucleotide 3'-dTdT overhangs were purchased from Dharmacon (Lafayette,  CO) in deprotected and desalted forms. The two different siRNA sequences  targeting human (rat) beta-arrestin-2 were  5'-GGACCGC(G)AAAGUGUUUGUG-3' and  5'-CCAACCUCAUUGAAUUU(C)GA-3', corresponding to positions 150-168  and 1112(1115)-1131(1133), relative to the start codon, respectively  (32). A non-silencing RNA  duplex (5'-UUCUCCGAACGUGUCACGU-3'), as the manufacturer (Xeragon,  Germantown, MD) indicated, was used as a control.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7794</offset><text>Cell Culture and Transfection:VSMCs were isolated from aorta  of male Sprague-Dawley rats and maintained as described  (32). Eight to 90% confluent  early passage (&lt;5) VSMCs were transfected with siRNA using the  Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent (Invitrogen) according to the modified  manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, 60 mul of the Lipofectamine 2000  transfection reagent was added to 300 mul of the medium-199 and 20 mug of  siRNA was added to 400 mul of the medium. Both solutions were allowed to  stand 5-10 min at room temperature and mixed by inversion. Following a  15-20-min incubation at room temperature, the entire transfection mixture was  added to VSMCs in a 100-mm dish containing 5 ml of the fresh, serum-free  medium. After cells were incubated for overnight at 37  C, an additional 5  ml of the medium with 20% fetal bovine serum and 2% penicillin/streptomycin  were added to the dish. Following an additional incubation for 24 h, cells  were divided into 6-well plates or 35-mm glass bottom dishes (MatTek, Ashland,  MA) for further procedures. For DNA transfection into VSMCs in either 35-mm  glass bottom dishes or 6-well plates, the Lipofectamine LTX transfection  reagent (Invitrogen) was used with the PLUS reagent (Invitrogen) according to  the manufacturer's instructions. HEK-293 cells, stably expressing  AT1A receptors (~600 fmol/mg of proteins), were established  after transfection with a zeocin-resistant AT1A receptor expression  plasmid using FuGENE 6 (Roche) according to the manufacturer's instructions.  Stable clones were selected in the presence of zeocin (300 mug/ml)  (Invitrogen). Cells were maintained and transfected with siRNAs using  GeneSilencer (Genlantis, San Diego, CA) as described  (22).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9546</offset><text>Cleaved Caspase-3 and DNA Fragmentation Assays:VSMCs were  serum-starved for ~24 h and then stimulated with 100 nm AngII  or 10 mum SII at 37  C for 5 min prior to treatment with  either 80 mum H2O2 or 50 mum  etoposide. After a further incubation overnight, cell lysates were prepared.  Pro- and cleaved caspase-3 were visualized, and the amounts of cleaved  caspase-3 were quantified as described for immunoblotting in this section. The  amounts of fragmented DNA were measured by the enzyme-linked immunosorbent  assay using the Cell Death Detection ELISAPLUS kit (Roche)  according to the manufacturer's instructions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10168</offset><text>Immunostaining:VSMCs on 35-mm glass bottom dishes were fixed  with 5% formaldehyde diluted in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). Fixed cells  were permeabilized by incubation with 0.2% Triton X-100 in PBS for 20 min.  After blocking with 2% bovine serum albumin in PBS for 1 h, cells were  incubated with the mouse monoclonal anti-cytochrome c (BD Pharmingen,  1:100) antibody at room temperature for 2 h, and repeatedly washed with PBS.  Next, incubation of the Bodipy fluorescein-conjugated secondary antibody  (Molecular Probes, 1:100) was done for 1 h at room temperature followed by  repeated washes with PBS. For subsequent staining of the hemaglutinin  epitope-tagged BAD, cells were incubated with a polyclonal hemaglutinin probe  (Y11) antibody (Santa Cruz, 1:200) at room temperature overnight. The Texas  Red-conjugated secondary antibody (Molecular Probes, 1:250) was then added for  1 h. Confocal images were obtained on a Zeiss LSM510 laser scanning microscope  using single line (488 nm) or multitrack sequential excitation (488 and 568  nm) and emission (515-540 nm, Bodipy fluorescein; 585-615 nm, Texas Red)  filter sets.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11306</offset><text>Immunoblotting and Immunoprecipitation:In most cases,  cellular extracts from VSMCs or HEK-293 cells on 6-well plates were prepared  as described previously (22).  For caspase-3 immunoblotting, VSMC lysates were prepared using the RIPA lysis  buffer. Equal amounts (~10 mug) of cellular extracts/lysates were used  for immunoblotting performed as described previously  (22). For immunoprecipitation,  lysates form HEK-293 cells in 100-mm dishes were prepared using the  glycerol/Nonidet P-40 lysis buffer  (33). Equal amounts of cell  lysates (300-500 mug of total protein in 1 ml of the buffer) were incubated  with 1-2 mug of either rabbit polyclonal 14-3-3 beta (C-20) or mouse  monoclonal BAD (C-7) antibody and protein A- or G-agarose beads, respectively,  overnight at 4  C. Co-immunoprecipitated proteins were detected by  immunoblotting. Each band in immunoblots was quantified by densitometry using  the GeneTools program (SynGene).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12248</offset><text>Statistical Analysis:Statistical significance in bar graphs  was determined by using a one-way analysis of variance (PRISM software) to  correct for multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's multiple comparison test) or  t test for single comparisons between AngII or SII-stimulated  versus non-stimulated in a certain condition, unless otherwise  indicated in each figure. Statistical significance in each time point of  kinetic graphs was determined by using a two-way analysis of variance  (Bonferroni's post-test) between beta-arrestin-2 siRNA-transfected and  control cells. p value (*, p &lt; 0.05;  **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001) of  &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>12926</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12934</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-2 Is Essential for the Anti-apoptotic Effects of AngII  on Primary Cultured Vascular Smooth Muscle Cells:It has been  previously reported that the octapeptide hormone angiotensin II (AngII)  promotes anti-apoptotic effects in VSMCs through AngII type 1 receptors  (AT1Rs) (34,  35). We and others have  previously found that beta-arrestin-2 is the isoform that mediates  AT1AR-activated ERK signaling  (33,  36), which is potentially an  anti-apoptotic pathway. We have also found that beta-arrestin-1 functionally  opposes this signaling (33).  Consequently, we used VSMCs to explore the role of beta-arrestin-2 in  regulating apoptosis. We first monitored the effects of AngII stimulation on  the activation of caspase-3 (cleavage of procaspase-3) induced by apoptotic  challenges in VSMCs transfected with either control or beta-arrestin-2  siRNAs. We used 100 nm AngII to obtain maximal responses in this  assay. It has been previously reported that AngII-stimulated ERK activation  reaches maximal levels with this concentration in HEK-293 cells transiently  expressing AT1AR  (33). Apoptotic stimulation by  either hydrogen peroxide (H2O2)  (Fig. 1A) or etoposide  (Fig. 1B) dramatically  increases the level of cleaved caspase-3 in control VSMCs. The levels of  cleaved caspase-3 induced by such apoptotic stimuli were reduced to ~50%  by AngII pretreatment (Fig. 1, C  and D). Next, we examined the effects of siRNA-mediated  beta-arrestin-2 knock-down on AngII-promoted protection from caspase-3  cleavage. Depletion of beta-arrestin-2 not only leads to increases (up to  ~150%) in the induction of cleaved caspase-3 levels by treatment with  hydrogen peroxide or etoposide, but also eliminates AngII-mediated decreases  in these levels (Fig. 1, C and  D). On the other hand, knocking-down beta-arrestin-1  leads to decreases in apoptotic reagent-induced caspase-3 cleavage even in the  absence of stimulation with AngII, which is similar in extent to the  protection observed in AngII-treated control cells. Stimulation with AngII  results in no significant further protection in cells knocked down for  beta-arrestin-1 (data not shown). These results suggest an essential role of  beta-arrestin-2 in AngII-stimulated protection from caspase-dependent  apoptotic processes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15232</offset><text>Because the release of cytochrome c from mitochondria is one of  the key upstream events for the coordinated activation of caspases  (34,  37), we next examined effects  of AngII stimulation on the hydrogen peroxide-induced redistribution of  cytochrome c in control or beta-arrestin-2 siRNA-transfected VSMCs.  In the absence of an apoptotic challenge, cytochrome c is well  distributed within cytoplasmic, mitochondrial networks in control cells  (Fig. 1E, upper  left panel). Treatment with hydrogen peroxide leads to the rearrangement  of cytochrome c into a cytoplasmic dotted pattern in cells  (Fig. 1E, upper  middle panel). Hydrogen peroxide-induced redistribution of cytochrome  c is largely reversed by prior stimulation with AngII  (Fig. 1E, upper  right panel). These staining patterns of cytochrome c are, in  all cases, superimposed with that of the Mito-Tracker, a mitochondrial marker  (supplemental Fig. S1), confirming that the changes in the staining patterns  of cytochrome c shown in Fig.  1E indeed represent mitochondrial remodeling.  Mitochondrial rearrangement and fragmentation have been observed in apoptotic  cells, especially when apoptosis has been induced by pro-apoptotic members of  the Bcl-2 family of proteins  (38,  39). Depletion of  beta-arrestin-2 has no effect on mitochondrial network organization  (Fig. 1E, lower  left panel), and does not alter the pattern of fragmentation observed  after hydrogen peroxide treatment (Fig.  1E, lower middle panel). However, unlike control  siRNA-transfected cells, pre-stimulation with AngII fails to reverse the  hydrogen peroxide-induced mitochondrial fragmentation in beta-arrestin-2  siRNA-transfected cells (Fig.  1E, lower right panel). These results further  support an important role for beta-arrestin-2 in mediating AngII-stimulated  anti-apoptotic activity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17079</offset><text>To further validate these findings, we measured DNA fragmentation, a  hallmark of cell death, in VSMCs transfected with either control or  beta-arrestin-2 siRNAs. Treatment with hydrogen peroxide  (Fig. 1F) or etoposide  (Fig. 1G) causes a  4-6-fold increase in DNA fragmentation. In control siRNA-transfected cells,  pre-stimulation with AngII reduces (by ~40%) the extent of DNA  fragmentation induced by both reagents  (Fig. 1, F and  G). On the contrary, we did not observe decreases in DNA  fragmentation after prestimulation with AngII in beta-arrestin-2  siRNA-transfected cells (Fig. 1, F  and G), mirroring the situation observed with caspase-3  activation. In the case of beta-arrestin-1 knock-down, effects on DNA  fragmentation also mirror the effects observed with caspase-3 cleavage (data  not shown). Taken together, these results demonstrate that beta-arrestin-2  is crucial for AngII-stimulated protection of VSMCs from apoptotic cell  death.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18039</offset><text>To establish whether the beta-arrestin-2-dependent  AT1R-mediated inhibition of apoptotic processes can be accomplished  in the absence of G protein activation, we stimulated VSMCs with an AngII  analog, [Sar1,Ile4,Ile8]AngII (SII). This  mutant form of AngII was previously shown not to activate G proteins  (21,  30). As shown in  Fig. 1, H and  I, stimulation of the cells with SII leads to significant  decreases (35-45%) in the levels of cleaved caspase-3 upon hydrogen peroxide  or etoposide treatment. The extent of DNA fragmentation induced by these  reagents is also reduced to a similar extent upon prestimulation with SII  (Fig. 1J). The extent  of SII-stimulated decreases (30-45%) in both assays is similar to those evoked  by AngII stimulation (40-50%). This result demonstrates that activation of the  AT1 receptor elicits cytoprotective effects mainly through G  protein-independent signaling.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>18949</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-2, but not activation of G proteins, is essential for  AngII-promoted cytoprotection against apoptotic challenges in rat VSMCs.  A-G, primary cultured VSMCs were transfected with either control  (CTL) or simultaneously two different beta-arrestin-2  (betaarr2) siRNAs. A and B, cells were stimulated  with AngII before either H2O2 (A) or etoposide  (B) treatment as described under &quot;Experimental  Procedures.&quot; Pro- and cleaved caspase-3 were visualized by  immunoblotting (IB). C and D, contents of cleaved  caspase-3 in the immunoblots were quantified and expressed as percent of the  level obtained in H2O2-(C) or etoposide-  (D) treated cells in the absence of stimulation with AngII. Data  represent the mean +- S.E. from at least five independent experiments.  E, 50 mum Z-VAD-fmk was treated to block  caspase-dependent cell death before stimulation with AngII. At ~6 h after  H2O2 treatment, cellular distribution of cytochrome  c was visualized by immunostaining. Images shown represent similar  results obtained from three independent experiments. F and  G, the amounts of H2O2-(F) or  etoposide- (G) induced DNA fragmentation in the absence or presence  of stimulation with AngII were measured as described under &quot;Experimental  Procedures.&quot; Values were expressed as folds over basal in  non-stimulated, non-treated (NT), CTL-siRNA-transfected cells and  represent the mean +- S.E. from at least six independent experiments.  H-J, VSMCs were stimulated with SII prior to treatment with either  H2O2 or etoposide as indicated. The amounts of cleaved  caspase-3 (H and I) and fragmented DNA (J) were  determined and expressed as described above. Data represent the mean +-  S.E. from at least 5 (I) or 6 (J) independent experiments.  All statistical analyses were performed as described under &quot;Experimental  Procedures.&quot;</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20791</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-2 Mediates Activation of ERK-RSK and AKT Signaling  Pathways, Leading to Phosphorylation of BAD in AngII-stimulated  VSMCs:Recently a growing list of biochemical pathways has been  shown to be stimulated via 7TMRs through beta-arrestin-dependent mechanisms  (2). These include the ERK1/2  MAPKs  (21-26)  and AKT (27). Because both ERK  and AKT signaling are reported to exert cytoprotective actions, we examined  their possible involvement in the anti-apoptotic effects of AngII on VSMCs.  Here we demonstrate that in VSMCs stimulated with AngII, ERK1/2 are activated,  and this is significantly reduced by siRNA-mediated knock-down of  beta-arrestin-2 (Fig. 2,  A-C). The reduction is observed only after a  2-min stimulation, suggesting that, as previously shown in HEK-293 cells  (22), prior to that time  activation proceeds exclusively through G protein-dependent mechanisms.  Ribosomal S6 kinase (RSK) is a well known downstream kinase for ERK signaling  and it mediates a variety of physiological responses including anti-apoptosis  (40,  41). Furthermore, RSK is  activated by phosphorylation in the cytoplasm  (40,  41) where ERK activated by  beta-arrestin-dependent mechanisms is confined  (22,  26). Moreover, our recent high  throughput proteomics screening using the stable isotope labeling amino acid  in cell culture method have revealed that the level of p90RSK phosphorylation  is increased by SII stimulation in HEK-293 cells expressing the  AT1A  receptor.3  Accordingly, we next tested whether phosphorylation of p90RSK occurs upon  stimulation with AngII and whether this is mediated by beta-arrestin-2. As  shown in Fig. 2, D and  E, the kinetic pattern of AngII-stimulated p90RSK  phosphorylation, particularly at ERK sites Thr359/Ser363  (40,  41), is similar to that for  ERK activation. In control siRNA-transfected cells, p90RSK phosphorylation  also reaches a maximal level at 5 min after stimulation although it lags  slightly behind ERK activation (compare 2-min points in  Fig. 2, C versus E)  and decreases gradually over 20 min. Silencing beta-arrestin-2 expression  leads to rapid and transient p90RSK phosphorylation, also similar to ERK  activation. These results suggest that ERKs activated through both  beta-arrestin-2- and G protein-dependent pathways can phosphorylate RSK.  However, beta-arrestin-2-mediated phosphorylation of p90RSK is much slower  and more prolonged than that due to activation of the  beta-arrestin-2-independent pathway, which is presumably  G-protein-mediated.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23332</offset><text>RSK is also known to have many downstream targets mediating numerous  physiological responses (40,  41). One such target is the  pro-apoptotic protein BAD and its phosphorylation by RSK is known to inhibit  its pro-apoptotic functions  (14-16).  Accordingly, we next examined phosphorylation of BAD at Ser113  (known to be a preferred RSK site) in VSMCs. In these cells, beta-arrestin-2  RNA interference interestingly leads to almost complete attenuation in  AT1R-mediated BAD phosphorylation  (Fig. 2, F and  G). Taken together, our results suggest that  AngII-induced RSK phosphorylation by ERK is partially mediated by  beta-arrestin-2- (especially &gt;2 min) and G protein (&lt;2 min)-dependent  pathways. Nonetheless, it is predominantly RSK activated through the  beta-arrestin-2-mediated pathway that phosphorylates BAD upon activation of  the AT1 receptors in VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24202</offset><text>To further validate the beta-arrestin-2-dependent nature of the  AT1R-mediated activation of the ERK/p90RSK/BAD cascade, we  stimulated the VSMCs with SII, which cannot activate G protein signaling. As  shown in Fig. 2, H and  I, SII stimulates both p90RSK and phosphorylation of BAD  at the RSK site, thus confirming the G protein independence of these  responses.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24568</offset><text>Another kinase that is known to phosphorylate and inactivate BAD leading to  anti-apoptotic effects is AKT  (17,  18). Moreover,  beta-arrestin-mediated activation of AKT has been demonstrated for 7TM  protease-activated receptors  (27) as well as for the  receptor tyrosine kinase insulin-like growth factor 1 receptor  (6). Accordingly, we tested the  ability of AngII to promote phosphorylation of the stimulatory site,  Ser473, of AKT in the VSMCs. As shown in  Fig. 2, J and  K, time-dependent phosphorylation was observed, which was  inhibited by beta-arrestin-2 siRNAs at times later than 2 min of  stimulation, indicating that this process is mediated in part by  beta-arrestin-2.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25257</offset><text>RSK- and AKT-mediated Phosphorylations of BAD Are Essential for  AngII-stimulated Cell Protection:Our data suggest that RSK- and/or  AKT-mediated phosphorylation of BAD might be a molecular mechanism that is  responsible for the beta-arrestin-2-mediated anti-apoptotic effects of AngII  on VSMCs. To test this hypothesis, we first examined the effects of the RSK  inhibitor SL0101 and the PI3K inhibitor LY294002, which is known to block AKT  activation, on AngII-induced anti-apoptosis in VSMCs. Treatment with either  SL0101 or LY294002 completely ablates the ability of AngII to protect against  etoposide-induced apoptosis as assessed by either caspase-3 cleavage  (Fig. 3, A and  C) or DNA fragmentation  (Fig. 3D).  Fig. 3B shows that  LY294002 blocks AngII-induced activation of AKT as assessed by phosphorylation  of AKT Ser473, and SL0101 blocks phosphorylation of BAD at the RSK  site, BAD Ser113. These results strongly support the thesis that  beta-arrestin-2 mediates AngII-stimulated cell protection by regulating RSK-  and AKT-mediated phosphorylation of BAD. Moreover the concerted activation of  both pathways appears to be necessary because blockade of either alone  completely eliminates the anti-apoptotic effect.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26491</offset><text>To directly test whether RSK- and AKT-mediated phosphorylation of BAD are  required for the anti-apoptotic actions of AngII, we studied the nature of  overexpressed wild-type and phosphorylation-deficient mutants of BAD in VSMCs.  We used the two mouse mutants BAD S112A and BAD S136A that are defective in  RSK- and AKT-mediated phosphorylation, respectively  (14,  18). Overexpression of  wild-type BAD in the VSMCs leads to a typical apoptotic pattern of  mitochondrial fragmentation as visualized by cytochrome c staining,  whereas cells that do not express BAD show an intact mitochondrial  architecture (Fig.  3E). Essentially identical images were obtained with the  two mutant forms of BAD (supplemental Fig. S2), confirming the abilities of  all these three forms of BAD to induce apoptosis upon overexpression.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27312</offset><text>Next we examined caspase-3 activation in cells expressing the three BAD  constructs (Fig. 3, F and  G). Despite relatively inefficient (&lt;10%) transfection  of the cells, robust increases in the levels of cleaved caspase-3 were  observed in all cases (Fig. 3, F  and G). In this system, AngII stimulation leads to  partial but significant (~30%) decreases in these levels in cells  overexpressing the wild-type BAD, whereas such reductions are not observed in  cells expressing BAD S112A or BAD S136A  (Fig. 3G). These  results support the conclusion that RSK- and AKT-mediated phosphorylation of  BAD are required for AngII-stimulated, beta-arrestin-2-mediated  cytoprotective processes. Furthermore, the results are consistent with the  findings shown above (Fig. 3,  A-D) that both activities of RSK and AKT are  essential for AngII-stimulated protection from apoptotic stimuli.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>28193</offset><text>Effects of silencing beta-arrestin-2 expression on ERK-RSK-BAD  phosphorylation as well as AKT activation in response to AngII in rat  VSMCs. A-G, indicated siRNA-transfected VSMCs were serum-starved  for ~24 h and then stimulated with 100 nm AngII at 37  C  for the indicated periods. After stimulation, expression of beta-arrestins  (A) and phosphorylation of ERK1/2 (B), p90RSK at  Thr359/Ser363 (D), and BAD at Ser113  (F) were visualized by immunoblotting (IB). C,  contents of ERK1/2 phosphorylation in the immunoblots (left panels)  were quantified and normalized by the amount of total ERK1/2 (right  panels). Values were expressed as percent of the maximal phosphorylation  of ERK1/2 obtained in control (CTL) siRNA-transfected cells. Data  were obtained from five independent experiments. E and G,  the amounts of p90RSK (E) and BAD (G) phosphorylation shown  in the immunoblots were measured and determined as described for C.  Data were obtained from six independent experiments. H and  I, serum-starved VSMCs were stimulated with 10 mum SII  for 5 min. The level of SII-induced p90RSK and BAD phosphorylation were  determined as described above and expressed folds over basal phosphorylation  in non-stimulated (NS) cells. Values were obtained from seven  independent experiments (I). J and K,  siRNA-transfected VSMCs were serum-starved and then stimulated with 100  nm AngII for the indicated periods. AKT phosphorylation at  Ser473 was visualized (J) and determined (K) as  described for C from six independent experiments. In all graphs, each  data point represents the mean +- S.E., and statistical analyses were  carried out as described under &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot;</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29883</offset><text>The AT1AR-stimulated ERK-RSK-BAD Phosphorylation Cascade in  HEK-293 Cells Is Also Mediated by  beta-Arrestin-2:Phosphorylation of BAD is thought to control  its apoptotic activity by regulating its functionally antagonistic binding to  anti-apoptotic proteins such as Bcl-xL (dephosphorylated form)  (11,  20) or the scaffold protein  14-3-3 (phosphorylated form)  (19). Accordingly, we wished  to determine the effects of beta-arrestin-2-mediated phosphorylation of BAD  on its binding to Bcl-xL and 14-3-3. However, we were unable to detect the  interaction of these proteins expressed at physiological levels in VSMCs with  our co-immunoprecipitation assay. Alternatively, we found that we were able to  perform such experiments with these proteins endogenously expressed in HEK-293  cells expressing the AT1A receptor. However, such experiments are  only relevant to the situation in VSMCs if the signaling pathway we have  identified in the VSMCs also operates in the HEK-293 cells. As shown in  Fig. 4, A-C,  in HEK-293 cells stably transfected with a plasmid expressing the  AT1A receptor, AngII provokes a protracted activation (assessed by  phosphorylation of Thr359/Ser363) of p90RSK. Two  different beta-arrestin-2 siRNAs (Fig.  4A) inhibit this response  (Fig. 4B), but only at  times after 5 min of stimulation (Fig.  4C). In contrast, the protein kinase C (PKC) inhibitor  Ro31-8425 or GF109203X, which has been shown in HEK-293 cells to block G  protein-dependent ERK activation by AngII  (21,  22), inhibits the early  component of p90RSK activation (Fig.  4C). Confirming that virtually all of the AngII-induced  phosphorylation of p90RSK at Thr359 and Ser363 is  mediated by ERK, the MEK inhibitor U0126 completely abolishes the p90RSK  phosphorylation response (Fig.  4C). These patterns of sensitivities to PKC blockade and  beta-arrestin-2 siRNA directly parallel our previous findings for  AngII-stimulated phosphorylation of ERK in these cells  (22).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31858</offset><text>Despite this evidence that beta-arrestin-2-mediated ERK activation  accounts for only the later (&gt;5 min) occurring phosphorylation of p90RSK,  the data in Fig. 4, D and  E, suggest that, as in the VSMCs, almost all of the  downstream phosphorylation of BAD by RSK is mediated by the pool of p90RSK,  which is activated through beta-arrestin-dependent ERK. After  beta-arrestin-2 siRNA transfection, there is almost complete loss of the  AngII-stimulated BAD phosphorylation at Ser75, the homologous site  of Ser113 in human BAD (Fig. 4,  D and E). As expected, virtually all the BAD  phosphorylation at this site is also blocked by the selective RSK inhibitor  SL0101 and MEK inhibitor U0126 (Fig.  4E). Because PKC inhibitors have been shown to  efficiently block RSK, which belongs to the same AGC kinase family as PKC  (42), their effects on BAD  phosphorylation could not be reliably studied.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32755</offset><text>To further validate the G protein-independent nature of the phosphorylation  of p90RSK and BAD, we stimulated HEK-293 cells expressing the AT1A  receptor with SII. As shown in Fig. 4,  F and G, this stimulation leads to prolonged  increases in both p90RSK and BAD phosphorylation. Taken together, results in  Fig. 4 confirm that the  AT1R-beta-arrestin-2-ERK-p90RSK-BAD pathway delineated in rat  VSMCs (Fig. 2) is also  operative in HEK-293 cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33204</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-2 Regulates Interactions of BAD with Its Partners upon  AngII Stimulation:As noted above, the dynamic interactions of BAD  with its partners regulate the pro-apoptotic function of BAD  (11,  19,  20). Our results demonstrate  that BAD phosphorylation by RSK is mediated predominantly by  beta-arrestin-2-dependent signaling (Figs.  2G and  4E) and also suggest  that its phosphorylation by AKT is partially dependent on beta-arrestin-2  (Fig. 2K).  Accordingly, we examined BAD interactions with its partners at their  endogenous levels upon AngII stimulation in control or beta-arrestin-2  siRNA-transfected HEK-293 cells stably expressing AT1A receptors.  Stimulation with AngII leads to a significant increase in the amount of BAD  present in 14-3-3 protein immunoprecipitates in control cells  (Fig. 5, A and  B). In parallel, the quantity of the 14-3-3 protein  co-immunoprecipitated with BAD is augmented by AT1A receptor  activation (Fig. 5, C and  D). AT1AR-mediated increases in the  interaction of BAD with 14-3-3 shown by both BAD and 14-3-3  immunoprecipitation are eliminated in beta-arrestin-2 siRNA-transfected  cells (Fig. 5, A-D).  Conversely, we found that AngII stimulation decreases the interaction of BAD  with Bcl-xL. Fig. 5, E and  F, show the reduced amount of Bcl-xL in BAD  immunoprecipitates upon AngII stimulation in control cells. This reduction is  not observed in beta-arrestin-2 siRNA-transfected cells.  Fig. 5, G and  H, show that in the HEK-293 cell lysates used in these  experiments, AngII-stimulated BAD phosphorylation at the RSK site  (Ser75) is completely abolished by beta-arrestin-2 siRNA, as  shown in Fig. 4E.  Taken together, these results demonstrate that activation of AT1  receptors leads to a beta-arrestin-2-dependent increase in BAD interaction  with 14-3-3 and a decrease in its association with Bcl-xL, resulting in an  anti-apoptotic signal. Moreover, the results strongly suggest that  AngII-stimulated changes in BAD complex formation are mediated by p90RSK and  AKT phosphorylation of BAD in a beta-arrestin-2-dependent manner.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>35304</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35315</offset><text>The present study shows that beta-arrestin-2 plays a crucial role in  AngII-stimulated anti-apoptotic responses and delineates the downstream  biochemical pathways responsible for this AngII-stimulated,  beta-arrestin-2-mediated cytoprotection from apoptotic challenge. Upon  stimulation with AngII, the pro-apoptotic protein BAD is phosphorylated  through two signaling pathways, ERK-p90RSK and PI3K-AKT. Activation of both  pathways appears to be beta-arrestin-2-dependent. This  beta-arrestin-2-dependent BAD phosphorylation leads to increases in  BAD-14-3-3 association and decreases in the interaction of BAD with Bcl-xL.  Such changes in the association of BAD with its partners lead to attenuation  of its pro-apoptotic function, resulting in AngII-stimulated protection from  apoptotic challenges. There have been reports implicating beta-arrestins in  both pro- and anti-apoptotic responses as well as in non-apoptotic cell death  (3-10).  However, the biochemical pathways through which beta-arrestins mediate these  responses upon 7TMR activation have not been delineated. The results reported  here establish a downstream molecular mechanism by which beta-arrestin-2  mediates anti-apoptosis in response to activation of the physiologically  important AT1 receptor in a non-transfected natural cell, VSMC.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36633</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-mediated, but G protein-independent, activation of ERK1/2  has been a focus of study for the functions of beta-arrestins as signal  transducers for 7TMR activation  (2,  21-25).  In the case of AT1AR-mediated ERK activation, it has been  demonstrated that upon activation of the receptor, beta-arrestin-2 scaffolds  the components of the ERK cascade, Raf-1, MEK1, and ERK1/2, into the receptor  complex, leading to activation of ERK1/2  (2,  43). In addition, we have  previously shown that beta-arrestin-2-dependent activation displays distinct  temporal and spatial patterns from those due to G protein-dependent activation  (22). In particular, ERK  activated via the beta-arrestin-2-dependent pathway is confined to the  cytoplasm, whereas ERK activated via G proteins translocates into the nucleus  (22,  26). These distinct patterns  strongly suggest that the substrates of ERK activated via  beta-arrestin-2-mediated signaling may be largely cytoplasmic. Cytoplasmic  ERK activity appears to be important in the regulation of cell morphology,  migration, and viability (2,  22). However, very little is  known about how phosphorylation of cytoplasmic ERK substrates, downstream of  beta-arrestin signaling, regulates cellular responses. The only known  example is the very recent finding that beta-arrestin-2-mediated ERK  activation by the AT1 receptor leads to an increase in protein  synthesis via activation of a downstream kinase, Mnk1  (32). The present study  reveals anti-apoptosis mediated by BAD phosphorylation as another downstream  response of beta-arrestin-mediated ERK signaling stimulated by a 7TMR. These  results thus expand our understanding of the roles of beta-arrestin in  determining the physiological outcomes of signaling initiated from 7TMRs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>38423</offset><text>Kinase activities of both RSK and AKT as well as BAD phosphorylation are  required for AngII-promoted cellular protection in rat VSMCs.  A-D, serum-starved VSMCs were incubated with either 100  mum SL0101 for 2 h or 1 mum LY294004 for 1 h at 37   C before stimulation with AngII and following etoposide treatment.  A and C, contents of pro- and cleaved caspase-3 were  visualized (A), and the amounts of cleaved caspase-3 were determined  (C) as described in the legend to  Fig. 1. Values were expressed  as percent of the level obtained in vehicle alone (dimethyl sulfoxide,  DMSO) and then etoposide-treated cells in the absence of stimulation  with AngII and represent the mean +- S.E. from seven independent  experiments (C). B, after stimulation with AngII for 5 min,  phosphorylation of AKT at Ser473 and BAD at Ser113 were  visualized by immunoblotting (IB). D, levels of fragmented  DNA were measured and expressed as described for C. Data represent  the mean +- S.E. from seven independent experiments. E-G, VSMCs  were transfected with each plasmid expressing the indicated BAD. Empty pcDNA3  was used as a transfection control. E, cells were treated with 50  mum Z-VAD-fmk during transfection. Within 24 h after  transfection, cellular distribution of cytochrome c (green)  and expression of hemagglutinin-tagged BAD (red) were visualized by  immunostaining. Images shown represent similar results obtained from four  independent experiments. F, approximately 6 h after transfection,  cells were stimulated with 300 nm AngII and incubated overnight.  Contents of pro- and cleaved caspase-3 were visualized by immunoblotting.  G, the amounts of cleaved caspase-3 were measured and expressed as  percent of the maximum level obtained from each 10 independent experiment.  Values represent the mean +- S.E. All statistical analyses were carried  out as described under &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot;</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40327</offset><text>Besides ERK1/2, beta-arrestins have been implicated in the regulation of  various other signaling molecules. These include other MAPKs, JNK3, and p38 as  well as c-Src, PI3K, AKT, and RhoA  (2). Most of these molecules  have been shown to be involved in regulation of apoptosis. In the case of AKT  for example, it has been reported that deficiency of beta-arrestins 1 and 2  leads to loss of AKT activation and anti-apoptotic effects following  insulin-like growth factor 1 stimulation in mouse embryonic fibroblasts  (6). Although there has been a  report showing beta-arrestin-1-dependent AKT activation in response to  thrombin mediated through 7TM protease-activated receptors  (27), its function in  apoptosis was not studied. Our present data show that stimulation of the  AT1 receptor leads to AKT activation in a  beta-arrestin-2-dependent manner (Fig. 2,  J and K). Our results also demonstrate that the  activity of PI3K, the upstream kinase of AKT, is required for AngII-stimulated  protection from apoptotic challenges in VSMCs  (Fig. 3, C and  D). As described above, beta-arrestin might regulate  apoptotic processes through multiple mechanisms. In fact, the present study  indicates that beta-arrestin-2 mediates the anti-apoptotic response to AngII  through two different pathways, ERK-RSK and PI3K-AKT.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>41648</offset><text>beta-Arrestin-2 also mediates the ERK-RSK-BAD phosphorylation cascade  upon stimulation of the AT1A receptor stably expressed in HEK-293  cells. A-E, cells were transfected with the indicated siRNAs and  serum starved for ~6 h. During starvation, inhibitors were pre-treated  before stimulation: 1 mum Ro31-8425, 2.5 mum  GF109203X (GFX), and 5 mum U0126 for 30 min; 100  mum SL0101 for 2 h. After stimulation with 100 nm  AngII at 37  C for the indicated periods, whole cell extracts were  prepared to visualize expression beta-arrestins (A) and  phosphorylation of p90RSK at Thr359/Ser363 (B)  and BAD at Ser75 (D) by immunoblotting (IB).  Levels of p90RSK (C) and BAD (D) phosphorylation in each  sample were determined as described for  Fig. 2 and expressed as percent  of the maximal phosphorylation in control (CTL) siRNA-transfected  cells. Data were obtained from at least three independent experiments.  F and G, serum-starved AT1AR-expressing HEK-293  cells were stimulated with 10 mum SII for the indicated periods.  Contents of p90RSK (left panel) and BAD (right panel)  phosphorylation were visualized (F) and determined (G).  Levels of phosphorylation in each time point were expressed as percent of the  maximal phosphorylation obtained in three independent experiments  (G). In all graphs, each data point represents the mean +- S.E.  and statistical analyses were carried out as described under  &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot;</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43088</offset><text>We show that p90RSK is a kinase that transfers the beta-arrestin-mediated  ERK activation signal to anti-apoptotic effects in response to AT1  receptor activation. RSK is a well known ERK substrate and mediates signals to  many cellular responses, including cell survival, through phosphorylation of  its downstream targets (40,  41). One such target is BAD,  which RSK phosphorylates at serine 113 (in the case of rat BAD)  (14-16).  In addition to RSK, PKA and AKT have been considered as putative upstream  kinases for BAD phosphorylation  (16,  17,  44). Nonetheless, our data  show that inhibition of either ERK or RSK, but not PI3K activities completely  abolishes phosphorylation of BAD at this site following activation of the  AT1 receptor (Figs.  3B and  4E). Such data clearly  demonstrate that BAD phosphorylation at Ser113 in response to  AT1 receptor activation is mediated through the ERK-RSK pathway. In  addition to the ERK-RSK-BAD pathway, our data show that blockade of the  PI3K-AKT pathway also eliminates AngII-stimulated anti-apoptosis  (Fig. 3, C and  D). However, this PI3K/AKT-dependent anti-apoptotic  effect must be mediated through phosphorylation of BAD at a different site,  e.g. Ser136  (17,  18) or possibly  phosphorylation of other targets  (45).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44370</offset><text>Our data show that knocking-down beta-arrestin-2 expression leads to  almost complete inhibition in RSK-mediated phosphorylation of BAD following  AT1 receptor activation (Figs.  2, F and G,  and 4, D and  E), suggesting that this process may be entirely  beta-arrestin-2-mediated. These results are quite interesting in view of the  previous and present findings that ERK activation in response to stimulation  of the AT1 receptor is mediated both by independent  beta-arrestin-2- and G protein-mediated signaling pathways  (21,  22). The data presented here  also show that activation of p90RSK, the kinase that transfers signals from  activated ERK to BAD phosphorylation, is mediated through these two pathways  (Fig. 2, D and  E, and 4, B  and C). Furthermore, we have previously demonstrated that  PKC activity is essential for G protein-dependent, but not  beta-arrestin-mediated signaling to ERK activation following stimulation of  the AT1A receptor  (21,  22). There have been reports  that PKC is involved in RSK-mediated BAD phosphorylation  (46,  47), implying that G  protein-dependent signaling might be involved. However, we found that SII, a  mutant ligand that fails to activate G proteins, induces BAD phosphorylation  by RSK (Figs. 2, H and  I, and 4, F  and G) as well as promotes anti-apoptotic effects  (Fig. 1,  H-J). This strongly supports the contention that  AT1R-mediated BAD phosphorylation via the ERK-RSK pathway in VSMCs  as well as HEK-293 cells is G protein-independent. Furthermore, we have  previously shown that restriction of activated ERK to the cytoplasm, where BAD  resides (13), is one of the  striking characteristics of beta-arrestin-, but not G protein-dependent ERK  activation (22,  26). Consequently,  AT1R-induced phosphorylation of BAD by RSK provides an example of  how an appreciation of the distinct characteristics of beta-arrestin  versus G protein signaling can illuminate issues of apparent  &quot;compartmentalization&quot; of cellular signaling events.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>46372</offset><text>Effects of beta-arrestin-2 knocking down on AngII-induced  interaction of BAD with its partners in AT1AR-stably expressing  HEK-293 cells. Cells were transfected with either control (CTL)  or beta-arrestin-2 (betaarr2) siRNA. After transfection, cells  were serum-starved for ~6 h and then stimulated with 100 nm  AngII for 30 min. A, cell lysates were prepared and used for  immunoprecipitation (IP) with a 14-3-3 antibody. The BAD protein  co-immunoprecipitated with 14-3-3 was visualized by immunoblotting  (IB) (upper blot), and its amount in each sample was  quantified and normalized by the amounts of BAD in input lysates (lower  blot). B, values were expressed as folds over the basal level  obtained in non-stimulated (NS), CTL siRNA-transfected cells. Data  were obtained from four independent experiments. C-F, after  immunoprecipitation with a BAD antibody, co-immunoprecipitated 14-3-3  (C) and Bcl-xL (E) proteins with BAD were visualized, and  their amounts were determined as described for A. D, data were  expressed as folds over the basal level and obtained from three independent  experiments. F, values were expressed as percent of the basal level  and obtained from four independent experiments. G and H,  phosphorylation of BAD at Ser75 in each lysate used for  immunoprecipitation experiments were visualized (G) and measured  (H). Data were expressed as percent of the response to AngII in CTL  siRNA-transfected cells and obtained from four independent experiments  (H). In all graphs, values represent the mean +- S.E., and  statistical analyses were carried out as described under &quot;Experimental  Procedures.&quot;</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>48008</offset><text>Apoptosis of VSMCs plays a significant role in vascular remodeling as well  as in vascular diseases, including atherosclerosis and neointima formation  after injury, which are also associated with cell proliferation  (34,  48,  49). AngII is a well known  cell survival factor for VSMCs  (28,  29,  34). Our data establish a  mechanism by which AngII leads to cellular protection as well as demonstrate  that beta-arrestin-2 is a key mediator of this mechanism. Our results thus  suggest that beta-arrestin-2 may play an important role in vascular diseases  and remodeling, and raise the possibility that beta-arrestins may represent  a therapeutic target in such diseases. Several previous findings support this  idea. Atherosclerotic human coronary arteries show up-regulated (~2-fold  higher) beta-arrestin-2 mRNA levels compared with normal human coronary  arteries (50).  beta-Arrestin-2 appears to be the predominant beta-arrestin isoform in the  atherosclerotic lesion (48).  Moreover, deficiency of beta-arrestin-2 leads to reduced aortic  atherosclerosis and a decrease in the prevalence of atheroma SMCs in low  density lipoprotein receptor-deficient mice  (48). In agreement with our  results, it also has been reported that beta-arrestin-2 knock-out mice show  augmented medial SMC apoptosis in carotid arteries after endothelial  denudation to induce neointimal hyperplasia  (48). Furthermore, ERK and AKT  activation in SMCs of injured arteries is reduced in beta-arrestin-2  knock-out mice compared with wild-type animals  (48).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>49552</offset><text>In summary, the present study reveals anti-apoptosis as a physiological  consequence of beta-arrestin-mediated signaling upon activation of the 7TM  AT1 receptor, and delineates the beta-arrestin-2-mediated  anti-apoptotic pathways. These results also provide better understanding of  the role of beta-arrestin-2 in apoptosis-related vascular diseases at the  molecular level and may allow the development of therapeutic agents that  target the beta-arrestins for such diseases.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>50031</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>50054</offset><text>   </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>50058</offset><text>  </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hall, R. A., Premont, R. T., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -932</infon><infon key="fpage">927</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10352011</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">145</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>50061</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DeWire, S. M., Ahn, S., Lefkowitz, R. J., and Shenoy, S. K.  ()    -510</infon><infon key="fpage">483</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17305471</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">69</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>50062</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shi, Y., Feng, Y., Kang, J., Liu, C., Li, Z., Li, D., Cao, W., Qiu,  J., Guo, Z., Bi, E., Zang, L., Lu, C., Zhang, J. Z., and Pei, G.  ()    -824</infon><infon key="fpage">817</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17618287</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Immunol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>50063</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhao, M., Wimmer, A., Trieu, K., Discipio, R. G., and  Schraufstatter, I. U. ()    -49267</infon><infon key="fpage">49259</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15364949</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>50064</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Revankar, C. M., Vines, C. M., Cimino, D. F., and Prossnitz, E. R.  ()     -24584</infon><infon key="fpage">24578</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15051714</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>50065</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Povsic, T. J., Kohout, T. A., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -51339</infon><infon key="fpage">51334</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14534298</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>50066</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DeFea, K. A., Vaughn, Z. D., O'Bryan, E. M., Nishijima, D., Dery,  O., and Bunnett, N. W. ()    -11091</infon><infon key="fpage">11086</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10995467</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.  U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>50067</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Luan, B., Zhang, Z., Wu, Y., Kang, J., and Pei, G.  ()     -4246</infon><infon key="fpage">4237</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16308565</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>50068</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wang, P., Gao, H., Ni, Y., Wang, B., Wu, Y., Ji, L., Qin, L., Ma,  L., and Pei, G. ()     -6370</infon><infon key="fpage">6363</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12488444</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>50069</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Castro-Obregon, S., Rao, R. V., del Rio, G., Chen, S. F., Poksay,  K. S., Rabizadeh, S., Vesce, S., Zhang, X. K., Swanson, R. A., and Bredesen,  D. E. ()     -17553</infon><infon key="fpage">17543</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14769794</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>50070</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Adams, J. M., and Cory, S. ()     -1337</infon><infon key="fpage">1324</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17322918</infon><infon key="source">Oncogene</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>50071</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Datta, S. R., Ranger, A. M., Lin, M. Z., Sturgill, J. F., Ma, Y.  C., Cowan, C. W., Dikkes, P., Korsmeyer, S. J., and Greenberg, M. E.  ()    -643</infon><infon key="fpage">631</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12431371</infon><infon key="source">Dev. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>50072</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bergmann, A. ()    -608</infon><infon key="fpage">607</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12431365</infon><infon key="source">Dev. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>50073</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bonni, A., Brunet, A., West, A. E., Datta, S. R., Takasu, M. A.,  and Greenberg, M. E. ()     -1362</infon><infon key="fpage">1358</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10558990</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">286</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>50074</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shimamura, A., Ballif, B. A., Richards, S. A., and Blenis, J.  ()    -135</infon><infon key="fpage">127</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10679322</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>50075</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yang, X., Liu, L., Sternberg, D., Tang, L., Galinsky, I., DeAngelo,  D., and Stone, R. ()     -7347</infon><infon key="fpage">7338</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16103085</infon><infon key="source">Cancer Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">65</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>50076</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">del Peso, L., Gonzalez-Garcia, M., Page, C., Herrera, R., and  Nunez, G. ()     -689</infon><infon key="fpage">687</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9381178</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>50077</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Datta, S. R., Dudek, H., Tao, X., Masters, S., Fu, H., Gotoh, Y.,  and Greenberg, M. E. ()    -241</infon><infon key="fpage">231</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9346240</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>50078</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Datta, S. R., Katsov, A., Hu, L., Petros, A., Fesik, S. W., Yaffe,  M. B., and Greenberg, M. E. ()    -51</infon><infon key="fpage">41</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10949026</infon><infon key="source">Mol.  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>50079</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yang, E., Zha, J., Jockel, J., Boise, L. H., Thompson, C. B., and  Korsmeyer, S. J. ()    -291</infon><infon key="fpage">285</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7834748</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">80</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>50080</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wei, H., Ahn, S., Shenoy, S. K., Karnik, S. S., Hunyady, L.,  Luttrell, L. M., and Lefkowitz, R. J. ()    -10787</infon><infon key="fpage">10782</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12949261</infon><infon key="source">Proc.  Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">100</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>50081</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ahn, S., Shenoy, S. K., Wei, H., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -35525</infon><infon key="fpage">35518</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15205453</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>50082</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ren, X. R., Reiter, E., Ahn, S., Kim, J., Chen, W., and Lefkowitz,  R. J. ()    -1453</infon><infon key="fpage">1448</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15671180</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">102</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>50083</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gesty-Palmer, D., Chen, M., Reiter, E., Ahn, S., Nelson, C. D.,  Wang, S., Eckhardt, A. E., Cowan, C. L., Spurney, R. F., Luttrell, L. M., and  Lefkowitz, R. J. ()     -10864</infon><infon key="fpage">10856</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16492667</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>50084</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shenoy, S. K., Drake, M. T., Nelson, C. D., Houtz, D. A., Xiao, K.,  Madabushi, S., Reiter, E., Premont, R. T., Lichtarge, O., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -1273</infon><infon key="fpage">1261</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16280323</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>50085</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tohgo, A., Pierce, K. L., Choy, E. W., Lefkowitz, R. J., and  Luttrell, L. M. ()     -9436</infon><infon key="fpage">9429</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11777902</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>50086</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Goel, R., Phillips-Mason, P. J., Raben, D. M., and Baldassare, J.  J. ()     -18648</infon><infon key="fpage">18640</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11901145</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>50087</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mehta, P. K., and Griendling, K. K. ()     -C97</infon><infon key="fpage">C82</infon><infon key="source">Am. J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">292</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>50088</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nakashima, H., Suzuki, H., Ohtsu, H., Chao, J. Y., Utsunomiya, H.,  Frank, G. D., and Eguchi, S. ()    -78</infon><infon key="fpage">67</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16472178</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Vasc.  Pharmacol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>50089</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Holloway, A. C., Qian, H., Pipolo, L., Ziogas, J., Miura, S.,  Karnik, S., Southwell, B. R., Lew, M. J., and Thomas, W. G.  ()    -777</infon><infon key="fpage">768</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11901215</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Pharmacol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">61</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>50090</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Attramadal, H., Arriza, J. L., Aoki, C., Dawson, T. M., Codina, J.,  Kwatra, M. M., Snyder, S. H., Caron, M. G., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -17890</infon><infon key="fpage">17882</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1517224</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">267</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>50091</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DeWire, S. M., Kim, J., Whalen, E. J., Ahn, S., Chen, M., and  Lefkowitz, R. J. ()     -10620</infon><infon key="fpage">10611</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18276584</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>50092</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ahn, S., Wei, H., Garrison, T. R., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -7811</infon><infon key="fpage">7807</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14711824</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>50093</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mallat, Z., and Tedgui, A. ()    -962</infon><infon key="fpage">947</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10882378</infon><infon key="source">Br. J.  Pharmacol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">130</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>50094</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pollman, M. J., Yamada, T., Horiuchi, M., and Gibbons, G. H.  ()    -756</infon><infon key="fpage">748</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8831498</infon><infon key="source">Circ. Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">79</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>50095</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lee, M. H., El-Shewy, H. M., Luttrell, D. K., and Luttrell, L. M.  ()     -2097</infon><infon key="fpage">2088</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18006496</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>50096</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fabregat, I., Roncero, C., and Fernandez, M. ()     -162</infon><infon key="fpage">155</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17311609</infon><infon key="source">Liver Int.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">27</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>50097</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Desagher, S., and Martinou, J. C. ()     -377</infon><infon key="fpage">369</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10932094</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>50098</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sun, M. G., Williams, J., Munoz-Pinedo, C., Perkins, G. A., Brown,  J. M., Ellisman, M. H., Green, D. R., and Frey, T. G. ()     -1065</infon><infon key="fpage">1057</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17721514</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>50099</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Frodin, M., and Gammeltoft, S. ()    -77</infon><infon key="fpage">65</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10411321</infon><infon key="source">Mol.  Cell. Endocrinol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">151</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>50100</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hauge, C., and Frodin, M. ()    -3023</infon><infon key="fpage">3021</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16868029</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell  Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">119</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>50101</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Davies, S. P., Reddy, H., Caivano, M., and Cohen, P.  ()    -105</infon><infon key="fpage">95</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10998351</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">351</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>50102</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Luttrell, L. M., Roudabush, F. L., Choy, E. W., Miller, W. E.,  Field, M. E., Pierce, K. L., and Lefkowitz, R. J. ()      -2454</infon><infon key="fpage">2449</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11226259</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">98</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>50103</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Harada, H., Becknell, B., Wilm, M., Mann, M., Huang, L. J., Taylor,  S. S., Scott, J. D., and Korsmeyer, S. J. ()    -422</infon><infon key="fpage">413</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10230394</infon><infon key="source">Mol.  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>50104</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Parcellier, A., Tintignac, L. A., Zhuravleva, E., and Hemmings, B.  A. ()    -30</infon><infon key="fpage">21</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17716864</infon><infon key="source">Cell. Signal.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>50105</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lee, K. W., Kim, S. G., Kim, H. P., Kwon, E., You, J., Choi, H. J.,  Park, J. H., Kang, B. C., Im, S. A., Kim, T. Y., Kim, W. H., and Bang, Y. J.  ()     -1926</infon><infon key="fpage">1916</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18339873</infon><infon key="source">Cancer Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">68</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>50106</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tan, Y., Ruan, H., Demeter, M. R., and Comb, M. J.  ()     -34867</infon><infon key="fpage">34859</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10574959</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>50107</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kim, J., Zhang, L., Peppel, K., Wu, J. H., Zidar, D. A., Brian, L.,  DeWire, S. M., Exum, S. T., Lefkowitz, R. J., and Freedman, N. J.  ()    -79</infon><infon key="fpage">70</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18519945</infon><infon key="source">Circ. Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>50108</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Korshunov, V. A., and Berk, B. C. ()     -254</infon><infon key="fpage">250</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18391793</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Hematol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>50109</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Archacki, S. R., Angheloiu, G., Tian, X. L., Tan, F. L., DiPaola,  N., Shen, G. Q., Moravec, C., Ellis, S., Topol, E. J., and Wang, Q.  ()    -74</infon><infon key="fpage">65</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12902549</infon><infon key="source">Physiol. Genomics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>50110</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>50111</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: 7TMR, 7-transmembrane receptor; AngII,  angiotensin II; AT1R, angiotensin II type 1 receptor; ERK,  extracellular signal-regulated kinase; HEK, human embryonic kidney; MAPK,  mitogen-activated protein kinase; PI3K, phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase; PKC,  protein kinase C; RSK, ribosomal S6 kinase; SII,  [Sar1,Ile4,Ile8]angiotensin II; siRNA, small  interfering RNA; VSMC, vascular smooth muscle cell; Z, benzyloxycarbonyl; fmk,  fluoromethyl ketone; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>50620</offset><text>S. Ahn and R. J. Lefkowitz, unpublished data.</text></passage></document></collection>
