<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19193640</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M807043200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2665074</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19193640</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">10202</infon><infon key="fpage">10202</infon><infon key="issue">15</infon><infon key="lpage">10210</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hayes;given-names:Matthew J.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Moss;given-names:Stephen E.</infon><infon key="p">Author's Choice:Final version full  access.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Annexin 2 Has a Dual Role as Regulator and Effector of v-Src in Cell  Transformation*S</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>87</offset><text>Cell transformation by v-Src involves rearrangement of the actin  cytoskeleton, disassembly of focal adhesions, and the development of  anchorage-independent growth. Here, we report that this is dependent on  annexin 2, a v-Src substrate and calcium-dependent regulator of actin  dynamics. Using a thermoactivatable mutant of v-Src, we show that at the  permissive temperature, annexin 2 becomes phosphorylated and colocalizes with  activated v-Src and focal adhesion kinase both at the plasma membrane and in a  Rab11-positive compartment of the endosomal pathway. In cells depleted of  annexin 2 by small interfering RNA, v-Src becomes activated at the permissive  temperature but does not target to the plasma membrane or to perinuclear  vesicles, and cell transformation does not occur. Our findings reveal a dual  role for annexin 2, first as a regulator of v-Src trafficking and targeting  and second as a v-Src effector in the reorganization of actin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1046</offset><text>Annexin 2 was first identified as a major substrate of v-Src, the  transforming gene product of the Rous sarcoma virus  (1-3).  It belongs to a large family of highly conserved proteins, members of which  are present in all eukaryotic phyla and at least one prokaryote  (4,  5). There are 12 annexin genes  in humans, and they are implicated in the pathology of numerous diseases,  including hematological disorders and cancer  (6). The proteins are  characterized by their ability to bind and order membrane phospholipids,  particularly membranes enriched in cholesterol, with binding being most  commonly but not invariably regulated by Ca2+  (7). Some annexins have been  shown to interact with actin  (8-11),  and we recently demonstrated that annexin 2 regulates actin dynamics in  vitro and in vivo by inhibiting actin polymerization at the  rapidly growing barbed ends of actin filaments  (12). Annexin 2 is associated  with early endosomes (13),  recycling endosomes (14), and  phagosomes and enlargeosomes  (15) and is critical for the  actin-dependent rocketing of macropinosomes  (16). In these contexts,  annexin 2 has the capacity to bind the negatively charged lipid components of  the vesicles while also potentially regulating the actin-based structures that  promote vesicle formation, budding, and transport. Spatial and temporal  control of annexin 2 activity may occur through binding to  phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate on the vesicles  (17,  18), which is known to  regulate the activity of many proteins involved in actin remodeling at these  sites (19,  20).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2635</offset><text>Annexin 2 forms a heterotetrameric complex with S100A10 in vivo,  and it was this complex that was first reported to bundle actin filaments  in vitro. Phosphorylation of annexin 2 by v-Src was shown to  completely inhibit this activity  (21), suggesting that v-Src or  c-Src could play a role in regulating annexin-actin interactions in  vivo. Such a role for annexin 2 would be consistent with some of the  downstream consequences of v-Src activation, which include remodeling of the  cytoskeleton, extensive cellular ruffling, stress-fiber breakdown, and  ultimately, focal adhesion turnover  (22,  23). c-Src and v-Src  phosphorylate a broad and largely overlapping range of substrates, many of  which are implicated in cell motility and cell transformation  (24-28)  and among which focal adhesion kinase  (FAK)2 is a prime  target. FAK is a key regulator of focal adhesion dynamics and becomes  phosphorylated on a number of tyrosines, some of which have been identified as  targets of Src kinases  (29-31).  Indeed, Src and FAK form a complex that regulates focal adhesion turnover by  phosphorylating members of the Rho family of small GTPases, the large scaffold  protein paxillin, myosin light chain kinase, and ERK  (32).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3867</offset><text>Recent publications have demonstrated the importance of the phosphorylation  of annexin 2 in the epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition induced by v-Src  overexpression or treatment with hepatocyte growth factor  (33) and in the  insulin-mediated transformation of baby hamster kidney cells (BHK-IR cells)  (34). In both studies,  expression of a pseudo-phosphorylated mutant of annexin 2 was sufficient to  partially phenocopy the transformed phenotype. In this study, we used small  interfering RNA (siRNA) to deplete fibroblasts of annexin 2 and then examined  the effects of activation of a temperature-sensitive mutant of v-Src on cell  morphology, F-actin, the localization of activated Src, and the  phosphorylation of FAK. Consistent with previous reports, we observed that  annexin 2 becomes phosphorylated when v-Src is active  (3,  33). We demonstrate that cells  lacking annexin 2 fail to undergo the phenotypic changes and  anchorage-independent growth that characterize transformation and show that  phosphorylation of FAK on tyrosine 576 is defective. We also show that the  targeting of activated Src to the plasma membrane and its subsequent  internalization and sorting onto Rab11-positive endosomes are compromised.  Thus, our data reveal a major role for phosphorylated annexin 2 as a  downstream effector of Src, inducing dynamic restructuring of the actin  cytoskeleton, and also show that it has an essential upstream activity,  regulating Src targeting and subsequent recycling.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>5368</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5392</offset><text>Cell Lines and Antibodies:Rat-1 fibroblasts containing the  L29A temperature-sensitive, constitutively active mutant of v-Src were a kind  gift from Margaret Frame. MIO cells are a spontaneously immortalized human  Muller (retinal glial) cell line described elsewhere  (12). The anti-annexin 2  monoclonal antibody HH7 was a kind gift from Volker Gerke, and the antibody to  total Src was a kind gift from Michael Way. Anti-FAK antibodies came from  Santa Cruz Biotechnology, and FAK-pY576, FAK-pY925, Src family-pY416, and  paxillin-pY118 came from BIOSOURCE. Alexa Fluor-conjugated phalloidins were  obtained from Molecular Probes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6026</offset><text>Indirect Immunofluorescence:Cells were fixed in 3.7%  paraformaldehyde in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 20 min, washed twice  with PBS, and then stained with primary antibodies in PBS containing 0.2%  Triton X-100 overnight at 4  C. Cells were washed three times for 10 min  with PBS and then incubated with secondary antibodies and/or Alexa  Fluor-conjugated phalloidin (to observe the F-actin cytoskeleton) for 45 min  at 37  C. They were then washed a further three times and mounted in  VECTASHIELD. Images were collected on a Leica SP2 AOBS confocal  microscope.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6600</offset><text>Annexin 2 Depletion with siRNA:Annexin 2-specific siRNA  oligonucleotides (target sequence AAGTGCCTATGGGTCAA) were obtained from  Qiagen. R1LA29 cells were plated on Matek dishes or in 24-well plates in  Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium + 10% fetal calf serum overnight to provide  a 40% confluent population. Complexes were made according to the  manufacturer's instructions in Opti-MEM. Cells were transfected for 2 days and  then treated with a second dose of siRNA complexes for a further 2 days. In  most experiments, an siRNA duplex designed against green fluorescent protein  (GFP) was used as a control. In the experiments in which the cells were  subsequently to be transiently transfected with GFP constructs, an siRNA  duplex designed against human annexin 11 (which had been shown not to work in  these cells) was used as a control. The efficiency of protein depletion was  assessed by Western blotting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7518</offset><text>Rescue of Knockdown Phenotype Using hdanx2-GFP:Cells were  depleted of annexin 2 for 3 days as described above and then were transiently  transfected with either a GFP empty vector (Clontech) or a vector encoding GFP  fused to the C terminus of annexin 2 (referred to as hdanx2-GFP) into which  three silent mutations had been introduced  (12). These variations from  the normal sequence render transcripts from the construct resistant to  hybridization with the siRNA complexes and are therefore not subject to  degradation. Cells were left for a further 2 days in the presence of siRNA to  allow endogenous annexin 2 to be robustly depleted in siRNA-transfected cells  and to give the introduced hdanx2-GFP construct time to be expressed. After  the first 24 h, some cells were placed at 35  C to activate v-Src. Cells  were then fixed and stained for F-actin with Cy5-phalloidin and Src-pY416 (to  allow identification of the knockdown phenotype) and were imaged by confocal  microscopy. Green cells expressing either hdanx2-GFP or GFP alone were counted  and scored as being either transformed or untransformed. At least 300 GFP- or  hdanx2-GFP-expressing cells were analyzed on three separate plates in three  independent experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8758</offset><text>Immunoprecipitation, SDS-PAGE, and Western Blotting:1  x 108 R1LA29 cells were washed twice with cold PBS, scraped  off the flask with a rubber policeman, and resuspended in lysis buffer (150  mm NaCl, 20 mm Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 1 mm EGTA,  2% Triton X-100, 1 mm Na3VO4). They were  passaged 10 times though a 22-gauge needle and then spun on a microcentrifuge  at 13,000 rpm for 10 min. The supernatant was carefully removed so as not to  disturb the pellet and was spun again for a further 10 min. 400 mul of  supernatant was then incubated for 90 min at 4  C with 8 mug of the  anti-annexin 2 monoclonal antibody or total mouse IgG control (Caltag  Laboratories) and 35 mul of 50% Protein G-Sepharose 4B (Sigma). The samples  were washed four times with 1.5 ml of lysis buffer and once with 1.5 ml of  Tris-buffered saline (150 mm NaCl, 20 mm Tris-HCl, pH  7.4). Following SDS-PAGE and Western blotting, tyrosine-phosphorylated annexin  2 was identified using the pTyr-100 monoclonal antibody (Cell Signaling).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9769</offset><text>Anchorage-independent Growth:Cells were initially depleted  of annexin 2 for 3 days with siRNA or treated with a GFP-specific control  siRNA. They were then grown in soft agarose (0.4% agarose matrix in Dulbecco's  modified Eagle's medium with 5% fetal bovine serum on a lower layer of 0.6%  agarose in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium with 5% fetal bovine serum) at  41 or 35  C for the final 48 h to activate v-Src and to allow colonies to  form. Colonies were observed by low power phase microscopy and were classified  according to how many cells were present in each clump of cells. The data were  calculated from the mean of three plates.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10416</offset><text>Statistical Methods:Student's t test was carried  out to test the significance of all quantified observations. Two-tailed tests  were carried out assuming that control and test samples were of equal  variance.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>10626</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10634</offset><text>Redistribution of Annexin 2, v-Src, and FAK-pY576 during  Transformation:To test the hypothesis that a functional  relationship may exist between annexin 2, Src, and FAK, we used the well  characterized Rat-1 embryonic fibroblast model of v-Src transformation that  expresses the thermoactivatable LA29 mutant of Src (R1LA29 cells). In  agreement with other studies, we found that when cells were cultured at 41   C (the nonpermissive temperature), the F-actin cytoskeleton appeared to  be predominantly organized into basal stress fibers, with the cells flattened  and apparently contact-inhibited  (27). Annexin 2 is distributed  throughout the cytoplasm in such cells but is excluded from the nucleus, and  there is little detectable staining of Src-pY416  (Fig. 1A).  Phosphorylation of Src at tyrosine 416 (Src-pY416) stabilizes the protein in  an open conformation (25) and  is indicative of its activity. Over a 48-h time course following a switch to  the permissive temperature (35  C), annexin 2 became enriched at the cell  cortex, and Src-pY416 was observed at the focal adhesions (not visible in  Fig. 1, which shows a confocal  section through the middle of the cell, but clear in  Fig. 3A) and then also  the plasma membrane. Transformation was also accompanied by dramatic  rearrangement of the F-actin cytoskeleton and a change in cell shape. Thus,  cells switched from a flattened, stress fiber-dominated phenotype to become  rounder, elongated, or fusiform with cortical F-actin. Western blot analysis  revealed rapid appearance of Src-pY416, FAK-pY925, and paxillin-pY118 at 1 h  (Fig. 1B).  Phosphorylation of FAK on tyrosine 576 (in the kinase domain activation loop)  appeared somewhat later. In some experiments, we observed an apparent biphasic  peak of phosphorylation of Src and FAK-pY925 (as shown in these blots), but  this was not seen consistently. We did not observe tyrosine phosphorylation of  annexin 2 in cells at 41  C, but after 4 h at 35  C, it became  detectable and was strongly phosphorylated by 18 h  (Fig. 1C). These  findings are consistent with published reports of annexin 2 tyrosine  phosphorylation by the temperature-sensitive NY68 Src mutant  (35,  36). Interestingly, the  relocalization of annexin 2 to the cortex is evident even after 1 h at the  permissive temperature (see example in Fig.  3), suggesting that annexin 2 translocates before it becomes  tyrosine-phosphorylated. By 48 h, many of the cells showed marked enrichment  of Src-pY416 and annexin 2 in the cortex, in ruffles, on large macropinosomes,  and on perinuclear vesicles (Fig.  1A, inset). When we examined R1LA29 cells  transiently transfected with a GFP fusion of the temperature-sensitive LA29  Src mutant, we observed migration of v-Src-GFP from what appeared to be focal  adhesions (short, linear, and basal structures at the periphery of the cell)  to large macropinosomes when they were grown at the permissive temperature  (supplemental Fig. 1 and movie). The protein appeared to spool off the focal  adhesion onto the nascent macropinosome. Similar results were observed for  c-Src-GFP (data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>13769</offset><text>Annexin 2 and Src-pY416 relocalize during v-Src transformation of R1LA29  cells. A, R1LA29 cells were grown at the nonpermissive  temperature (41  C) and then switched to the permissive temperature (35   C) for 8 and 48 h. Cells were stained for annexin 2 (anx 2),  Src-pY416, and F-actin. The inset on the 48-h merged image shows the  colocalization of annexin 2 and Src-pY416 at the plasma membrane  (arrowheads). Scale bars, 20 mum. B, cell  extracts were prepared from cells grown at 41 and 35  C for the times  indicated. Samples were immunoblotted for annexin 2, tubulin (as a loading  control), total Src, total FAK, and also for tyrosine-phosphorylated forms of  Src, FAK, and paxillin. Protein bands were visualized by enhanced  chemiluminescence. C, annexin 2 is phosphorylated on tyrosine when  v-Src is active. Annexin 2 was immunoprecipitated (IP-anx 2) from  extracts of cells grown at 41 or 35  C for 4 or 18 h. The samples were  resolved by SDS-PAGE, Western-blotted (w. blot), and probed with  antibodies to phosphotyrosine. No phosphorylated annexin 2 was  immunoprecipitated by control mouse IgG (IP-IgG), and it was  virtually undetectable in cells grown at 41  C. However, a phosphoannexin  2 band was clearly visible after 4 h at 35  C, which became prominent by  18 h (asterisk). All blots are representative of three independent  experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15136</offset><text>In agreement with other studies  (33,  34), we were able to partially  phenocopy cellular transformation by overexpression of an annexin  2Y23E-GFP (phosphomimetic) fusion protein. Cells overexpressing  this construct showed varying degrees of actin remodeling, including the  restructuring of stress fibers, cellular ruffling, and macropinosome formation  (data not shown). Taken together, these observations support the notion that  annexin 2, when phosphorylated by v-Src on tyrosine 23, is an important  effector of actin remodeling.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15674</offset><text>Annexin 2 Is Required for Plasma Membrane Targeting of  v-Src:To determine whether annexin 2 is required for the  relocalization of temperature-sensitive v-Src, we used siRNA to deplete R1LA29  cells of annexin 2 prior to switching the cells to the permissive temperature.  At the restrictive temperature, annexin 2-depleted cells were not  morphologically different from wild-type cells, and there was no obvious  difference in the staining intensity or localization of active Src, F-actin,  or FAK-pY576 (Figs. 2A  and 3). At the permissive  temperature, however, cells lacking annexin 2 failed to exhibit the  relocalization of active Src, FAK-pY576, paxillin-pY118, and actin to the  perinuclear endosomal compartment, membrane ruffles, or macropinosomes, and  the morphological changes associated with transformation did not occur. The  cells remained large and flat with abundant stress fibers. Cells depleted of  annexin 2 still contained active Src, as observed on Western blotting  (Fig. 2B), but this  was almost entirely localized at focal adhesions (see white  arrowheads at the 24-h time point in  Fig. 2A).  Fig. 2 (C and  D) shows histograms representing the proportion of Src  phosphorylation on tyrosine 416 observed at various time points and the  efficiency of annexin 2 knockdown achieved at each time point. There was no  statistically significant difference in the kinetics of v-Src phosphorylation  (believed to be an auto-catalytic event) between control and annexin  2-depleted cells, suggesting that v-Src activation alone is insufficient to  elicit the morphological changes associated with transformation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17308</offset><text>Phosphorylation of FAK on tyrosine 576 was visualized by immunostaining  both control and annexin 2-depleted cells  (Fig. 3). Levels of FAK-pY576  were almost undetectable by Western blot analysis following siRNA treatment  for annexin 2 (Fig.  2B), whereas total FAK in the cells remained constant  (data not shown). In annexin 2-depleted cells, FAK-pY576 remained tightly  associated with the focal adhesions (Fig.  3, pink arrowheads), whereas in annexin 2-positive cells,  FAK-pY576 levels increased, and the protein relocated, together with annexin  2, to the cortex and to perinuclear vesicles (white arrowheads). The  kinetics of phosphorylation of other potential targets of activated Src such  as paxillin-pY118 and FAK-pY925 (data not shown) were not affected by the  depletion of annexin 2 (Fig.  2B).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>18121</offset><text>Membrane targeting of activated Src requires annexin 2. A,  R1LA29 cells were depleted of annexin 2 by siRNA treatment for 4 days at 41   C. Cultures were then moved to 35  C for the times indicated prior to  fixation and immunostaining for annexin 2 (anx 2), Src-pY416, and  F-actin. The top panel shows confocal sections at the base of cells  grown at 41  C, with both annexin 2-positive and annexin 2-negative cells  in the field of view. Annexin 2 is present throughout the cytoplasm, the actin  cytoskeleton is dominated by stress fibers, and Src-pY416 is undetectable.  After 4 h at 35  C, annexin 2, actin, and Src-pY416 appear at the  actin-rich cortex and in a perinuclear vesicular domain (pink  arrowheads), whereas there is no appearance of Src-pY416 at these sites  and no change in cell shape in annexin 2-depleted cells. After 24 h, Src-pY416  is clearly enriched at the focal adhesions (white arrowheads) in  annexin 2-depleted cells, but there is no morphological transformation.  Insets show diagrammatic representations of the confocal plane.  Scale bars, 25 mum. B, whole cell extracts were prepared  from R1LA29 cells following a 4-day culture at 41  C in the presence of  control or annexin 2 siRNA and from cells that had been switched to the  permissive temperature for the times indicated and immunoblotted as described  in the legend to Fig.  1B. The right panel shows extracts from the  control siRNA-treated cells at the restrictive temperature and after 36 h at  the permissive temperature. There is an increase in phosphorylation of Src on  phospho-Tyr416 and of paxillin on phospho-Tyr118, but  phosphorylation on FAK at phospho-Tyr576 is impaired. C,  densitometric analysis of Src-pY416 Western blots in control and annexin  2-depleted cells shows that the band intensity, indicative of Src activation,  increases in a similar manner under both experimental conditions. KD,  knockdown. D, a densitometric analysis shows that annexin 2 levels  are maintained at least 50% below the control (Ctrl; when normalized  to tubulin) for the duration of the experiment.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20215</offset><text>We also investigated annexin 2 involvement in the activation of endogenous  c-Src by performing siRNA experiments to deplete annexin 2 in MIO cells, an  untransformed, spontaneously motile glial cell line described in previous  studies (12). In these cells,  Src-pY416 is normally enriched at dynamic ruffles and at the cell cortex,  whereas in cells depleted of annexin 2, Src-pY416 was mislocalized to the ends  of F-actin stress fibers (supplemental Fig. 2). We showed previously that the  abundant F-actin stress fibers in annexin 2-depleted MIO cells are tethered at  focal adhesions (12); thus,  annexin 2 depletion in both MIO and R1LA29 cells results in the accumulation  of active Src at focal adhesions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20929</offset><text>To confirm that the resistance of annexin 2-depleted cells to  transformation by Src was a direct result of the loss of annexin 2 and not due  to some other epiphenomenon, we performed a &quot;reversal of  phenotype&quot; experiment in which an siRNA-resistant &quot;hardened&quot;  annexin 2-GFP fusion protein (hdanx2-GFP) was expressed in knockdown R1LA29  cells (12). The proportion of  cells that appeared to be flat and untransformed (by examination of the actin  phenotype, cell shape, and localization of active Src to the plasma membrane)  was established at both the permissive and nonpermissive temperatures. As  expected, a higher proportion of cells remained morphologically untransformed  when annexin 2 was depleted. However, more of these cells subsequently adopted  a transformed phenotype when the hdanx2-GFP construct was expressed compared  with those transformed with GFP alone, indicating that ectopic overexpression  of annexin 2 can indeed compensate for loss of the endogenous protein  (supplemental Fig. 3).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21943</offset><text>Targeting of Annexin 2 and Src to Rab11-positive Vesicles:In  cells in which v-Src is fully active, we observed relocalization of annexin 2,  Src-pY416, FAK-pY576, FAK-pY925, paxillin-pY118, PAK1 (data not shown), and  F-actin not only to dynamic actin-rich ruffles at the cell cortex but also to  cytoplasmic and perinuclear vesicles (Fig.  4, A and D). A subset of the annexin 2-positive  vesicles, most notably those at the perinuclear compartment, also labeled  positively for the recycling endosomal marker Rab11  (Fig. 4B, pink  arrowheads). To confirm this result and to examine the role of annexin 2  in the formation of this endosomal compartment, cells were transiently  transfected with Rab11-GFP (Fig.  4C). At the nonpermissive temperature and despite forced  expression, Rab11-GFP was very faint in all cells, exhibiting some perinuclear  enrichment with vesicles throughout the cytoplasm. In contrast, following a  period of growth at the permissive temperature, Rab11-GFP-positive vesicles  formed a more prominent perinuclear aggregation, in addition to a marked  increase in Rab11-GFP at the plasma membrane. The Rab11-GFP-positive  perinuclear compartment also stained for annexin 2  (Fig. 4C), which,  taken with the data in Fig.  4A, shows that annexin 2, Src-pY416, and Rab11 all  accumulate in this compartment. In cells switched to the permissive  temperature and depleted of annexin 2 (Fig.  4C, white arrowhead), the localization of  Rab11-GFP resembled that observed in normal cells at the nonpermissive  temperature (blue arrowheads). These observations show that although  annexin 2 is not required for the targeting of Rab11 to the perinuclear  endosomal compartment, annexin 2 is absolutely required for the association of  activated v-Src with this compartment.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>23737</offset><text>Relocalization of FAK-pY576 in response to v-Src-mediated cell  transformation is dependent upon annexin 2. R1LA29 cells were partially  depleted of annexin 2 as described in the legend to  Fig. 5, fixed, and  immunostained for annexin 2 (anx 2), FAK-pY576, and F-actin in both  the untransformed and transformed states. Following the switch from  restrictive to permissive temperature for 1 h, annexin 2-depleted cells  (pink arrowheads) remained large and flat with numerous focal  adhesions enriched in FAK-pY576. In contrast, annexin 2-positive cells  acquired a transformed phenotype in which annexin 2 relocalized to the cell  cortex. By 8 h, there was a dramatic increase in the cellular content of  FAK-pY576 in annexin 2-positive cells, in which it relocalized to the annexin  2-rich cortex and to the perinuclear annexin 2-rich and actin-rich vesicles  (white arrowheads). Relocalization of FAK-pY576 did not occur in  annexin 2-depleted cells. Scale bars, 20 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24712</offset><text>Remodeling of Focal Adhesions and Cell  Transformation:Although the relative importance of phosphorylation  on the various tyrosines in FAK is not fully understood, the current consensus  is that phosphorylation of Tyr576 and Tyr577, which are  in the kinase activation loop, is indicative of enhanced kinase activity  (31). We therefore  hypothesized that if annexin 2 has an essential role in Src targeting and  activation, then phosphorylation of FAK, remodeling of focal adhesions, and  cell transformation would be defective in cells lacking annexin 2. To address  these questions, we performed a semiquantitative analysis in which R1LA29  cells were depleted of annexin 2 with siRNA, and the fluorescence intensity of  FAK-pY576 staining was determined at individual focal adhesions or invadopodia  (actin-rich structures analogous to focal adhesions that form in the  transformed cells) (Fig.  5A). Although there was no difference in the integrated  fluorescence signal from untransformed control and knockdown cells at 41   C, at the permissive temperature, there was ~50% less FAK-pY576  staining at the focal adhesions of annexin 2-depleted cells compared with the  invadopodia of the morphologically transformed annexin 2-positive cells  (Fig. 5B). The  quantitative reduction in immunostaining of FAK-pY576 in the annexin  2-depleted cells is consistent with the results in Figs.  2B and  3 and reinforces the idea that  annexin 2 is required for the tyrosine phosphorylation of FAK on tyrosine 576  by activated v-Src, a key step promoting the dynamic remodeling of both the  actin cytoskeleton and focal adhesions that are necessary for cell  transformation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26386</offset><text>Finally, to examine whether the changes in Src signaling and cell  morphology observed upon siRNA-mediated annexin 2 depletion have consequences  for anchorage-independent growth, we performed an assay in which proliferation  of both control and annexin 2-depleted R1LA29 cells was examined at the  nonpermissive and permissive temperatures in soft agar. At 41  C, as  expected, ~95% of both control and annexin 2-depleted cells remained as  single cells, indicating that the cells were unable to proliferate when Src  was inactive. However, at 35  C, when Src is active, only 25% of control  cells failed to divide, whereas nearly 60% of cells in the annexin 2-depleted  culture remained as single undivided cells  (Fig. 6). These findings  confirm the supposition implied by the morphological consequences of annexin 2  depletion, namely that annexin 2 is necessary for v-Src-mediated cell  transformation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>27295</offset><text>Annexin 2, actin, and phosphorylated components of the focal adhesion  colocalize on Rab11-positive perinuclear vesicles when v-Src is active.  A, R1LA29 cells were grown at 35  C for 8 h and stained for  annexin 2 (anx 2), Src-pY416, and F-actin. Annexin 2 and a small  amount of Src-pY416 are present at the actin-rich cortex of the cell, and  there is an accumulation of annexin 2, Src-pY416, and F-actin on vesicular  structures in the perinuclear region of the cell. B, cells were  prepared as in A and immunostained for annexin 2, Rab11, and F-actin.  The merged image shows intense colocalization of annexin 2 at the perinuclear  endosomal compartment (pink arrowheads). C, R1LA29 cells  were transfected with Rab11-GFP and immunostained for annexin 2 and F-actin.  At 41  C and in cells expressing annexin 2, Rab11-GFP staining was faint,  although mainly targeted to the perinuclear endosomal compartment (blue  arrowheads). In cells switched to the permissive temperature and  partially depleted of annexin 2, the localization and intensity of Rab11-GFP  appeared similar to those observed in control cells at 41  C (white  arrowhead). However, as in B, control cells exhibited strong  enrichment of annexin 2 and Rab11-GFP at the perinuclear endosomal compartment  (pink arrowhead). D, in cells prepared as in A,  annexin 2 colocalizes with FAK-pY925 and paxillin-pY118 at the cell cortex, on  ruffling membranes (yellow arrowheads), on vesicles in the cytoplasm  (white arrowheads), and in the perinuclear recycling compartment  (pink arrowheads). Scale bars, 10 and 15 mum, as  indicated.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>28897</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28908</offset><text>In this study, we have used a cell line expressing a temperature-sensitive  mutant of v-Src to investigate the role of annexin 2 in v-Src-mediated cell  transformation. Although in vitro experiments have shown that  tyrosine phosphorylation of annexin 2 by Src leads to reduced affinity for  phospholipid bilayers (37) and  impaired actin-bundling activity  (21), the effects of tyrosine  phosphorylation on annexin 2 in vivo are less clear. Here, our data  suggest that v-Src activation stimulates annexin 2-dependent remodeling of the  actin cytoskeleton. This is consistent with our previous studies in human  Muller cells in which we showed that annexin 2 is involved in the  remodeling of actin filaments by barbed end capping  (12) and with recent reports  that tyrosine phosphorylation of annexin 2 is sufficient to induce the changes  in actin dynamics that accompany transformation and epithelial-to-mesenchymal  transition (33,  34).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29852</offset><text>Interestingly, in the study of de Graauw et al.  (33), pseudo-phosphorylated  annexin 2 also induced hepatocyte growth factor-independent branching and  restructuring of Madin-Darby canine kidney cells grown as cysts in a  three-dimensional collagen matrix. When cells were depleted of annexin 2 in  this system, the cysts failed to form a proper lumen, underlining the  importance of annexin 2 in maintaining cellular junctions and polarity, a  process known to be dependent upon c-Src  (38-40).  In their study, annexin 2 was shown to exert its effects on actin dynamics by  regulating ROCK- and LIM kinase-dependent phosphorylation of cofilin on serine  3 (33), which is an  established step in v-Src transformation of fibroblasts  (41). A further possibility is  that phosphorylation of annexin 2 brings about actin remodeling as a direct  consequence of its association with actin, without the necessity of signaling  through ROCK. This suggestion is not ruled out by published observations  because the molecular link between annexin 2 and the ROCK/LIM kinase/cofilin  pathway is not fully understood. Indeed, it is possible that both direct and  indirect mechanisms could exist.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>31038</offset><text>Phosphorylation of FAK on tyrosine 576 is increased in v-Src-transformed  cells in an annexin 2-dependent manner. A, R1LA29 cells were  partially depleted of annexin 2 using siRNA, and v-Src transformation was  induced by growing the cells at the permissive temperature for 24 h. Cells  were then fixed and stained for annexin 2, F-actin, and FAK-pY576. FAK-pY576  fluorescence levels in focal adhesions were measured in annexin 2-positive and  annexin 2-depleted cells on the same plate at 41  C and also in the  invadopodia of annexin 2-positive transformed cells and focal adhesions of  untransformed annexin 2-depleted cells at 35  C. The inset shows  focal adhesions in untransformed (annexin 2-depleted) cells (blue  arrows) and invadopodia (pink arrowheads). Scale bar,  25 mum. B, at 41  C, there was no statistical difference  between the amount of FAK-pY576 in annexin 2-positive and annexin 2-depleted  cells, whereas at 35  C, there was more FAK-pY576 present in the  invadopodia of transformed cells than in the focal adhesions of annexin  2-depleted (anx 2) untransformed cells. Data represent the total  integrated signal intensity per focal adhesion/invadopodium and are the mean  of three independent experiments. **, p &lt; 1 x  10-22. arb. units, arbitrary units.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>32318</offset><text>Transformation by v-Src requires annexin 2. Following exposure to  either control or annexin 2 (anx 2) siRNA, R1LA29 cells were cultured  in soft agar at both restrictive and permissive temperatures. The  histogram shows the range of clump sizes according to the number of  constituent cells. *, p = 0.023 (5-7 cells), 0.032 (8-16  cells), and 0.017 (17-25 cells); **, p = 0.0025 (1 cell)  and 0.0003 (&gt;25 cells). Error bars represent the S.E. of three  different plates. RNAi, RNA interference.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32814</offset><text>Unlike other members of the Src family that are both myristoylated and  palmitoylated and therefore constitutively associated with membranes, c-Src  itself is only myristoylated. Its membrane binding is therefore partially  dependent upon a number of protein-protein interactions mediated by three  &quot;anchorage domains&quot;  (42). Using the LA31  thermoactivatable v-Src protein, it was shown that membrane recruitment of  v-Src is synchronous with its thermoactivation. Membrane association is weak,  dependent upon cholesterol, and represents incorporation into &quot;lipid  rafts&quot; (in this case enriched in GM1 ganglioside but lacking flotillin-2  or caveolin) as well as nonraft components on endosomes  (43). Differential  localization of v-Src was shown to have consequences for its downstream  signaling. Cholesterol depletion impaired Src recruitment to the plasma  membrane and its subsequent activation of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt  while preserving its association with internal endosomes and mitogen-activated  protein kinase (MAPK)-ERK activation. The kinetics of activation of these  pathways suggest that localization to and signaling from the endosomal  compartment precedes that at the plasma membrane.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34032</offset><text>The colocalization we observed between annexin 2 and active Src, FAK-Y576,  and paxillin-Y118 on internal membranes during transformation is consistent  with the idea that trafficking and targeting of v-Src to the plasma membrane  are coupled to the retrieval and recycling of v-Src and other focal adhesion  components via macropinosomes or endosomes. This is significant in light of  previous studies showing that the cellular localization and organization of  recycling endosomes are dependent upon annexin 2  (44). These observations show  that annexin 2 is required for the intracellular targeting of activated Src to  the appropriate vesicular compartments and plasma membrane. When the failure  of v-Src to accumulate on the perinuclear Rab11-positive endosomal recycling  compartment in annexin 2-depleted cells is also taken into account, these  results suggest that without annexin 2, there is neither endosomal traffic of  v-Src to nor macropinocytic/endocytic cycling from the  plasma membrane. This result thus identifies these perinuclear vesicular  structures as the previously reported endosomal recycling compartment through  which Src has been shown to traffic en route to the plasma membrane  (45). Trafficking through this  compartment was shown to be essential for full activation of v-Src and was  blocked in cells expressing a dominant-negative mutant of Rab11. Instead,  activated Src remains on the focal adhesions, but even at this site, it fails  to phosphorylate FAK on tyrosine 576, and so there is no turnover of the focal  adhesion, and cell transformation fails to occur.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35636</offset><text>Given that annexin 2 is essential for the formation of actin tails that  propel endosomes and macropinosomes from the plasma membrane to the interior  of the cell (16,  18,  46), we propose that annexin 2  forms part of the actin regulatory machinery that regulates the endosomal  trafficking and activation of Src. In a recent study, tyrosine phosphorylation  of annexin 2 was shown to promote its association with endosomal membranes  (47). Thus, v-Src activation  and its subsequent phosphorylation of annexin 2 could be the trigger to  promote association of both proteins with membranes and to initiate  actin-dependent dynamic cycling through the endosomal pathway.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36308</offset><text>In conclusion, our observations identify a functional link between v-Src  and annexin 2 in cell transformation, a connection that was first hinted at  more than 20 years ago when annexin 2 was discovered and cloned as a major  cellular substrate of v-Src  (3). Our data suggest a role  for annexin 2 not only in the trafficking of Src to the plasma membrane that  is essential for its activation but also in the stimulation of actin dynamics  and the remodeling of focal adhesions that are required for transformation.  Given the correlation between altered patterns of expression, phosphorylation,  and localization of Src and annexin 2 in many high-grade metastatic cancers  (6,  24-28,  48-52),  an improved understanding of the cross-talk between these ubiquitous proteins  is imperative.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>37101</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37124</offset><text>   </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37128</offset><text>  </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Glenney, J. R., Jr. ()    -82</infon><infon key="fpage">79</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2414132</infon><infon key="source">FEBS  Lett.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">192</infon><infon key="year">1985</infon><offset>37131</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Glenney, J. R., Jr., and Tack, B. F. ()      -7888</infon><infon key="fpage">7884</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2415974</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">82</infon><infon key="year">1985</infon><offset>37132</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Saris, C. J., Tack, B. F., Kristensen, T., Glenney, J. R., Jr., and  Hunter, T. ()    -212</infon><infon key="fpage">201</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3013423</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">46</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>37133</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gerke, V., and Moss, S. E. ()    -371</infon><infon key="fpage">331</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11917092</infon><infon key="source">Physiol.  Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">82</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37134</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gerke, V., Creutz, C. E., and Moss, S. E. ()     -461</infon><infon key="fpage">449</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15928709</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>37135</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hayes, M. J., and Moss, S. E. ()      -1170</infon><infon key="fpage">1166</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15336964</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">322</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37136</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Babiychuk, E. B., and Draeger, A. ()    -1124</infon><infon key="fpage">1113</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10973999</infon><infon key="source">J.  Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">150</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>37137</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Glenney, J. ()    -4262</infon><infon key="fpage">4258</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3012561</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.  U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">83</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>37138</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Martin, F., Derancourt, J., Capony, J. P., Watrin, A., and  Cavadore, J. C. ()     -859</infon><infon key="fpage">777</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2970844</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">251</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><offset>37139</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Filipenko, N. R., and Waisman, D. M. ()     -5316</infon><infon key="fpage">5310</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11067857</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>37140</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hayes, M. J., Rescher, U., Gerke, V., and Moss, S. E.  ()    -576</infon><infon key="fpage">571</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15260827</infon><infon key="source">Traffic</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37141</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hayes, M. J., Shao, D., Bailly, M., and Moss, S. E.  ()     -1826</infon><infon key="fpage">1816</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16601677</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">25</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37142</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Emans, N., Gorvel, J. P., Walter, C., Gerke, V., Kellner, R.,  Griffiths, G., and Gruenberg, J. ()    -1369</infon><infon key="fpage">1357</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8449982</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">120</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>37143</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Trischler, M., Stoorvogel, W., and Ullrich, O. ()     -4783</infon><infon key="fpage">4773</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10574724</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">112</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>37144</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lorusso, A., Covino, C., Priori, G., Bachi, A., Meldolesi, J., and  Chieregatti, E. ()     -5456</infon><infon key="fpage">5443</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">29</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37145</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Merrifield, C. J., Rescher, U., Almers, W., Proust, J., Gerke, V.,  Sechi, A. S., and Moss, S. E. ()    -1141</infon><infon key="fpage">1136</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11509239</infon><infon key="source">Curr.  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>37146</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hayes, M. J., Merrifield, C. J., Shao, D., Ayala-Sanmartin, J.,  Schorey, C. D., Levine, T. P., Proust, J., Curran, J., Bailly, M., and Moss,  S. E. ()     -14164</infon><infon key="fpage">14157</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14734570</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37147</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hayes, M. J., Shao, D. M., Grieve, A., Levine, T., Bailly, M.,  Moss, S. E. () , in press</infon><infon key="source">Biochim. Biophys.  Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37148</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Araki, N., Egami, Y., Watanabe, Y., and Hatae, T.  ()     -1507</infon><infon key="fpage">1496</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17368443</infon><infon key="source">Exp. Cell Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">313</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37149</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Scott, C. C., Dobson, W., Botelho, R. J., Coady-Osberg, N.,  Chavrier, P., Knecht, D. A., Heath, C., Stahl, P., and Grinstein, S.  ()     -149</infon><infon key="fpage">139</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15809313</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">169</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>37150</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hubaishy, I., Jones, P. G., Bjorge, J., Bellagamba, C.,  Fitzpatrick, S., Fujita, D. J., and Waisman, D. ()     -14534</infon><infon key="fpage">14527</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7578058</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">34</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>37151</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Boschek, C. B., Jockusc, B. M., Friis, R. R., Back, R., Grundman,  E., and Bauer, H. ()    -184</infon><infon key="fpage">175</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6263486</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">1981</infon><offset>37152</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Meijne, A. M. L., Ruuls-Van Stalle, L., Feltkamp, C. A., McCarthy,  J. B., and Roos, E. ()     -485</infon><infon key="fpage">477</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9260918</infon><infon key="source">Exp. Cell Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">234</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>37153</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Frame, M. C., and Brunton, V. G. ()     -43</infon><infon key="fpage">36</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11790552</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37154</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Frame, M. C. ()    -130</infon><infon key="fpage">114</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12020799</infon><infon key="source">Biochim. Biophys.  Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1602</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37155</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Carragher, N. O., and Frame, M. C. ()      -1543</infon><infon key="fpage">1539</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12379276</infon><infon key="source">Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">34</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37156</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Frame, M. C., Fincham, V. J., Carragher, N. O., and Wyke, J. A.  ()    -245</infon><infon key="fpage">233</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11994743</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37157</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Timpson, P., Jones, G. E., Frame, M. C., and Brunton, V. G.  ()     -1846</infon><infon key="fpage">1836</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11728306</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>37158</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Calalb, M. B., Polte, T. R., and Hanks, S. K. ()     -963</infon><infon key="fpage">954</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7529876</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>37159</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Calalb, M. B., Zhang, X., Polte, T. R., and Hanks, S. K.  ()     -668</infon><infon key="fpage">662</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8941336</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">228</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>37160</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mitra, S. K., and Schlaepfer, D. D. ()     -523</infon><infon key="fpage">516</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16919435</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37161</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Webb, D. J., Donais, K., Whitmore, L. A., Thomas, S. M., Turner, C.  E., Parsons, J. T., and Horwitz, A. F. ()    -161</infon><infon key="fpage">154</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14743221</infon><infon key="source">Nat.  Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37162</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">de Graauw, M., Tijdens, I., Smeets, M. B., Hensbergen, P. J.,  Deelder, A. M., and van de Water, B. ()    -1040</infon><infon key="fpage">1029</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18070928</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell.  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">28</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37163</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rescher, U., Ludwig, C., Konietzko, V., Kharitonenkov, A., and  Gerke, V. ()     -2185</infon><infon key="fpage">2177</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18565825</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">121</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37164</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Garber, E. A., Krueger, J. G., Hanafusa, H., and Goldberg, A. R.  ()    -86</infon><infon key="fpage">73</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6189290</infon><infon key="source">Virology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">126</infon><infon key="year">1983</infon><offset>37165</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yamaoka, K., Imajoh-Ohmi, S., Fukuda, H., Akita, Y., Kurosawa, K.,  Yamamoto, Y., and Sanai, Y. ()    -1246</infon><infon key="fpage">1240</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16716253</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. Biophys.  Res. Commun.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">345</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37166</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Powell, M. A., and Glenney, J. R. ()     -328</infon><infon key="fpage">321</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2962567</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">247</infon><infon key="year">1987</infon><offset>37167</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yamada, A., Irie, K., Hirota, T., Ooshio, T., Fukuhara, A., and  Takai, Y. ()     -6027</infon><infon key="fpage">6016</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15574423</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">280</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>37168</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yamada, A., Fujita, N., Sato, T., Okamoto, R., Ooshio, T., Hirota,  T., Morimoto, K., Irie, K., and Takai, Y. ()     -5102</infon><infon key="fpage">5085</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16607281</infon><infon key="source">Oncogene</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">25</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>37169</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Martin-Belmonte, F., Gassama, A., Datta, A., Yu, W., Rescher, U.,  Gerke, V., and Mostov, K. ()     -397</infon><infon key="fpage">383</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17254974</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">128</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37170</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pawlak, G., and Helfman, D. M. ()    -26933</infon><infon key="fpage">26927</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12011049</infon><infon key="source">J.  Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>37171</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kaplan, K. B., Varmus, H. E., and Bishop, J. M. ()     -1009</infon><infon key="fpage">1000</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1689455</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>37172</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">de Diesbach, P., Medts, T., Carpentier, S., D'Auria, L., van der  Smissen, P., Platek, A., Mettlen, M., Caplanusi, A., van den Hove, M. F.,  Tyteca, D., and Courtoy, P. J. ()    -1479</infon><infon key="fpage">1465</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18316074</infon><infon key="source">Exp. Cell  Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">314</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37173</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zobiack, N., Rescher, U., Ludwig, C., Zeuschner, D., and Gerke, V.  ()     -4908</infon><infon key="fpage">4896</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">13679511</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Biol. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>37174</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sandilands, E., Cans, C., Fincham, V. J., Brunton, V. G., Mellor,  H., Prendergast, G. C., Norman, J. C., Superti-Furga, G., and Frame, M. C.  ()    -869</infon><infon key="fpage">855</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15572128</infon><infon key="source">Dev. Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>37175</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Merrifield, C. J., Moss, S. E., Ballestrem, C., Imhof, B. A.,  Giese, G., Wunderlich, I., and Almers, W. ()    -74</infon><infon key="fpage">72</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10559868</infon><infon key="source">Nat.  Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>37176</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Morel, E., and Gruenberg, J. ()    -1611</infon><infon key="fpage">1604</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18990701</infon><infon key="source">J.  Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><offset>37177</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mohammad, H. S., Kurokohchi, K., Yoneyama, H., Tokuda, M.,  Morishita, A., Jian, G., Shi, L., Murota, M., Tani, J., Kato, K., Miyoshi, H.,  Deguchi, A., Himoto, T., Usuki, H., Wakabayashi, H., Izuishi, K., Suzuki, Y.,  Iwama, H., Deguchi, K., Uchida, N., Sabet, E. A., Arafa, U. A., Hassan, A. T.,  El-Sayed, A. A., and Masaki, T. ()    -1163</infon><infon key="fpage">1157</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19020748</infon><infon key="source">Int. J.  Oncol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">33</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37178</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yao, H., Zhang, Z., Xiao, Z., Chen, Y., Li, C., Zhang, P., Li, M.,  Liu, Y., Guan, Y., Yu, Y., and Chen, Z. () , in press</infon><infon key="source">Lung  Cancer</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37179</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Mussunoor, S., and Murray, G. I. ()    -140</infon><infon key="fpage">131</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18698663</infon><infon key="source">J.  Pathol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">216</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37180</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fizazi, K. ()     -1773</infon><infon key="fpage">1765</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17426060</infon><infon key="source">Ann. Oncol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>37181</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hilbig, A. ()    -185</infon><infon key="fpage">179</infon><infon key="source">Recent Res. Cancer  Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">177</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>37182</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>37183</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: FAK, focal adhesion kinase; ERK, extracellular  signal-regulated kinase; siRNA, small interfering RNA; GFP, green fluorescent  protein; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline.</text></passage></document></collection>
