<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19254952</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M808176200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2673264</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19254952</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">11953</infon><infon key="fpage">11953</infon><infon key="issue">18</infon><infon key="lpage">11962</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kim;given-names:Jihee</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ahn;given-names:Seungkirl</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Rajagopal;given-names:Keshava</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Lefkowitz;given-names:Robert J.</infon><infon key="p">This work was supported, in whole or in part, by  Grants  and  (to R. J. L.).</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Independent beta-Arrestin2 and Gq/Protein Kinase Czeta  Pathways for ERK Stimulated by Angiotensin Type 1A Receptors in Vascular  Smooth Muscle Cells Converge on Transactivation of the Epidermal Growth Factor  Receptor*</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>220</offset><text>Recent studies in receptor-transfected cell lines have demonstrated that  extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) activation by angiotensin type 1A  receptor and other G protein-coupled receptors can be mediated by both G  protein-dependent and beta-arrestin-dependent mechanisms. However, few  studies have explored these mechanisms in primary cultured cells expressing  endogenous levels of receptors. Accordingly, here we utilized the  beta-arrestin biased agonist for the angiotensin type 1A receptor,  SII-angiotensin (SII), and RNA interference techniques to investigate  angiotensin II (ANG)-activated beta-arrestin-mediated mitogenic signaling  pathways in rat vascular smooth muscle cells. Both ANG and SII induced DNA  synthesis via the ERK activation cascade. Even though SII cannot induce  calcium influx (G protein activation) after receptor stimulation, it does  cause ERK activation, although less robustly than ANG. Activation by both  ligands is diminished by depletion of beta-arrestin2 by small interfering  RNA, although the effect is more complete with SII. ERK activation at early  time points but not later time points is strongly inhibited by those protein  kinase C inhibitors that can block protein kinase Czeta. Moreover, ANG- and  SII-mediated ERK activation require transactivation of the epidermal growth  factor receptor via metalloprotease 2/9 and Src kinase. beta-Arrestin2  facilitates ANG and SII stimulation of Src-mediated phosphorylation of Tyr-845  on the EGFR, a known site for Src phosphorylation. These studies delineate a  convergent mechanism by which G protein-dependent and  beta-arrestin-dependent pathways can independently mediate ERK-dependent  transactivation of the EGFR in vascular smooth muscle cells thus controlling  cellular proliferative responses.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2031</offset><text>G protein-coupled receptors, also known as seven transmembrane  (7TM)2 receptors,  control virtually all known physiological processes in mammals  (1). The various functions of  these receptors are mediated and modulated by three families of proteins,  which share the property that they interact virtually universally with the  receptors in a strictly stimulus-dependent way  (1). These three families of  proteins are the heterotrimeric G proteins, the G protein-coupled receptor  kinases (GRKs), and the beta-arrestins. Activation of the receptors  stimulates classical G protein-dependent signaling, often involving regulation  of levels of second messengers such as cAMP and diacyglycerol. However, as has  been known for many years, interaction of activated receptors with GRKs  leading to their phosphorylation, and subsequent interaction with  beta-arrestins leads to desensitization of G protein signaling.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2947</offset><text>In recent years, however, it has become increasingly clear that the  beta-arrestin-GRK system is in fact bifunctional  (2). Thus, even as it  desensitizes G protein signaling by the receptors, it also serves as a signal  transduction system in its own right, activating a growing list of signaling  pathways. These positive signaling functions are often mediated by the ability  of beta-arrestin to serve as an adaptor or scaffold molecule, bringing  elements of diverse signaling pathways into proximity with one another and the  receptors and thereby facilitating their activation. This new paradigm for  understanding the previously unrecognized signaling properties of the  beta-arrestin-GRK system has been explored in a wide variety of transfected  cultured cell systems.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3725</offset><text>However, to date, relatively little investigation of these novel signaling  pathways has been carried out in primary cell culture systems expressing  endogenous levels of 7TM receptors. In seeking such a system in which to  characterize and compare beta-arrestin and G protein-mediated signaling  pathways from a typical 7TM receptor, our attention was drawn to cultured rat  vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs). Several features of rat VSMCs suggest  this to be a relevant system for these purposes. Rat VSMCs express a variety  of physiologically important 7TM receptors including the angiotensin II type  1A receptor (AT1R) (3). This  receptor has been the focus of extensive study in transfected cell systems  with respect to its beta-arrestin-mediated signaling to a variety of  pathways, most particularly extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK).  Moreover, the AT1R mediates the physiologically important effects of  angiotensin II (ANG) on vascular tone as well as on proliferation and  chemotaxis (4,  5). Pathophysiologically, ANG  stimulation of this receptor has been implicated in VSMC proliferation and  chemotaxis, which are thought to play an important role in such important  disease processes as atherosclerosis and restenosis after angioplasty  (6,  7). Moreover, a ligand has been  characterized  [Sar1,Ile4,Ile8](SII)-angiotensin (SII), a  triply mutated angiotensin octapeptide that, in transfected cell systems, acts  as a specific agonist for beta-arrestin-mediated signaling, although not  activating G protein-mediated signaling  (8).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5291</offset><text>Accordingly, in the studies described here, we set out to investigate the  characteristics of activation of ERK in rat VSMCs that might be mediated  through G protein as well as beta-arrestin signaling. The results not only  demonstrate the importance of beta-arrestin-mediated signaling in  ERK-mediated proliferative responses of these cells, but also shed new light  on the molecular mechanisms and interrelationships between the beta-arrestin  and classical G protein-mediated activation of these pathways.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>5802</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5826</offset><text>Materials:[Sar1,Ile4,Ile8]-Angiotensin  II was synthesized in the Cleveland Clinic core synthesis facility. Valsartan  was obtained from Novartis and PD 123319 from RBI was used. Angiotensin II was  purchased from Sigma. Human recombinant epidermal growth factor (EGF) was  purchased from Roche Molecular Biochemicals. The EGFR-specific inhibitor  tyrphostin AG1478, the Src-specific inhibitor  4-amino-5-(4-chlorophenyl)-7-(t-butyl)pyrazolo[3,4-D]pyrimidine  (PP2), the MEK inhibitor PD98059, and N-phenylsulfonyl hydroxamic  acid derivative  (2R-[(4-biphenylsulfonyl)amino]-N-hydroxy-3-phenylpropinamide)  (BiPS), and PKC inhibitors (GFX, Go6976, and Go6983) were from  Calbiochem. Polyclonal anti-EGFR and anti-phospho-EGFR (Tyr845)  antibodies used for immunoprecipitation and immunoblotting were from Cell  Signaling and Upstate Biotechnology, Inc. Polyclonal rabbit beta-arrestin  1(A1CT) and polyclonal rabbit anti-beta-arrestin 2 (A2CT) antibodies were  used for detecting beta-arrestin1 and -2, respectively  (9). Polyclonal PKCzeta  antibody was from Santa Cruz. Polyclonal anti-phospho-ERK antibody (Cell  Signaling) and polyclonal anti-ERK2 antibody (Millipore) were used for ERK  activation assay. [3H]Thymidine was purchased from Amersham  Biosciences. Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagents were from  Invitrogen.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7157</offset><text>Synthesis of Small Interfering RNAs (siRNAs):Chemically  synthesized, double-stranded siRNAs, with 19-nucleotide duplex RNA and  2-nucleotide 3'-dTdT overhangs were purchased from Dharmacon in  deprotected and desalted forms. The siRNA sequence targeting beta-arrestin1  is 5'-AGCCUUCUGUGCUGAGAAC-3', corresponding to position  431-459 relative to the start codon. The siRNA sequences targeting  beta-arrestin2 are 5'-GGACCGCAAAGUGUUUGUG-3' and  5'-CCAACCTCATTGAATTCGA-3', corresponding to positions  150-168 and 1115-1133 relative to the start codon  (10). siGENOME ON-TARGET plus  set of four rat PRKCZ was purchased from Dharmacon. A non-silencing RNA duplex  (5'-AAUUCUCCGAACGUGUCACGU-3'), as the manufacturer indicated, was  used as a control.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7906</offset><text>Cell Culture and RNA Transfection:VSMCs were prepared from  aorta of male Sprague-Dawley rats by enzymatic digestion  (11) and maintained in Medium  199 (M199) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 1%  penicillin-streptomycin. Eighty to 90% confluent, slow growing early passage  (&lt;5) cells in 100-mm dishes were transfected with 20 mug of siRNA using  60 mul of Lipofectamine 2000 transfection reagent  (11). Forty-eight hours after  transfection, cells were starved with media with 0.1% bovine serum albumin for  at least 48 h prior to stimulation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8464</offset><text>Calcium Fluorimetry:Cells were loaded with the dye Fura-2 as  per the manufacturer's instructions (Invitrogen), and treated with either ANG  (100 nm) or SII (10 mum), in the presence of either 1  mum valsartan (Angiotensin receptor type 1 blocker, AT1RB) or 300  nm PD123319 (Angiotensin receptor type 2 blocker, AT2RB). The  instantaneous 340/380-nm excitation ratio for Fura-2 was calculated and  plotted as a function of time.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8894</offset><text>DNA Synthesis:DNA synthesis was determined as incorporation  of [3H]thymidine into trichloroacetic acid-insoluble material as  described (11). Cells were  seeded 10,000 cells/well in 12-well plates and grown to subconfluence (1 day).  Cells were rendered quiescent by 48 h in serum-free M199 supplemented with  0.1% bovine serum albumin and stimulated by addition of fresh medium  containing the agonists and/or inhibitors. [3H]Thymidine (0.5  muCi/ml) was added to the medium at the time of stimulation. Cells were  washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline and three times with 0.5%  trichloroacetic acid, and then cells were lysed with 1 n NaOH.  Extent of cell growth was determined by counting incorporation of  [3H]thymidine into nascent DNA strands.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9653</offset><text>Immunoprecipitation and Western Blotting:Immunoprecipitation  was performed by a modification of the methods of Daub et al.  (12). Cells were serum-starved  in M199 with 0.1% bovine serum albumin for 48 h after siRNA transfection.  Stimulation of serum-starved rat VSMC in 100-mm dishes with appropriate  agonists was done at 37  C for 2 min. After stimulation, monolayers were  washed once with ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline and lysed in buffer  containing 50 mm HEPES (pH 7.5), 150 mm NaCl, 1% Triton  X-100, 1 mm EDTA, 10% glycerol, 10 mm sodium  pyrophosphate, 2 mm sodium orthovanadate, 10 mm sodium  fluoride, 1 mm phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, and 10 mug/ml  aprotinin. The EGFR was immunoprecipitated using 4 mug of anti-EGFR antibody  plus 25 mul of 50% slurry of Protein G Plus/Protein A-agarose and agitated  overnight at 4  C. Western blotting was performed to detect  phosphorylation residues at Tyr-845 of the EGFR with antibody (Cell  Signaling).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10621</offset><text>For Western blotting for ERK activation, VSMCs on 6-well plates were  starved for at least 48 h in serum-free medium prior to stimulation. After  stimulation, cells were solubilized by directly adding the 2x SDS sample  buffer followed by sonication. Aliquoted cells after transfection were  solubilized in a lysis buffer, as described previously  (13), to measure the protein  concentration. Equal amounts of cellular extracts were separated on  4-20% Tris glycine polyacrylamide gels and transferred to nitrocellulose  membranes for immunoblotting. Phosphorylated ERK1/2, total ERK1/2, and  beta-arrestins were detected by immunoblotting with rabbit polyclonal  anti-phospho-ERK (Cell Signaling, 1:2,000), anti-ERK (Upstate Technology Inc,  1:10,000), and anti-beta-arrestin (A1CT, 1:3,000 and A2CT, 1:3000)  antibodies, respectively (9).  Chemiluminescent detection was performed using the SuperSignal West Pico  reagent (Pierce), and all the immunoblots were visualized and quantified by  Bio Imaging system (Syngene). The levels of ERK phosphorylation was normalized  to a loading control (total ERK). Statistical analysis was done using a  one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) (PRISM software) to correct for multiple  comparisons (Bonferroni's multiple comparison test) with post test.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>11914</offset><text>Mobilization of calcium, DNA synthesis, and phosphorylation of ERK  stimulated by ANG and SII in VSMCs. A, VSMCs were loaded with the  calcium-binding dye Fura-2, and stimulated either with ANG (100 nm)  or SII (10 mum) in the presence or absence of pretreatment with  the AT1R antagonist (AT1RB) valsartan (50 mum) or AT2R  antagonist (AT2RB) PD123319 (30 mum). Calcium  fluorimetric traces are shown with the 340/380 nm excitation ratio (y  axis) plotted as a function of time (x axis). Results displayed are  mean +- S.E. of three independent experiments. B, VSMCs were  serum starved for 24 h to arrest cycling and pretreated with dimethyl  sulfoxide (DMSO) or MEK inhibitor PD98056 (20 mum). ANG  (100 nm), SII (10 mum), or EGF (10 ng/ml) along with  3H-labeled thymidine were then added to the media, and 24 h later  cells were harvested as described under &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot;  NS indicates no stimulation. Results depicted represent the mean  +- S.E. of count per minute (cpm) values from four independent  experiments. Statistical analysis was done using a one-way ANOVA (PRISM  software) to correct for multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's multiple  comparison test) with post test. The PD98056-pretreated condition shows  significant reduction compare with the dimethyl sulfoxide-pretreated condition  for each stimulant (*, p &lt; 0.05). C, VSMCs with  endogenous AT1R were treated with 100 nm ANG or 10 mum  SII for the indicated times. Equal amounts of cell lysate were separated by  SDS-PAGE and analyzed for phosphorylated ERK (p-ERK) and total ERK  (ERK) by Western blotting. IB, immunoblot. D,  signals were quantified by densitometry and p-ERK was normalized to a loading  control (ERK). p-ERK activation was expressed as percentage of the maximal  phosphorylated ERK obtained by ANG stimulation at 5 min. Each data point  represents the mean +- S.E. from eight independent experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>13821</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13829</offset><text>Intracellular Calcium Mobilization and Its Effect on DNA Synthesis and  ERK Activation Stimulated with ANG or SII:ANG regulates vascular  tone and induces mitogenic responses. To understand the functions of  beta-arrestins in endogenously expressed AT1R-mediated mitogenic pathways,  we utilized a triply mutated angiotensin octapeptide (SII) that acts as a  specific agonist for beta-arrestin-mediated signaling while not activating G  protein-mediated signaling (8).  To validate the utility of SII as an activator of only  beta-arrestin-dependent signaling pathways in primary cultured rat VSMCs (as  is the case with receptor-transfected HEK 293 cells  (8)), calcium influx in  response to ANG and SII was measured. As shown in  Fig. 1A, VSMCs treated  with ANG display robust calcium mobilization, whereas cells treated with SII  shows no calcium mobilization, implying that SII cannot activate G-protein  pathways in these cells. The ANG response is completely blocked in the  presence of an angiotensin receptor type 1 blocker (AT1RB, Valsartan) but not  by an angiotensin receptor type 2 blocker (AT2RB, PD 123319)  (Fig. 1A).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14964</offset><text>It is well known that ERK activation plays an important role in cell  proliferation. To investigate the contribution of beta-arrestin-mediated ERK  activation to VSMC proliferation, we studied ANG- and SII-mediated DNA  synthesis in VSMCs as an indicator of cell proliferation. VSMCs were  pretreated or not with a pharmacological inhibitor (PD98059) of  mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase (MEK) followed by stimulation with 100  nm ANG, 10 mum SII, or 10 ng/ml EGF. Although SII  cannot activate classical G-protein-dependent Ca2+ fluxes  (Fig. 1A), it  significantly increased DNA synthesis (thymidine incorporation) to a level  similar to that provoked by ANG or EGF stimulation in VSMCs  (Fig. 1B).  Pretreatment with PD98059 ablated virtually all activation over basal levels  (n = 5; p &lt; 0.05), indicating that ERK activation  regulates DNA synthesis in VSMCs (Fig.  1B). These data indicate that a G-protein-independent ERK  activation mechanism that can be stimulated by SII can mediate AT1R-regulated  DNA synthesis in rat VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16008</offset><text>In transfected HEK 293 cells it has been demonstrated that SII elicits AT1R  signaling to ERK activation without activating the Gq protein  (8).  Fig. 1 demonstrates the  inability of SII to activate calcium fluxes, a classic Gq response  in VSMCs, whereas retaining the ability to induce DNA synthesis, which  requires ERK activation. Next, we tested SII-mediated ERK activation mediated  by the AT1R-expressed endogenously in VSMCs.  Fig. 1, C and  D, show that ERK activation by SII in VSMCs reaches  maximal levels by 5 min, and amounted to a 2-fold increase over basal, which  was about 50% of ANG-mediated ERK activation. Both ANG- and SII-stimulated ERK  activation is completely sensitive to AT1RB pretreatment in VSMCs (data not  shown). These results demonstrate that a G protein-independent pathway  contributes to ERK activation in primary VSMCs through endogenously expressed  AT1R.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>16904</offset><text>Effects of beta-arrestin RNAi on ANG-mediated phosphorylation of  ERK. VSMCs were transfected with the control (CTL),  beta-arrestin1 and -2 siRNAs using Lipofectamine 2000. A,  representative Western blot for expression of beta-arrestins after siRNA  transfection was shown. beta-Arrestin1 and -2 were detected by  immunoblotting (IB) with rabbit polyclonal anti-beta-arrestin1  (A1CT) and anti-beta-arrestin2 (A2CT) antibodies,  respectively. Immunoblotting with actin was shown as a loading control.  B-D, serum-starved cells were treated with 100 nm  ANG for the indicated times and cell lysates were analyzed for phosphorylated  ERK (p-ERK) and total ERK (ERK). B, representative  Western blot for ANG induced p-ERK and ERK in siRNA-transfected VSMCs was  shown. C and D, signals were quantified by densitometry and  p-ERK was normalized to a loading control (ERK). The signal at each point is  expressed as percentage of the maximal p-ERK signal (5 min) in CTL  siRNA-transfected cells. The graphs represent mean +- S.E. from  six independent experiments. Statistical analysis was done using a one-way  ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's  multiple comparison test) with post test. The siRNA transfected condition  shows significant differences compared with control siRNA-transfected cells at  each time point (*, p &lt; 0.05; **, p &lt; 0.01).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18287</offset><text>Effect of beta-Arrestin Depletion on ANG- and SII-mediated  ERK Activation:As shown in Figs.  1, G protein-independent signaling is involved in AT1R-mediated  DNA synthesis via ERK activation in VSMCs. In HEK 293 cells, we have  previously demonstrated that beta-arrestins play critical roles in G  protein-independent ERK activation  (13). Therefore, we examined  the effects of RNA interference (RNAi)-mediated suppression of  beta-arrestin1 and -2 expression on the kinetics of ERK activation following  stimulation with ANG and SII in VSMCs. Transfection with siRNAs targeting  beta-arrestin1 or -2 effectively and specifically silence the expression of  each beta-arrestin (Fig.  2A). In beta-arrestin1 siRNA-transfected cells, ANG  stimulation evokes a kinetic pattern of ERK activation similar to control but  with significantly elevated levels of activation at the 2-min time point,  compared with control siRNA-transfected cells  (Fig. 2, B and  C). In contrast, depletion of beta-arrestin2 leads to  decreased ERK activation (by over 30%) at the later time points (5 to 20 min)  (Fig. 2, B and  D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19396</offset><text>SII-stimulated ERK activation is completely lost in beta-arrestin2  siRNA-transfected VSMCs (Fig. 3, A  and B), suggesting that SII-stimulated ERK activation is  entirely beta-arrestin2-mediated. To further validate the contribution of  beta-arrestin2 to VSMC proliferation, we measured ANG- and SII-induced  thymidine incorporation as an indicator of DNA synthesis and cell  proliferation in VSMCs after depletion of beta-arrestin1 or -2. ANG- and  SII-induced DNA synthesis was significantly inhibited only by deletion of  beta-arrestin2 (Fig.  3C). Taken together, these results indicate that  beta-arrestin2 has a major role in AT1R-mediated ERK signaling and cell  proliferation in VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20090</offset><text>Role of PKC in AT1R-mediated ERK Activation in VSMCs:Upon  agonist binding, AT1R activates Gq protein, which activates  phospholipase C. Active phospholipase C generates inositol triphosphate and  diacyglycerol, which increase intracellular calcium influx and PKC,  respectively (14). We have  previously found that in HEK 293 cells AT1R-mediated G protein-dependent ERK  activation requires PKC activity. This process is rapid (peak &lt; 2 min) and  quite transient (~2 min)  (13). Therefore, we assessed  the role of PKC in mediating ANG-stimulated ERK activation in VSMCs by using  PKC inhibitors. We tested several PKC inhibitors including GFX  (bisindolylmaleimide I), Ro-31-8425, Go6976, and Go6983, which  inhibit the activities of various combinations of conventional (alpha,  beta, or gamma), novel (delta, epsilon, or mu), and atypical (zeta,  iota) isoforms of PKC in a concentration-dependent way. There was no  significant inhibition of ERK activation by either 1 mum  Go6976, a selective inhibitor of PKC alpha, beta, and chi  (Fig. 4A), or by 1  mum Ro-31-8425 (data not shown), a selective inhibitor of PKC  alpha, beta, chi, and epsilon. ANG-mediated ERK activation was also not  inhibited by either 1 mum Go6983  (Fig. 4B) or 5  mum GFX (data not shown), which at the concentrations tested only  inhibit the activities of PKC isoforms alpha, beta, delta, and/or chi.  In contrast, pretreatment with PKC inhibitors (15 mum GFX and 10  mum Go6983) resulted in dramatic decreases (~75%) in ERK  activation at early time points (1 and 2 min) after ANG stimulation, but  little inhibition was observed at longer time points (10 and 20 min)  (Fig. 4). The general PKC  activator, phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate induced ERK activation and this was  abolished by all of the PKC inhibitors used in VSMCs (data not shown). The  kinetic pattern of ERK activation in the presence of the PKC inhibitors GFX  and Go6983 in VSMCs (Fig.  4) is similar to that observed previously for ANG-stimulated,  beta-arrestin2-dependent ERK activation in HEK 293 cells expressing AT1R  (13). Only early activity  (i.e. prior to 5-10 min of stimulation) was inhibited. Thus,  the temporal patterns of G protein-dependent (PKC dependent) and  beta-arrestin2-dependent ERK activation through endogenous AT1Rs in VSMCs  are distinct from each other. The majority of early activity (&lt;=2 min) is  elicited via the G protein-dependent pathway (PKC inhibitor sensitive),  whereas late activity (&gt;5 min) is predominantly mediated by the  beta-arrestin2-dependent pathway.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22642</offset><text>PKCzeta Mediates G-protein-dependent ERK Activation Upon  Stimulation with ANG:Three isoforms of PKC, alpha, delta, and  zeta, have been shown to be expressed in VSMCs  (15). Among them, PKCzeta  has been implicated in ANG-mediated mitogenic responses and cell growth in  VSMCs (16), although different  isoforms of PKC may play roles in ERK activation in different cell types  (17,  18). In  Fig. 4, we observed inhibition  of ERK activation at the early time points when two PKC inhibitors capable of  blocking PKC activity were used. Furthermore, blockade of PKCalpha and  delta appears not to inhibit this ERK activation. Thus, we next examined the  role of PKCzeta in ERK activation in VSMCs utilizing the RNAi technique.  Transfection with PKCzeta-specific siRNA reduces the expression of PKCzeta  by 70% in VSMCs (Fig. 5, A and  B). ANG-induced ERK activation at early time points  (&lt;5 min) was significantly decreased in cells transfected with PKCzeta  siRNA compared with that in control siRNA-transfected VSMCs  (Fig. 5, C and  D). To further validate the role of PKCzeta in  beta-arrestin-dependent (or G protein-dependent) pathways, we also  stimulated VSMCs transfected with PKCzeta siRNA with SII. As shown in  Fig. 5, E and  F, SII leads to activation of ERK at the same magnitude  in both control and PKCzeta siRNA-transfected cells. Taken together, these  data suggest that PKCzeta, at least partially, mediates ANG-induced early  ERK activation, whereas not affecting beta-arrestin-dependent ERK activation  in VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>24178</offset><text>Effects of beta-arrestin RNAi on SII-mediated phosphorylation of  ERK. A and B, VSMCs were transfected with control  (CTL) or beta-arrestin2 siRNAs using Lipofectamine 2000.  Serum-starved cells were treated with 10 mum SII for the  indicated times and cell lysates were analyzed for phosphorylated ERK  (p-ERK) and total ERK (ERK). A, representative  Western blot for SII-induced p-ERK and total ERK in siRNA-transfected VSMCs  was shown. B, signals were quantified by densitometry and p-ERK was  normalized to a loading control (ERK). Signal at each point is  expressed as percentage of ANG stimulated the maximal p-ERK signal at 5 min in  control (CTL) siRNA-transfected cells as depicted in  Fig. 2B. The  graph represents mean +- S.E. from six independent experiments.  Statistical analysis in each time point of kinetic graphs were determined by  using a two-way ANOVA (Bonferroni's post test) between beta-arrestin2 and  control (CTL) siRNA-transfected cells (*, p &lt; 0.05).  C, VSMCs were transfected with control, beta-arrestin1 or -2 siRNAs  using Lipofectamine 2000 and then serum starved for 24 h to arrest cycling.  ANG (100 nm) or SII (10 mum) along with  3H-labeled thymidine was then added to the media, and 24 h later  cells were harvested as described under &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot;  NS indicates no stimulation. Results depicted represent the mean  +- S.E. of fold-increase of basal counts per minute (cpm) values from  three independent experiments. Statistical analysis was done using a one-way  ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's post  test). ANG and SII significantly increase thymidine incorporation compared  with NS control (*, p &lt; 0.05). Depletion of beta-arrestin2 shows  significant reduction on both ANG- and SII-mediated thymidine incorporation  compared with its own agonist stimulation in the CTL siRNA-transfected  condition (**, p &lt; 0.05). IB, immunoblot.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>26108</offset><text>Effects of PKC inhibitors on ANG-stimulated phosphorylation of ERK.  Serum-starved VSMCs were pretreated with vehicle (dimethyl sulfoxide,  DMSO) or the indicated PKC inhibitors for 30 min, and then stimulated  with 100 nm ANG for the indicated times. Western blots for  phosphorylated ERK (p-ERK) and total ERK (ERK) were  performed. A, representative p-ERK Western blots and targeted PKC  subtypes for PKC inhibitors were presented. B and C, signals  were quantified by densitometry and p-ERK was normalized to a loading control  (ERK). The percentage of p-ERK was calculated for each time point and plotted  as percentage of the maximal p-ERK signal with dimethyl sulfoxide at 5 min.  Data represent the mean +- S.E. of four independent experiments.  Statistical analysis was done using a one-way ANOVA (PRISM software) to  correct for multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's post test). Pretreated  conditions with PKC inhibitors show the significant differences compared with  dimethyl sulfoxide-treated cells at the indicated time point (*, p  &lt; 0.05). IB, immunoblot.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27178</offset><text>ANG- and SII-mediated ERK Activation Is Dependent on EGFR Kinase and  Metalloprotease 2/9 in VSMCs:It is known that AT1R-mediated EGFR  transactivation plays an important role in proliferation of various cell types  including VSMCs (19). ANG  promotes activation of the EGFR pathway through release of the EGFR ligand  &quot;heparin-binding EGF&quot; in various cell types  (12,  19). However, it is not clear  whether EGFR transactivation is required for beta-arrestin-dependent ERK  activation in VSMCs. To answer this question, we examined ERK activation after  ANG and SII stimulation in the presence of various pharmacological inhibitors  of components thought to be involved in the EGFR transactivation pathway.  First we tested the requirement for EGFR kinase activity in ANG-induced ERK  activation. In the presence of AG1478, an EGFR-specific kinase inhibitor,  ANG-induced ERK activation is dramatically inhibited at all tested time points  (Fig. 6, A and  B). Next, we investigated the contribution of EGFR kinase  activity particularly for the beta-arrestin2-dependent pathway by testing  ANG-mediated ERK activation in the presence of AG1478 after depletion of  beta-arrestin2. In VSMCs transfected with beta-arrestin2 siRNA, ERK  activation was further reduced by AG1478 as shown in  Fig. 6, C and  D. ANG-stimulated ERK activation was inhibited by AG1478  in both control and beta-arrestin2 siRNA-transfected VSMCs (reduced to  ~40-50% of maximal ANG stimulation  (Fig. 6, B and  D). These data indicate that, without beta-arrestin2,  the remaining G protein-dependent component was also affected by the EGFR  kinase inhibitor. Thus, both G protein- and beta-arrestin2-dependent  components required EGFR transactivation for AT1R-mediated ERK activation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>28938</offset><text>Effects of PKCzeta RNAi on AT1R-mediated phosphorylation of ERK.  VSMCs were transfected with control (CTL) siRNA or siGENOME ON-TARGET  plus a set of four rat PKCzeta siRNAs (Dharmacon) using Lipofectamine 2000.  A, representative Western blot for expression of PKCzeta and actin  after siRNA transfection was shown. B, the expression levels of  PKCzeta after siRNA transfection were measured by Western blot and  normalized with its loading control (actin). Results are shown as % of  expression of PKCzeta in CTL siRNA cells. Data represent mean +- S.E.  from four independent experiments (*, p &lt; 0.05).  C-F, siRNA-transfected and serumstarved VSMCs were stimulated  by 100 nm ANG or 10 mum SII for the indicated times  and cell lysates were analyzed for phosphorylated ERK (p-ERK) and  total ERK (ERK). C and E, representative p-ERK and  ERK Western blots were presented for ANG (C) and SII (E)  stimulation. D and F, signals were quantified by  densitometry and p-ERK was normalized to a loading control (ERK). Data  represent mean +- S.E. from four independent experiments. Signal at each  point is expressed as percentage of the maximal p-ERK signal-stimulated ANG  for 5 min in CTL siRNA VSMCs. D, statistical analysis was done using  a one-way ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for multiple comparisons  (Bonferroni's post test) for ANG-induced ERK activation in PKCzeta  siRNA-transfected cells compared with CTL siRNA-transfected cells at each time  point (* p &lt; 0.05). F, SII-induced ERK activation was not  significantly different between PKCzeta siRNAs and CTL siRNA-transfected  VSMCs. IB, immunoblot.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30556</offset><text>In addition, SII-mediated ERK activation was virtually completely abolished  by AG1478 as shown in Fig. 6, E  and F. Because SII only activates  beta-arrestin-dependent pathways, this is clear evidence that EGFR kinase  activity is required for beta-arrestin2-dependent ERK activation in VSMCs.  Our results utilizing RNA interference and pharmacological inhibitors reveal  that beta-arrestin-dependent ERK activation requires EGFR kinase activity,  suggesting that EGFR transactivation is required for both G protein and  beta-arrestin2-dependent ERK activation by AT1R.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31128</offset><text>ANG is known to induce transactivation of the EGFR through activation of  metalloproteases that mediate cleavage of heparin-binding EGF from its  precursor. It has been reported that BiPS, previously known as matrix  metalloprotease-2/9 inhibitor, blocks ANG-induced EGFR transactivation  (20). We examined the effect  of BiPS on SII-mediated ERK activation in VSMCs. Pretreatment with BiPS  completely inhibits SII-induced ERK activation; whereas it inhibits  ANG-induced ERK activation by about 50%  (Fig. 6, G and  H). EGF-induced ERK activation is not affected by  pretreatment with BiPS (data not shown). Furthermore, we observed that both  ANG- and SII-induced DNA synthesis were significantly inhibited by  pretreatment with AG1478 (Fig.  6I). These data imply that ERK activation stimulated by  ANG in VSMCs may consist of several distinct components. Our data suggest that  the AT1R-mediated G-protein- and beta-arrestin-dependent signaling pathways  converge by promoting EGFR transactivation-dependent ERK activation, which  results in VSMC proliferation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32195</offset><text>Role of Src Kinase in beta-Arrestins-dependent ERK  Activation and EGFR Transactivation:In recent years, Src tyrosine  kinase has emerged as a key player in ANG-mediated cellular effects including  the Ras/ERK activation pathway  (21,  22). Dominant negative mutants  of c-Src lead to decreases in ANG-induced ERK activation in VSMCs  (23). Furthermore, it has been  reported that ERK activation by ANG is reduced in VSMCs derived from Src  knock-out mice (24).  Therefore, we examined the function of Src kinase on AT1R-mediated,  beta-arrestin-dependent ERK activation in VSMCs.  Fig. 7, A and  B, shows that in the presence of PP2, a Src kinase  inhibitor, AT1R-mediated ERK stimulation by either ANG or SII is significantly  reduced. These levels are similar to those obtained with the EGFR kinase  inhibitor, shown in Fig. 6, A and  E. These data demonstrate that both ANG- and  SII-stimulated ERK activation require Src kinase activity. We also found that  EGF-mediated ERK itself is sensitive to PP2 being reduced by 45% (data not  shown). This further suggests that AT1R-mediated Src kinase activation may  play multiple roles in regulating ERK activation both prior to and/or  subsequent to EGFR transactivation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>33417</offset><text>EGFR-dependent activation of ERK mediated by ANG and SII  stimulation. A-F, VSMCs were transfected with control  (CTL) or beta-arrestin2 siRNAs using Lipofectamine 2000.  Serum-starved VSMCs were pretreated with dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) or 250  nm AG1478 and then stimulated with 100 nm ANG or 10  mum SII for the indicated times. Equal amounts of cell lysate  were separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed for phosphorylated ERK  (p-ERK) and total ERK (ERK) by Western blotting. Signals  were quantified by densitometry and p-ERK was normalized to a loading control  (ERK). Signal at each point is expressed as percentage of the maximal p-ERK  signal (ANG for 5 min) in a dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO)-treated CTL  siRNA-transfected condition. A and C, representative Western  blots of p-ERK and ERK from ANG-stimulated CTL siRNA (A) and  beta-arrestin2 siRNAs-transfected VSMCs (C) are presented.  B and D, data represent mean +- S.E. from six  independent experiments in panels A and C. Statistical  analysis was done using a one-way ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for  multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's post test). *, p &lt; 0.05  compared with the dimethyl sulfoxide-treated condition at each time point.  E, representative SII-induced p-ERK and ERK Western blots from VSMCs  pretreated with DMSO or AG1478. F, data represent mean +- S.E.  from six independent experiments. Statistical analysis in each time point of  kinetic graphs were determined by using a two-way ANOVA (Bonferroni's post  test) between dimethyl sulfoxide and AG1478-treated cells (*, p &lt;  0.05). G and H, serum-starved VSMCs were pretreated with  dimethyl sulfoxide or 10mum BiPS and then stimulated with 100  nm ANG or 10 mum SII for 5 min. Equal amounts of cell  lysate were separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed for p-ERK and ERK by Western  blotting. Signals were quantified by densitometry and p-ERK was normalized to  a loading control (ERK). Signals at each condition were expressed as  percentage of the maximal p-ERK obtained at 5 min for ANG stimulation in  DMSO-treated VSMCs. Each data point represents the mean +- S.E. from  four independent experiments. Statistical analysis was done using a one-way  ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's post  test). *, p &lt; 0.05, compared with the DMSO-pretreated condition  for each stimulant. I, VSMCs were serum starved for 24 h to arrest  cycling and pretreated with dimethyl sulfoxide or 250 nm AG1478.  ANG (100 nm) or SII (10 mum) along with  3H-labeled thymidine was then added to the media, and 24 h later  cells were harvested as described under &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot;  Results depicted represent the mean +- S.E. of fold-increase over basal  counts per minute (cpm) from four independent experiments. Statistical  analysis was done using a one-way ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for  multiple comparisons (Bonferroni's post test). The AG1478-pretreated condition  shows significant reduction compared with the dimethyl sulfoxide-pretreated  condition for each stimulant (*, p &lt; 0.05). IB,  immunoblot.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36487</offset><text>Proteins in the Src tyrosine kinase family have been suggested previously  to function as upstream mediators of EGFR transactivation, particularly in  response to the stimulation of 7TM receptors  (25). Thus we hypothesized  that Src can be recruited to the AT1R upon agonist binding by beta-arrestin2  and play a role in AT1R-mediated EGFR transactivation. To test this  hypothesis, we examined the phosphorylation of EGFR at Tyr-845 upon ANG and  SII stimulation in control or beta-arrestins siRNA-transfected VSMCs. This  site is known to be phosphorylated by Src kinase  (26). Both ANG and SII  significantly stimulate phosphorylation of EGFR at Tyr-845 in control cells  (Fig. 7, C and  D). Interestingly, SII is equally effective as ANG in  inducing phosphorylation at this site, which is a 1.9 +- 0.2-fold  increase over basal. Both ANG- and SII-induced EGFR phosphorylation at Tyr-845  is dramatically reduced by depletion of beta-arrestin2 expression by siRNA.  On the contrary, depletion of beta-arrestin1 expression had no effect on  AT1R-mediated phosphorylation of EGFR (data not shown). Consistent with other  findings, stimulation with the PKC activator phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate  failed to induce phosphorylation of EGFR on Tyr-845 (data not shown). Our  results suggest that beta-arrestin2 regulates AT1R-mediated EGFR  transactivation and subsequent ERK activation by recruiting downstream  signaling molecules such as Src kinase to the receptors.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>37959</offset><text>Roles of Src in ANG- and SII-induced activation of ERK and EGFR.  A and B, VSMCs were pretreated with DMSO or 10  mum PP2 (Src inhibitor) and then treated with 100 nm  ANG or 10 mum SII for 5 min. Equal amounts of cell lysate were  separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed for phosphorylated ERK (p-ERK) and  total ERK (ERK) by Western blotting. Signals were quantified by  densitometry and p-ERK was normalized to a loading control (ERK). Signal at  each point is expressed as percentage of the maximal p-ERK signal (ANG for 5  min) in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO)-treated VSMCs. A,  representative p-ERK and ERK Western blots in dimethyl sulfoxide or  PP2-pretreated VSMCs were presented. B, each data point represents  the mean +- S.E. from four independent experiments. Statistical analysis  was done using a one-way ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for multiple  comparisons (Bonferroni's post test). *, p &lt; 0.05, compared with  dimethyl sulfoxide treatment for each stimulant. C and D,  VSMCs were transfected with the indicated siRNAs using Lipofectamine 2000.  Serum-deprived VSMCs were incubated with 100 nm ANG and 10  mum SII for 2 min and immunoprecipitated with EGFR antibody.  EGFRY845 phosphorylation was determined by Western analysis with  Tyr(P)-845-specific antibody and EGFR antibody. EGFRY845  phosphorylation was quantified by densitometry and normalized to a loading  control (EGFR). C, representative Western blots for  EGFRY845 and EGFR in siRNA-transfected VSMCs were presented.  D, data are presented as fold-increase over basal (the mean +-  S.E.) from six independent experiments. Statistical analysis was done using a  one-way ANOVA (PRISM software) to correct for multiple comparisons  (Bonferroni's post test). ANG and SII significantly increase phosphorylation  of EGFR at Tyr-845 compared with no stimulation (NS) control (*,  p &lt; 0.05). Depletion of beta-arrestin2 shows a significant  reduction on both ANG and SII mediated phosphorylation of EGFR at Tyr-845  compared with its own agonist stimulation in the control siRNA-transfected  condition (**, p &lt; 0.05).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>40049</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40060</offset><text>ANG-mediated signaling in VSMCs plays important roles in the development of  pathological conditions such as restenosis, atherosclerosis, and hypertension.  Abnormal regulation of 7TM receptor-mediated VSMC proliferation and migration  are the major forces inducing such pathological conditions in a variety of  vascular diseases. Mechanisms of VSMC proliferation induced by G protein  signaling induced by 7TM receptor systems have been extensively studied. Here  we investigated the novel roles of beta-arrestins in 7TM receptor-mediated  signaling in VSMCs. Classically, beta-arrestins terminate signals emanating  from agonist-bound 7TM receptors by physically interfering with receptor  coupling to its cognate G protein (desensitization), and also removing  receptors from the cell surface through initiating interaction with several  elements of the clathrin-coated pit endocytic machinery (internalization).  Recent data, however, have revealed that beta-arrestins also act as signal  transducers and adaptors that scaffold a variety of signaling molecules,  leading to mitogen-activated protein kinase activation, DNA synthesis, protein  translation, and cell migration  (2).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>41245</offset><text>Roles of beta-arrestins as signal transducers have been extensively  studied for AT1R-mediated ERK activation in receptor-transfected HEK 293 cells  (13,  27). Here, we studied  ANG-stimulated ERK activation in a physiologically relevant cell type, rat  VSMCs, and compared the results to those observed previously in HEK 293 cells  transiently transfected with AT1R. Whereas, the overall patterns were similar,  several notable differences were observed. AT1R-mediated ERK activation in  VSMCs is more transient than that in AT1R-transfected HEK 293 cells. In the  latter, ANG-stimulated ERK activation reached maximal levels rapidly, remained  stable for up to 10 min, and decreased very slowly (over 1 h)  (13). On the other hand, ANG-  and SII-induced ERK activation in VSMCs peaks at 5 min and is quite transient,  decreasing to background levels by 30 min. This may be due to the very low  levels of endogenously expressed AT1R in VSMCs (~15 fmol/mg). By utilizing  beta-arrestin RNAi and PKC inhibitors, two pathways for ERK activation by  the AT1R expressed in HEK 293 cells have been distinguished previously; rapid  and transient G protein-dependent activation, which is sensitive to PKC  inhibitors versus slow and prolonged beta-arrestin2-dependent  activation, which is sensitive to beta-arrestin2 RNAi  (13). In VSMCs, pretreatment  with PKC inhibitors also specifically inhibits early activation of ERK  (1-2 min) but not that at later time points, indicating that early  activation of ERK requires G-protein-mediated second messenger production.  Furthermore, depletion of beta-arrestin2, but not of beta-arrestin1, using  RNAi leads to inhibition of ANG-mediated ERK activation at later time points  in VSMCs. However, ERK activation at later time points in VSMCs was not  completely abolished as was previously observed in AT1R-transfected HEK 293  cells, possibly due to incomplete depletion of beta-arrestin2 (~70%) in  primary cultured VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43209</offset><text>Functions of beta-arrestins as signal transducers have been demonstrated  for many different 7TM receptors including angiotensin II type 1A  (AT1A) (13),  beta2-adrenergic  (28), neurokinin 1  (29), proteinase-activated  (30), vasopressin 2  (31), CXCR4 chemokine  (32), and parathyroid hormone  (33) receptors, as well as for  other types of receptors including the insulin-like growth factor 1-receptor  (34), ion channels  (35), nicotinic acetylcholine  receptor (36), and  transforming grow factor beta receptor  (37). In the case of 7TM  receptor-mediated ERK activation, the later phase of beta-arrestin-dependent  ERK activation is sometimes blocked by depletion of either beta-arrestin, by  depletion of beta-arrestin2, but not beta-arrestin1, or vice versa  depending on receptor and cell type. For example, both beta-arrestin1 and -2  are required for beta-arrestin-dependent ERK activation mediated by  beta2-adrenergic  (28) and parathyroid hormone  (33) receptors. On the other  hand, beta-arrestin1 and -2 show reciprocal functions in AT1R  (27) and V2  (31) receptor-mediated ERK  activation; beta-arrestin1 acts as a physiological  &quot;dominant-negative&quot; of beta-arrestin2-mediated ERK activation by  these receptors. In the present study, ANG-mediated ERK activation in  beta-arrestin1 siRNA-transfected VSMCs was not enhanced compared with that  from control siRNA-transfected cells except at the 2-min time point, and  SII-mediated ERK activation was not changed in beta-arrestin1  siRNA-transfected cells. Thus the role of beta-arrestin1, if any, in  modulating beta-arrestin2-mediated ERK activation stimulated via the AT1R in  VSMCs is not clear.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44875</offset><text>AT1R is a typical Gq-coupled 7TM receptor that initiates  generation of inositol triphosphate and diacyglycerol second messengers by  activation of phosphatidylinositol-specific phospholipase C. These second  messengers in turn trigger mobilization of intracellular calcium and  activation of PKC, which has been known to play important roles in  AT1R-mediated ERK activation  (14). In VSMCs, PKCdelta has  been known to be activated upon ANG stimulation leading to AKT activation  (38) and PKCzeta has been  suggested to play a major role in AT1R-mediated ERK/Elk-1 activation via the  Ras/MEK pathway (24). We  showed that inhibition of PKCzeta activity using chemical inhibitors or by  depletion of its expression by RNAi inhibited G protein-dependent (early time  point) AT1R-mediated ERK activation in VSMCs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>45689</offset><text>Numerous 7TM receptors have been known to utilize EGFR transactivation  mechanisms to activate ERK in various cell types. Moreover, it has been  observed that AT1R-mediated ERK activation requires EGFR kinase activity in  several cell types including C9 hepatocytes and COS-7 cells transfected with  the AT1R as well as in VSMCs  (19,  39). It has been shown that G  protein activation plays a role in AT1R-mediated EGFR transactivation through  an heparin binding-EGF shedding mechanism  (40). Here we found that the  beta-arrestin-biased analogue SII-ANG induced ERK activation and subsequent  DNA synthesis also require EGFR kinase activity in VSMCs. Moreover,  SII-mediated ERK activation was also inhibited in the presence of an matrix  metalloprotease inhibitor, which is known to block heparin binding-EGF  shedding in VSMCs, suggesting that beta-arrestin2 as well as G proteins can  mediate an heparin binding-EGF shedding mechanism in VSMCs. We also found that  stimulation with either ANG or SII induced EGFR phosphorylation at Tyr-845 by  Src kinase, which is known to activate EGFR. It has been shown that activation  of many 7TM receptors recruits activated c-Src to the receptor complex in a  beta-arrestin-dependent manner  (41). It thus appears that  multiple signaling mechanisms can mediate AT1R and EGFR cross-talk in VSMCs.  It will be of interest to determine whether distinct physiological outcomes of  AT1R-mediated EGFR transactivation are associated with these different  signaling mechanisms.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>47208</offset><text>Several physiologic consequences of beta-arrestin-dependent signaling  have been discovered in recent years. For example, beta-arrestin-mediated  signal transduction via the AT1R results in positive inotropic and lusitropic  effects in isolated adult mouse cardiomyocytes  (42).  beta-Arrestin-dependent ERK signaling regulates mRNA translation and protein  synthesis via Mnk1, a protein that both physically interacts with and is  activated by beta-arrestin  (43).  beta1-Adrenergic receptors have been shown to mediate  beta-arrestin-dependent transactivation of the EGFR thus promoting  activation of the cardioprotective pathway in the heart that counteracts the  effects of catecholamine toxicity  (44). In addition,  atherosclerosis and restenosis in an animal model are aggravated by  beta-arrestin2 through mechanisms involving VSMC proliferation and migration  (11). Taken together, these  findings indicate the physiological and pathological importance of  beta-arrestins as transducers regulating mitogenic signals through 7TM  receptors.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>48258</offset><text>In summary, our findings indicate that for the ATIR in VSMCs G  protein-dependent second messenger-mediated and beta-arrestin2-dependent  signaling pathways converge on transactivation of the EGFR and subsequent ERK  activation. Each pathway contributes to ANG-mediated regulation of  cardiovascular function. These results underscore the complexity and  multiplicity of signaling mechanisms available to 7TM receptors and add to the  growing recognition of the importance of beta-arrestins as signal  transducers.</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Drake, M. T., Shenoy, S. K., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -582</infon><infon key="fpage">570</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16973913</infon><infon key="source">Circ. Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">99</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48773</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DeWire, S. M., Ahn, S., Lefkowitz, R. J., and Shenoy, S. K.  ()     -510</infon><infon key="fpage">483</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17305471</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">69</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>48774</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Demoliou-Mason, C. D. ()    -97</infon><infon key="fpage">90</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9629460</infon><infon key="source">Biol. Signals  Recept.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>48775</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nozawa, Y., Matsuura, N., Miyake, H., Yamada, S., and Kimura, R.  ()     -2070</infon><infon key="fpage">2061</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10374931</infon><infon key="source">Life Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">64</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>48776</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wassmann, S., and Nickenig, G. ()    -S21</infon><infon key="fpage">S15</infon><infon key="source">J.  Hypertens.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48777</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yu, P. J., Ferrari, G., Pirelli, L., Gulkarov, I., Galloway, A. C.,  Mignatti, P., and Pintucci, G. ()    -1371</infon><infon key="fpage">1359</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17448633</infon><infon key="source">Cell.  Signal.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>48778</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rudijanto, A. ()    -93</infon><infon key="fpage">86</infon><infon key="source">Acta Med.  Indonesia</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">39</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>48779</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wei, H., Ahn, S., Shenoy, S. K., Karnik, S. S., Hunyady, L.,  Luttrell, L. M., and Lefkowitz, R. J. ()    -10787</infon><infon key="fpage">10782</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12949261</infon><infon key="source">Proc.  Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">100</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>48780</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Attramadal, H., Arriza, J. L., Aoki, C., Dawson, T. M., Codina, J.,  Kwatra, M. M., Snyder, S. H., Caron, M. G., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -17890</infon><infon key="fpage">17882</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1517224</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">267</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>48781</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ahn, S., Nelson, C. D., Garrison, T. R., Miller, W. E., and  Lefkowitz, R. J. ()    -1744</infon><infon key="fpage">1740</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12582207</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">100</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>48782</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kim, J., Zhang, L., Peppel, K., Wu, J. H., Zidar, D. A., Brian, L.,  DeWire, S. M., Exum, S. T., Lefkowitz, R. J., and Freedman, N. J.  ()     -79</infon><infon key="fpage">70</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18519945</infon><infon key="source">Circ. Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>48783</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Daub, H., Wallasch, C., Lankenau, A., Herrlich, A., and Ullrich, A.  ()     -7044</infon><infon key="fpage">7032</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9384582</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>48784</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ahn, S., Shenoy, S. K., Wei, H., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -35525</infon><infon key="fpage">35518</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15205453</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>48785</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">de Gasparo, M., Catt, K. J., Inagami, T., Wright, J. W., and Unger,  T. ()     -472</infon><infon key="fpage">415</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10977869</infon><infon key="source">Pharmacol. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">52</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>48786</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Assender, J. W., Kontny, E., and Fredholm, B. B.  ()     -80</infon><infon key="fpage">76</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8143854</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">342</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>48787</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Parmentier, J. H., Zhang, C., Estes, A., Schaefer, S., and Malik,  K. U. ()     -H1613</infon><infon key="fpage">H1602</infon><infon key="source">Am. J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">291</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48788</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Porreca, E., Ciccarelli, R., Di Febbo, C., and Cuccurullo, F.  ()     -145</infon><infon key="fpage">137</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8141837</infon><infon key="source">Atherosclerosis</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">104</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>48789</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kariya, K., Karns, L. R., and Simpson, P. C. ()     -10026</infon><infon key="fpage">10023</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2037558</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">266</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>48790</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Eguchi, S., Iwasaki, H., Ueno, H., Frank, G. D., Motley, E. D.,  Eguchi, K., Marumo, F., Hirata, Y., and Inagami, T. ()     -36851</infon><infon key="fpage">36843</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10601235</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>48791</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Saito, S., Frank, G. D., Motley, E. D., Dempsey, P. J., Utsunomiya,  H., Inagami, T., and Eguchi, S. ()    -1029</infon><infon key="fpage">1023</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12074579</infon><infon key="source">Biochem.  Biophys. Res. Commun.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">294</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>48792</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zhou, C. H., Qian, Z. Y., Zheng, S. G., and Xiang, M.  ()     -68</infon><infon key="fpage">61</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16580346</infon><infon key="source">Eur. J. Pharmacol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">535</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48793</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Seta, K., Nanamori, M., Modrall, J. G., Neubig, R. R., and  Sadoshima, J. ()     -9277</infon><infon key="fpage">9268</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11777928</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>48794</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Zou, Y., Komuro, I., Yamazaki, T., Kudoh, S., Aikawa, R., Zhu, W.,  Shiojima, I., Hiroi, Y., Tobe, K., Kadowaki, T., and Yazaki, Y.  ()     -345</infon><infon key="fpage">337</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9486662</infon><infon key="source">Circ. Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">82</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>48795</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Godeny, M. D., and Sayeski, P. P. ()     -C1307</infon><infon key="fpage">C1297</infon><infon key="source">Am. J. Physiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">291</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48796</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Poppleton, H. M., Wiepz, G. J., Bertics, P. J., and Patel, T. B.  ()     -236</infon><infon key="fpage">227</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10068444</infon><infon key="source">Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">363</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>48797</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Xu, K. P., Yin, J., and Yu, F. S. ()      -2839</infon><infon key="fpage">2832</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16799022</infon><infon key="source">Investig. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">47</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48798</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ahn, S., Wei, H., Garrison, T. R., and Lefkowitz, R. J.  ()     -7811</infon><infon key="fpage">7807</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14711824</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>48799</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Drake, M. T., Violin, J. D., Whalen, E. J., Wisler, J. W., Shenoy,  S. K., and Lefkowitz, R. J. ()    -5676</infon><infon key="fpage">5669</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18086673</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>48800</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Jafri, F., El-Shewy, H. M., Lee, M. H., Kelly, M., Luttrell, D. K.,  and Luttrell, L. M. ()     -19357</infon><infon key="fpage">19346</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16670094</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48801</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DeFea, K. A., Zalevsky, J., Thoma, M. S., Dery, O., Mullins, R. D.,  and Bunnett, N. W. ()     -1281</infon><infon key="fpage">1267</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10725339</infon><infon key="source">J. Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">148</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>48802</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ren, X. R., Reiter, E., Ahn, S., Kim, J., Chen, W., and Lefkowitz,  R. J. ()    -1453</infon><infon key="fpage">1448</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15671180</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">102</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>48803</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Lagane, B., Chow, K. Y., Balabanian, K., Levoye, A., Harriague, J.,  Planchenault, T., Baleux, F., Gunera-Saad, N., Arenzana-Seisdedos, F., and  Bachelerie, F. ()     -44</infon><infon key="fpage">34</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18436740</infon><infon key="source">Blood</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">112</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>48804</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gesty-Palmer, D., Chen, M., Reiter, E., Ahn, S., Nelson, C. D.,  Wang, S., Eckhardt, A. E., Cowan, C. L., Spurney, R. F., Luttrell, L. M., and  Lefkowitz, R. J. ()     -10864</infon><infon key="fpage">10856</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16492667</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48805</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Girnita, L., Shenoy, S. K., Sehat, B., Vasilcanu, R., Vasilcanu,  D., Girnita, A., Lefkowitz, R. J., and Larsson, O. ()     -11338</infon><infon key="fpage">11329</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17303558</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">282</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>48806</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Puckerin, A., Liu, L., Permaul, N., Carman, P., Lee, J., and  Diverse-Pierluissi, M. A. ()    -31141</infon><infon key="fpage">31131</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16912040</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48807</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dasgupta, P., Rastogi, S., Pillai, S., Ordonez-Ercan, D., Morris,  M., Haura, E., and Chellappan, S. ()    -2217</infon><infon key="fpage">2208</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16862215</infon><infon key="source">J. Clin.  Investig.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">116</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48808</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chen, W., Kirkbride, K. C., How, T., Nelson, C. D., Mo, J.,  Frederick, J. P., Wang, X. F., Lefkowitz, R. J., and Blobe, G. C.  ()     -1397</infon><infon key="fpage">1394</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12958365</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">301</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>48809</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nakashima, H., Frank, G. D., Shirai, H., Hinoki, A., Higuchi, S.,  Ohtsu, H., Eguchi, K., Sanjay, A., Reyland, M. E., Dempsey, P. J., Inagami,  T., and Eguchi, S. ()     -238</infon><infon key="fpage">232</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18180404</infon><infon key="source">Hypertension</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">51</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>48810</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shah, B. H., Yesilkaya, A., Olivares-Reyes, J. A., Chen, H. D.,  Hunyady, L., and Catt, K. J. ()    -2048</infon><infon key="fpage">2035</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15143154</infon><infon key="source">Mol.  Endocrinol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>48811</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Prenzel, N., Zwick, E., Daub, H., Leserer, M., Abraham, R.,  Wallasch, C., and Ullrich, A. ()     -888</infon><infon key="fpage">884</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10622253</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">402</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>48812</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Luttrell, L. M., Hawes, B. E., van Biesen, T., Luttrell, D. K.,  Lansing, T. J., and Lefkowitz, R. J. ()    -19450</infon><infon key="fpage">19443</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8702633</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>48813</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Rajagopal, K., Whalen, E. J., Violin, J. D., Stiber, J. A.,  Rosenberg, P. B., Premont, R. T., Coffman, T. M., Rockman, H. A., and  Lefkowitz, R. J. ()    -16289</infon><infon key="fpage">16284</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17060617</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>48814</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">DeWire, S. M., Kim, J., Whalen, E. J., Ahn, S., Chen, M., and  Lefkowitz, R. J. ()     -10620</infon><infon key="fpage">10611</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18276584</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">283</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>48815</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Noma, T., Lemaire, A., Naga Prasad, S. V., Barki-Harrington, L.,  Tilley, D. G., Chen, J., Le Corvoisier, P., Violin, J. D., Wei, H., Lefkowitz,  R. J., and Rockman, H. A. ()    -2458</infon><infon key="fpage">2445</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17786238</infon><infon key="source">J. Clin.  Investig.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">117</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>48816</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>48817</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: 7TM, seven transmembrane; AT1R, angiotensin  type 1 receptor; ANG, angiotensin II; SII,  [Sar1,Ile4,Ile8]-angiotensin II; ERK,  extracellular signal-regulated kinase; PKC, protein kinase C; siRNA, small  interfering RNA; HEK, human embryonic kidney; VSMC, vascular smooth muscle  cell; EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor; GRK, G protein-coupled receptor  kinases; BiPS,  2R-[(4-biphenylsulfonyl)amino]-N-hydroxy-3-phenylpropinamide;  MEK, mitogen-activated protein kinase/extracellular signal-regulated kinase  kinase; RNAi, RNA interference; GFX, bisindolylmaleimide I; ANOVA, analysis of  variance.</text></passage></document></collection>
