<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19321442</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M901203200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2682871</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19321442</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">14230</infon><infon key="fpage">14230</infon><infon key="issue">21</infon><infon key="lpage">14235</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Dixon;given-names:Rebecca M.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mellor;given-names:Jack R.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hanley;given-names:Jonathan G.</infon><infon key="p">The work was funded by grants from , the , and  (ENI-NET).</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>PICK1-mediated Glutamate Receptor Subunit 2 (GluR2) Trafficking  Contributes to Cell Death in Oxygen/Glucose-deprived Hippocampal  Neurons*</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>140</offset><text>Oxygen and glucose deprivation (OGD) induces delayed cell death in  hippocampal CA1 neurons via Ca2+/Zn2+-permeable,  GluR2-lacking AMPA receptors (AMPARs). Following OGD, synaptic AMPAR currents  in hippocampal neurons show marked inward rectification and increased  sensitivity to channel blockers selective for GluR2-lacking AMPARs. This  occurs via two mechanisms: a delayed down-regulation of GluR2 mRNA expression  and a rapid internalization of GluR2-containing AMPARs during the OGD insult,  which are replaced by GluR2-lacking receptors. The mechanisms that underlie  this rapid change in subunit composition are unknown. Here, we demonstrate  that this trafficking event shares features in common with events that mediate  long term depression and long term potentiation and is initiated by the  activation of N-methyl-d-aspartic acid receptors. Using  biochemical and electrophysiological approaches, we show that peptides that  interfere with PICK1 PDZ domain interactions block the OGD-induced switch in  subunit composition, implicating PICK1 in restricting GluR2 from synapses  during OGD. Furthermore, we show that GluR2-lacking AMPARs that arise at  synapses during OGD as a result of PICK1 PDZ interactions are involved in  OGD-induced delayed cell death. This work demonstrates that PICK1 plays a  crucial role in the response to OGD that results in altered synaptic  transmission and neuronal death and has implications for our understanding of  the molecular mechanisms that underlie cell death during stroke.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1671</offset><text>Oxygen and glucose deprivation  (OGD)3 associated with  transient global ischemia induces delayed cell death, particularly in  hippocampal CA1 pyramidal cells  (1-3),  a phenomenon that involves Ca2+/Zn2+-permeable,  GluR2-lacking AMPARs (4).  AMPARs are heteromeric complexes of subunits GluR1-4  (5), and most AMPARs in the  hippocampus contain GluR2, which renders them calcium-impermeable and results  in a marked inward rectification in their current-voltage relationship  (6-8).  Ischemia induces a delayed down-regulation of GluR2 mRNA and protein  expression (4,  9-11),  resulting in enhanced AMPAR-mediated Ca2+ and Zn2+  influx into CA1 neurons (10,  12). In these neurons,  AMPAR-mediated postsynaptic currents (EPSCs) show marked inward rectification  1-2 days following ischemia and increased sensitivity to 1-naphthyl  acetyl spermine (NASPM), a channel blocker selective for GluR2-lacking AMPARs  (13-16).  Blockade of these channels at 9-40 h following ischemia is  neuroprotective, indicating a crucial role for Ca2+-permeable  AMPARs in ischemic cell death  (16).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2754</offset><text>In addition to delayed changes in AMPAR subunit composition as a result of  altered mRNA expression, it was recently reported that  Ca2+-permable, GluR2-lacking AMPARs are targeted to synaptic sites  via membrane trafficking at much earlier times during OGD  (17). This subunit  rearrangement involves endocytosis of AMPARs containing GluR2 complexed with  GluR1/3, followed by exocytosis of GluR2-lacking receptors containing GluR1/3  (17). However, the molecular  mechanisms behind this trafficking event are unknown, and furthermore, it is  not known whether these trafficking-mediated changes in AMPAR subunit  composition contribute to delayed cell death.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3415</offset><text>AMPAR trafficking is a well studied phenomenon because of its crucial  involvement in long term depression (LTD) and long term potentiation (LTP),  activity-dependent forms of synaptic plasticity thought to underlie learning  and memory. AMPAR endocytosis, exocytosis, and more recently subunit-switching  events (brought about by trafficking that involves endo/exocytosis) are  central to the necessary changes in synaptic receptor complement  (7,  18-20).  It is possible that similar mechanisms regulate AMPAR trafficking during  OGD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3953</offset><text>PICK1 is a PDZ and BAR (Bin-amphiphysin-Rus) domain-containing protein that  binds, via the PDZ domain, to a number of membrane proteins including AMPAR  subunits GluR2/3. This interaction is required for AMPAR internalization from  the synaptic plasma membrane in response to Ca2+ influx via NMDAR  activation in hippocampal neurons  (21-23).  This process is the major mechanism that underlies the reduction in synaptic  strength in LTD. Furthermore, PICK1-mediated trafficking has recently emerged  as a mechanism that regulates the GluR2 content of synaptic receptors, which  in turn determines their Ca2+ permeability  (7,  20). This is likely to be of  profound importance in both plasticity and pathological mechanisms.  Importantly, PICK1 overexpression has been shown to induce a shift in synaptic  AMPAR subunit composition in hippocampal CA1 neurons, resulting in inwardly  rectifying AMPAR EPSCs via reduced surface GluR2 and no change in GluR1  (24). This suggests that PICK1  may mediate the rapid switch in subunit composition occurring during OGD  (17). Here, we demonstrate  that the OGD-induced switch in AMPAR subunit composition is dependent on PICK1  PDZ interactions, and importantly, that this early trafficking event that  occurs during OGD contributes to the signaling that results in delayed  neuronal death.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>5288</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5312</offset><text>Electrophysiology:Brain slices were prepared from postnatal  day 13-15 male Wistar rats following a lethal dose of anesthetic  (isoflurane inhalation). Brains were dissected in ice-cold aCSF (in  mm, 119 NaCl, 2.5 KCl, 1  NaH2PO4 H2O, 26.2 NaHCO3,  10 glucose, 2.5 CaCl2, 9 MgSO4) saturated with 95%  O2 and 5% CO2. Transverse hippocampal slices  300-400 mum thick were cut using a vibratome (DTK-1000, DSK, Japan),  and slices were stored at room temperature for at least 1 h before use. Before  being transferred to the submerged recording chamber, the connections between  CA3 and CA1 were cut. Slices were placed in a submerged recording chamber  perfused with aCSF (as above) at room temperature with the addition of 50  mum picrotoxin. CA1 pyramidal cells were visualized using  infrared differential interference contrast optics on a Zeiss Axioskop  microscope. Patch electrodes with a resistance of 4-5 megaohms were  pulled from borosilicate filamented glass capillaries. Pipettes were filled  with intracellular solution containing (in mm) 130  CsMeSO3, 8 NaCl, 5 QX314-Cl, 10 HEPES, 0.5 EGTA, 4 Mg-ATP, 0.3  Na-GTP, 0.1 spermine, 0.1 bestatin, 0.1 leupeptin, 0.1 pepstatin and set to pH  7.2, 280-285 mosm. Peptides were added at a final  concentration of 30 mum. Recordings from CA1 pyramidal neurons  were made with an Axopatch 200B amplifier (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA),  filtered at 5 kHz, and digitized at 10 kHz using a data acquisition board and  Signal acquisition software (CED, Cambridge, UK). Cells were voltage-clamped  at -70 mV. Series resistance was monitored throughout the experiments,  and cells that showed &gt;20% change or were greater than 25 megaohms were  discarded from subsequent analysis. Synaptic responses were evoked with  100-mus square voltage steps applied at 0.1 Hz through a bipolar stimulating  electrode (FHC) located in the stratum radiatum. d-AP5 and  picrotoxin were purchased from Tocris Bioscience.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7268</offset><text>Rectification was calculated as the mean EPSC amplitude at +40 mV divided  by the mean EPSC amplitude at -70 mV. Mean EPSCs were averages of at  least 20 individual sweeps. Comparisons of EPSC rectification before and after  OGD were assessed by a paired Student's t test with the null  hypothesis rejected if p &lt; 0.05. Data are plotted as the mean  +- S.E.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7626</offset><text>Neuronal Cultures, Sindbis Virus Infection, and Plasmid  Transfection:Primary neuronal cultures were prepared from embryonic  day 18 Wistar rat hippocampi. Sindbis viruses were prepared according to the  Sindbis Expression System manual  (Invitrogen).4  Infections were carried out as described  (25). Transfections were  carried out using Lipofectamine 2000.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>7986</offset><text>OGD causes an NMDA receptor-dependent increase in AMPA receptor  rectification. A, OGD produces a reduction in the amplitude of  AMPA receptor-mediated synaptic responses recorded at +40 mV in comparison  with -70 mV. Example traces show synaptic responses recorded while  holding the CA1 pyramidal cell at -70 mV and +40 mV pre-OGD  (black) and post-OGD (red). Traces are shown  overlaid on the right. B, rectification is measured  by recording synaptic responses at -70 mV and +40 mV in d-AP5  before and after 30 min of OGD. d-AP5 is washed out of the slice  before OGD is commenced. Average normalized synaptic response is shown for  eight experiments. C, the rectification index decreases after OGD in  control conditions corresponding to an increase in AMPAR rectification  (n = 8). The rectification index change for each experiment is  represented by the filled circles. The decrease is blocked by the  presence of d-AP5 during OGD. *, p &lt; 0.05.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8940</offset><text>Oxygen/Glucose Deprivation:For biotinylations and cell death  assays, neuronal cultures were exposed to OGD by transferring them to culture  medium containing sucrose instead of glucose, which had been saturated with  95% N2,5%CO2. After three washes in this medium,  cultures were placed in a pre-warmed Billups-Rothenberg modular incubator  chamber in a 37  C incubator and flushed with 95%  N2,5%CO2 for 10 min. The air-tight chamber was then  sealed, and following various time points, cultures were transferred back to  normal conditioned medium (cell death assays) or processed for subsequent  experimentation (biotinylations). For electrophysiology experiments, slices  were perfused with 95% N2,5%CO2-saturated aCSF  containing sucrose in place of glucose for 30 min followed by perfusion with  normal aCSF. Stimulation was ceased during the OGD period.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9802</offset><text>Surface Biotinylation:Following OGD, cultures at 18-21  days in vitro were chilled on ice, washed in ice-cold PBS, and  incubated with 0.25 mg/ml Sulfo-NHS-SS-Biotin (Pierce) in PBS for 10 min on  ice. After washing three times in PBS plus 1 mg/ml bovine serum albumin and  three times in PBS, cells were lysed in 500 ml of lysis buffer (25  mm HEPES (pH 7.2), 150 mm NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 0.2%  SDS). After centrifugation, lysate was incubated with streptavidin-agarose  beads for 3 h at 4  C, washed four times in lysis buffer, and bound  protein detected by Western blotting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>10382</offset><text>OGD-induced increase in AMPA receptor rectification is blocked by  inhibiting PICK1 PDZ domain interactions. Top panels, example  traces recorded at -70 mV and +40 mV pre-OGD (black) and  post-OGD (red). Post-OGD traces are scaled so that -70 mV peaks  are identical. Bottom panels, average change in rectification  (n = 7) with individual experiments represented by circles.  A, control peptide pep2-SVKE has no effect on the OGD-induced  decrease in the rectification index. **, p &lt; 0.005. B,  PICK1-specific peptide pep2-EVKI completely blocks the OGD-induced change in  the rectification index. C, PICK1 and ABP/GRIP-blocking peptide  pep2-SVKI does not completely block OGD-induced change in the rectification  index. *, p &lt; 0.05.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11118</offset><text>Quantification of Western Blots:Films of Western blots from  at least four identical independent experiments were scanned and analyzed  using Image J. A ratio of values for bands representing surface over those for  total GluR2 was determined for a given condition. Error bars are  standard errors, and paired t tests were carried out to determine  significant differences.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11492</offset><text>Cell Death Assays:30 h following OGD, cultures at  20-22 days in vitro were stained with propidium iodide (PI; 4  mug/ml) and Hoechst stain (2 mug/ml) for 1 h before imaging. A field of  view was defined as a scan across the width of the coverslip. Within this  area, the proportion of Hoechst-positive nuclei that were PI-positive was  counted. For each experiment, the average of four fields of view was  calculated per condition. The experiment was then repeated four times  (peptides) or seven times (NASPM). Error bars are standard errors,  and paired t tests were carried out to determine significant  differences.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>12113</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12121</offset><text>OGD Induces an NMDAR-dependent Change in AMPAR  Rectification:AMPAR EPSC rectification is a well established assay  for the presence of GluR2-containing AMPARs. 99% of GluR2 subunits in CA1  pyramidal cells are edited at the Q/R site, preventing susceptibility to block  by endogenous polyamines. AMPARs lacking GluR2 are blocked by polyamines in a  voltage-dependent manner, with the degree of blockade much greater at positive  membrane potentials  (5-7).  These properties result in a linear current-voltage relationship for  GluR2-containing AMPARs but an inwardly rectifying relationship for those  lacking GluR2. It is therefore possible to assess the proportion of  GluR2-containing AMPARs at the synapse by measuring the inward rectification  displayed by the current-voltage relationship.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12919</offset><text>We measured the rectification of AMPAR-EPSCs by making whole-cell voltage  clamp recordings from CA1 pyramidal neurons in acute hippocampal slices and  stimulating the Schaffer collaterals. Cells were voltage-clamped at -70  mV and +40 mV in the presence of the NMDAR antagonist d-AP5 (50  mum) to measure the degree of AMPAR rectification  (Fig. 1, A and  B). After d-AP5 washout, a 30-min OGD protocol  was then applied to the slice (see &quot;Experimental Procedures&quot;),  after which d-AP5 was reapplied and the EPSC amplitude slowly  recovered over 10-15 min. Once the EPSC amplitude reached stability,  rectification was again measured at -70 mV and +40 mV  (Fig. 1B). The  rectification index was measured by dividing the EPSC amplitude at +40 mV by  that at -70 mV; therefore a decrease in the index corresponds to an  increase in the degree of current-voltage rectification. 30 min of OGD  produced a decrease in the rectification index in control experiments (pre-OGD  = 0.46 +- 0.02, post-OGD = 0.40 +- 0.02, n = 8,  p &lt; 0.001). This effect was blocked if d-AP5 was  present throughout the OGD protocol (pre-OGD = 0.38 +- 0.03, post-OGD =  0.42 +- 0.07, n = 6, p = 0.6)  (Fig. 1C).  Time-matched control experiments that were identical except without OGD  produced no change in the rectification index (pre-OGD = 0.35 +- 0.03,  post-OGD = 0.37 +- 0.05, n = 6, p = 0.58, data not  shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14311</offset><text>To ensure that OGD did not induce a change in the EPSC reversal potential,  we performed separate experiments recording responses at -70, -50,  -30, and -10 mV before and after OGD. By fitting a straight line  through the data points, we calculated the EPSC reversal potential and found  no change after OGD (pre-OGD 0.9 +- 3 mV, post-OGD 3.2 +- 5 mV,  n = 3, p = 0.49, data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14698</offset><text>The OGD-induced Change in AMPAR-EPSC Rectification Is  PICK1-dependent:The increase in rectification following OGD  suggests a rapid decrease in the proportion of synaptic GluR2-containing  AMPARs relative to GluR2-lacking AMPARs during the OGD insult. Because PDZ  domain interactions with GluR2 are known to regulate AMPAR trafficking  (19,  26,  27), we carried out  experiments to determine the role of such interactions during OGD using  peptides corresponding to the C terminus of GluR2 to block interactions with  the PDZ domains of PICK1 or of ABP and GRIP1 (hereafter referred to as  ABP/GRIP). The wild-type sequence pep2-SVKI blocks PICK1 and ABP/GRIP PDZ  domains, pep2-EVKI specifically blocks PICK1, and pep2-SVKE is an inactive  control peptide (28). These  peptides were included separately in our recording solution and diffused into  the cell during the experiment. As expected, inclusion of the control peptide  pep2-SVKE had no effect on the change in the rectification index induced by  OGD (Fig. 2A, pre-OGD  = 0.4 +- 0.04, post-OGD = 0.3 +- 0.03, n = 7, p  &lt; 0.005). However, the PICK1-specific pep2-EVKI completely blocked the  decrease in the rectification index (Fig.  2B, pre-OGD = 0.33 +- 0.02, post-OGD = 0.36  +- 0.02, n = 6, p = 0.46). Surprisingly, pep2-SVKI,  which blocks both PICK1 and ABP/GRIP PDZ domains, did not completely block the  decrease in the rectification index (Fig.  2C, pre-OGD = 0.42 +- 0.04, post-OGD = 0.37  +- 0.03, n = 6, p &lt; 0.05).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>16186</offset><text>OGD induces a rapid, PICK1-dependent removal of GluR2 from the surface  of hippocampal neurons. A, GluR1 surface levels are unaffected by  OGD. Dissociated hippocampal neurons were exposed to OGD for the times  indicated followed by biotinylation of surface proteins. The top  panel shows a representative Western blot of total GluR1 present in  lysates and surface (biotinylated) GluR1 after OGD. The graph shows pooled  data presented as ratios of surface over total GluR1. n = 5.  B, GluR2 is rapidly removed from the surface in response to OGD.  Methods are same as for A, above, except that the Western blot was  probed for GluR2. n = 5, *, p &lt; 0.01, **, p &lt;  0.001. C, OGD-induced internalization of GluR2 is blocked by peptides  that disrupt PICK1 PDZ domain interactions. Dissociated hippocampal neurons  were transduced with Sindbis virus to express pep2-SVKE, pep2-SVKI, or  pep2-EVKI. Cultures were exposed to OGD and analyzed as in B, above.  n = 5, *, p &lt; 0.005.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17162</offset><text>The inclusion of pep2-EVKI or pep2-SVKI in the intracellular solution has  previously been shown to produce changes in the EPSC amplitude in the absence  of OGD, although rectification changes were not tested  (21,  28). We performed time-matched  control experiments for each of the peptides used that were identical to the  experiments described above, except for the absence of OGD. None of these  controls produced changes in the rectification index (pep2-SVKE, pre-OGD =  0.34 +- 0.01, post-OGD = 0.31 +- 0.03, n = 6, p  = 0.21; pep2-EVKI, pre-OGD = 0.39 +- 0.03, post-OGD = 0.38 +-  0.02, n = 6, p = 0.57; pep2-SVKI, pre-OGD = 0.44 +-  0.04, post-OGD = 0.42 +- 0.04, n = 6, p = 0.48),  indicating that the inclusion of the peptides on their own did not alter  AMPAR-EPSC rectification.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17954</offset><text>The OGD-induced Reduction in Surface-expressed GluR2 Is  PICK1-dependent:To directly analyze the surface AMPAR subunit  switching induced by OGD, we carried out surface biotinylations in dissociated  hippocampal cultures. Neurons were subjected to OGD followed immediately by  biotinylation of surface proteins. We observed a time-dependent reduction in  GluR2 surface expression by OGD (Fig.  3B), which is consistent with a previous study  (17). 30 min of OGD was  sufficient to induce this trafficking event, with the maximal effect seen at  120 min. GluR1 surface expression was unaffected by OGD at all time points  tested (Fig. 3A), as  demonstrated previously (17).  To investigate the role of PICK1 PDZ interactions, we used the Sindbis virus  to express GluR2 C-terminal peptides in cultured neurons. The viruses are  bicistronic to express enhanced green fluorescent protein in addition to the  peptides. By visualizing green fluorescent protein fluorescence, we  consistently observed that 80-90% neurons were infected. We then assayed  surface GluR2 following a 30-min period of OGD. The control peptide pep2-SVKE  had no effect on OGD-induced GluR2 trafficking. However, pep2-SVKI and  pep2-EVKI, both of which disrupt PICK1 PDZ interactions, completely blocked  the reduction in surface-expressed GluR2 in response to OGD  (Fig. 3C). These data  strongly suggest that PICK1 plays a crucial role in the OGD-induced switch in  surface AMPAR subunit composition.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19428</offset><text>Activity of GluR2-lacking AMPARs during OGD Insult Contribute to  Delayed Neuronal Death:To investigate the functional relevance of  PICK1-mediated subunit switching during the OGD insult, we used NASPM to  specifically block GluR2-lacking AMPARs. We applied the drug before OGD and  washed it out immediately following the insult so that GluR2-lacking AMPARs  would be blocked specifically during OGD. Cell death was then analyzed by PI  staining 30 h later. NASPM application during OGD resulted in a significant  reduction in delayed cell death (Fig.  4A), indicating that channel activity of GluR2-lacking  AMPARs during OGD contributes to OGD-induced cell death.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>20096</offset><text>PICK1-mediated switching of AMPAR subunit composition during OGD  contributes to OGD-induced neuronal death. A, blockade of  GluR2-lacking receptors during OGD significantly reduces neuronal death.  Dissociated hippocampal neurons were exposed to 45 min of OGD in the absence  or presence of the GluR2-lacking AMPAR blocker NASPM (30 mum).  Coverslips were washed extensively before returning them to normal conditioned  growth medium. 30 h later, neurons were stained with Hoechst and PI, and the  proportion of nuclei stained with PI was counted. The left panels  show representative images for vehicle and NASPM-treated cultures. The graph  shows pooled data, normalized to the vehicle-treated control. n = 7,  **, p &lt; 0.01. B, blockade of PICK1 PDZ domain  interactions significantly reduces neuronal death. Dissociated hippocampal  neurons were transfected with plasmids encoding the peptides pep2-SVKE  (control), pep2-SVKI (wild type), and pep2-EVKI (PICK1-specific). Cultures  were exposed to 45 min of OGD and stained with Hoechst and propidium iodide 30  h later, and the proportion of nuclei stained with PI was counted. Data are  normalized to the pep2-SVKE condition. n = 4, *, p &lt;  0.05.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21298</offset><text>PICK1-dependent Subunit Switching during OGD Insult Contributes to  Delayed Neuronal Death:To specifically study the role of  PICK1-mediated trafficking, we transfected hippocampal neurons with plasmids  encoding GluR2 C-terminal peptides to block PICK1 PDZ domain interactions,  exposed the cultures to OGD, and quantified delayed cell death by PI staining.  Both the wild-type pep2-SVKI and the PICK1-specific pep2-EVKI significantly  rescued neurons from OGD-induced cell death when compared with the inactive  control peptide, pep2-SVKE (Fig.  4B). This strongly suggests that PICK1 PDZ domain  interactions, and therefore PICK1-mediated AMPAR trafficking, are required for  delayed OGD-induced cell death.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>22009</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22020</offset><text>In this study, we have identified the GluR2-PICK1 interaction as a crucial  mediator of OGD-induced AMPAR trafficking that results in an increased  proportion of synaptic GluR2-lacking receptors. Our work also defines this  trafficking event during OGD as a critical step leading to delayed neuronal  death following the insult. In a previous study, it was shown that GluR2-PICK1  binding increases in hippocampal neurons following OGD  (17); however, a causal link  between this interaction and the switch in AMPAR subunit composition was not  demonstrated. We have taken this further by providing direct evidence that  disrupting PICK1-GluR2 interactions blocks the internalization of GluR2 from  the cell surface and the resulting rectification change of synaptic  AMPAR-EPSCs. Furthermore, we have demonstrated that PICK1-mediated regulation  of GluR2 occurring during OGD is required for delayed neuronal death.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22937</offset><text>In addition to PICK1, the GluR2 PDZ ligand binds GRIP1 and ABP/GRIP. Our  biotinylation data and cell death assays indicate that interfering with both  PICK1 and ABP/GRIP PDZ domains (using pep2-SVKI) has the same effect as  blocking just PICK1 (pep2-EVKI), suggesting that PICK1 is the more important  protein. However, in our electrophysiology experiments, pep2-SVKI is less  potent at blocking the OGD-induced rectification change when compared with  pep2-EVKI. A possible explanation for this result may be that ABP/GRIP has an  influence on GluR2-containing AMPARs that opposes that of PICK1. Consistent  with this idea, it has been demonstrated that during OGD, the GluR2-PICK1  interaction is enhanced, whereas GluR2-ABP is reduced  (17). The difference between  the electrophysiology and cell biology results is likely to reflect the  difference in mode of presentation of the peptide: acute infusion when  compared with long term expression. The lack of an interfering peptide that is  specific to ABP/GRIP PDZ domains makes it difficult to assess the role of  ABP/GRIP using this approach.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24037</offset><text>It is well established that GluR2 mRNA levels and protein expression are  reduced in hippocampal CA1 neurons 24-48 h after ischemia  (29). The specific role of  GluR2-lacking AMPARs brought about by PICK1-mediated trafficking at an earlier  stage during OGD when compared with those expressed at later time points via  altered gene expression is unclear. It is possible that the role of the early  AMPAR-mediated calcium signal during OGD is to provide a trigger for signaling  pathways that result in additional synaptic changes at a later time point,  which may include altered GluR2 gene expression.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24640</offset><text>A change in AMPAR-EPSC rectification has recently been described following  LTP induction in CA1 hippocampal neurons  (30) (but see Ref.  31), which may be  PICK1-dependent (32). It has  been proposed that the calcium influx through these GluR2-lacking AMPARs is  required for stabilization of LTP, and therefore, for longer term changes in  synaptic transmission. In the case of LTP, the rectification change is  transient, lasting only for around 20 min following stimulus  (30). However, the OGD-induced  change in AMPAR subunit composition persists for at least 24 h after insult  (17), suggesting that  important functional as well as mechanistic differences exist between OGD and  LTP. In our experiments, the increased AMPAR-EPSC rectification seen  immediately after OGD is relatively small (~20% change) when compared with  that seen during LTP expression (~80% change). During OGD, therefore, the  resulting calcium influx via these early GluR2-lacking AMPARs is likely to be  small yet sustained, whereas during LTP, the AMPAR-mediated calcium signal may  be large and more transient  (30). These precise temporal  characteristics may be crucial in determining the downstream effects of AMPAR  subunit rearrangements.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25869</offset><text>PICK1 has now been implicated in a number of physiological and pathological  situations that involve regulating the GluR2 content of synaptic AMPARs.  Interestingly, in most of these events, including during OGD (this study),  PICK1 plays a role in restricting GluR2 from the synapse, rendering a  proportion of AMPARs calcium-permeable  (24,  33,  34). This is likely to reflect  a function for PICK1 in promoting GluR2 endocytosis or in restricting its  recycling (35). However, in  cerebellar stellate cells, PICK1 plays a role in mediating a switch from  GluR2-lacking to GluR2-containing synaptic AMPARs  (36,  37), suggesting that PICK1 can  also promote forward traffic (or restrict endocytosis) of GluR2-containing  AMPARs in certain cell types. Further work is needed to unravel the precise  mechanisms that underlie how PICK1 specifically sorts and targets  GluR2-containing AMPARs to appropriate subcellular locations.</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Choi, D. W. ()    -60</infon><infon key="fpage">58</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7537408</infon><infon key="source">Trends  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>26799</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kirino, T. ()     -69</infon><infon key="fpage">57</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7093691</infon><infon key="source">Brain Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">239</infon><infon key="year">1982</infon><offset>26800</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pulsinelli, W. A., Brierley, J. B., and Plum, F.  ()     -498</infon><infon key="fpage">491</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7103425</infon><infon key="source">Ann. Neurol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">1982</infon><offset>26801</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tanaka, H., Grooms, S. Y., Bennett, M. V., and Zukin, R. S.  ()     -207</infon><infon key="fpage">190</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11119696</infon><infon key="source">Brain Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">886</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>26802</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dingledine, R., Borges, K., Bowie, D., and Traynelis, S. F.  ()     -61</infon><infon key="fpage">7</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10049997</infon><infon key="source">Pharmacol. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">51</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>26803</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hollmann, M., Hartley, M., and Heinemann, S. ()     -853</infon><infon key="fpage">851</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1709304</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">252</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>26804</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Isaac, J. T., Ashby, M., and McBain, C. J. ()     -871</infon><infon key="fpage">859</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17582328</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">54</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26805</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, S. J., and Zukin, R. S. ()    -134</infon><infon key="fpage">126</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17275103</infon><infon key="source">Trends  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">30</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26806</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pellegrini-Giampietro, D. E., Zukin, R. S., Bennett, M. V., Cho,  S., and Pulsinelli, W. A. ()    -10503</infon><infon key="fpage">10499</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1438239</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad.  Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">89</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>26807</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gorter, J. A., Petrozzino, J. J., Aronica, E. M., Rosenbaum, D. M.,  Opitz, T., Bennett, M. V., Connor, J. A., and Zukin, R. S. ()     -6188</infon><infon key="fpage">6179</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9236229</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>26808</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Opitz, T., Grooms, S. Y., Bennett, M. V., and Zukin, R. S.  ()     -13365</infon><infon key="fpage">13360</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11087875</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>26809</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Yin, H. Z., Sensi, S. L., Ogoshi, F., and Weiss, J. H.  ()     -1279</infon><infon key="fpage">1273</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11850455</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>26810</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Tsubokawa, H., Oguro, K., Masuzawa, T., Nakaima, T., and Kawai, N.  ()     -225</infon><infon key="fpage">218</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7472325</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurophysiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">74</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>26811</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ying, H. S., Weishaupt, J. H., Grabb, M., Canzoniero, L. M., Sensi,  S. L., Sheline, C. T., Monyer, H., and Choi, D. W. ()     -9544</infon><infon key="fpage">9536</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9391008</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>26812</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, S., Lau, L., Wei, J., Zhu, D., Zou, S., Sun, H. S., Fu, Y.,  Liu, F., and Lu, Y. ()     -55</infon><infon key="fpage">43</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15233916</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">43</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>26813</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Noh, K. M., Yokota, H., Mashiko, T., Castillo, P. E., Zukin, R. S.,  and Bennett, M. V. ()    -12235</infon><infon key="fpage">12230</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16093311</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S.  A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">102</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>26814</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, B., Liao, M., Mielke, J. G., Ning, K., Chen, Y., Li, L.,  El-Hayek, Y. H., Gomez, E., Zukin, R. S., Fehlings, M. G., and Wan, Q.  ()     -5319</infon><infon key="fpage">5309</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16707783</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>26815</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Derkach, V. A., Oh, M. C., Guire, E. S., and Soderling, T. R.  ()     -113</infon><infon key="fpage">101</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17237803</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26816</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Collingridge, G. L., Isaac, J. T., and Wang, Y. T.  ()     -962</infon><infon key="fpage">952</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15550950</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>26817</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Cull-Candy, S., Kelly, L., and Farrant, M. ()      -297</infon><infon key="fpage">288</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16713244</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>26818</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kim, C. H., Chung, H. J., Lee, H. K., and Huganir, R. L.  ()     -11730</infon><infon key="fpage">11725</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11573007</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">98</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>26819</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Iwakura, Y., Nagano, T., Kawamura, M., Horikawa, H., Ibaraki, K.,  Takei, N., and Nawa, H. ()    -40032</infon><infon key="fpage">40025</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11498531</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>26820</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hanley, J. G., and Henley, J. M. ()     -3278</infon><infon key="fpage">3266</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16138078</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>26821</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Terashima, A., Cotton, L., Dev, K. K., Meyer, G., Zaman, S.,  Duprat, F., Henley, J. M., Collingridge, G. L., and Isaac, J. T.  ()     -5390</infon><infon key="fpage">5381</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15190111</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>26822</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hanley, J. G., Khatri, L., Hanson, P. I., and Ziff, E. B.  ()     -67</infon><infon key="fpage">53</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11931741</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">34</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>26823</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Greger, I. H., and Esteban, J. A. ()      -297</infon><infon key="fpage">289</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17475474</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Neurobiol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26824</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Shepherd, J. D., and Huganir, R. L. ()      -643</infon><infon key="fpage">613</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17506699</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26825</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Daw, M. I., Chittajallu, R., Bortolotto, Z. A., Dev, K. K., Duprat,  F., Henley, J. M., Collingridge, G. L., and Isaac, J. T. ()     -886</infon><infon key="fpage">873</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11163273</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">28</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>26826</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pellegrini-Giampietro, D. E., Gorter, J. A., Bennett, M. V., and  Zukin, R. S. ()     -470</infon><infon key="fpage">464</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9347614</infon><infon key="source">Trends Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>26827</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Plant, K., Pelkey, K. A., Bortolotto, Z. A., Morita, D., Terashima,  A., McBain, C. J., Collingridge, G. L., and Isaac, J. T. ()     -604</infon><infon key="fpage">602</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16582904</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>26828</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Adesnik, H., and Nicoll, R. A. ()    -4602</infon><infon key="fpage">4598</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17460072</infon><infon key="source">J.  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">27</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26829</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Terashima, A., Pelkey, K. A., Rah, J. C., Suh, Y. H., Roche, K. W.,  Collingridge, G. L., McBain, C. J., and Isaac, J. T. ()     -882</infon><infon key="fpage">872</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18367088</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">57</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>26830</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ho, M. T., Pelkey, K. A., Topolnik, L., Petralia, R. S., Takamiya,  K., Xia, J., Huganir, R. L., Lacaille, J. C., and McBain, C. J.  ()     -11662</infon><infon key="fpage">11651</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17959808</infon><infon key="source">J. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">27</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>26831</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bellone, C., and Luscher, C. ()    -641</infon><infon key="fpage">636</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16582902</infon><infon key="source">Nat.  Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>26832</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hanley, J. G. ()    -160</infon><infon key="fpage">152</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18353440</infon><infon key="source">Pharmacol.  Ther.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">118</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>26833</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Gardner, S. M., Takamiya, K., Xia, J., Suh, J. G., Johnson, R., Yu,  S., and Huganir, R. L. ()     -915</infon><infon key="fpage">903</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15797551</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">45</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>26834</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Liu, S. J., and Cull-Candy, S. G. ()     -775</infon><infon key="fpage">768</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15895086</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Neurosci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>26835</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>26836</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: OGD, oxygen and glucose deprivation; AMPA,  alpha-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid; AMPAR, AMPA  receptor; NMDA, N-methyl-d-aspartic acid; NMDAR, NMDA  receptor; LTP, long term potentiation; LTD, long term depression; EPSC,  excitatory postsynaptic current; NASPM, 1-naphthyl acetyl spermine; PI,  propidium iodide; ABP, AMPAR-binding protein; GRIP, glutamate receptor-binding  protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>27269</offset><text>Invitrogen, Sindbis Expression System Manual, Invitrogen,  Carlsbad, CA.</text></passage></document></collection>
