<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>19332540</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1074/jbc.M901488200</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2685662</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">19332540</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">14809</infon><infon key="fpage">14809</infon><infon key="issue">22</infon><infon key="lpage">14818</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nakamura;given-names:Seiji</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Takamura;given-names:Toshinari</infon><infon key="name_10">surname:Miyamoto;given-names:Ken-ichi</infon><infon key="name_11">surname:Kaneko;given-names:Shuichi</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Matsuzawa-Nagata;given-names:Naoto</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Takayama;given-names:Hiroaki</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Misu;given-names:Hirofumi</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Noda;given-names:Hiroyo</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Nabemoto;given-names:Satoko</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Kurita;given-names:Seiichiro</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Ota;given-names:Tsuguhito</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Ando;given-names:Hitoshi</infon><infon key="p">The on-line version of this article (available at  http://www.jbc.org)  contains supplemental Figs. 1-8.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Palmitate Induces Insulin Resistance in H4IIEC3 Hepatocytes through  Reactive Oxygen Species Produced by  Mitochondria*S</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>121</offset><text>Visceral adiposity in obesity causes excessive free fatty acid (FFA) flux  into the liver via the portal vein and may cause fatty liver disease and  hepatic insulin resistance. However, because animal models of insulin  resistance induced by lipid infusion or a high fat diet are complex and may be  accompanied by alterations not restricted to the liver, it is difficult to  determine the contribution of FFAs to hepatic insulin resistance. Therefore,  we treated H4IIEC3 cells, a rat hepatocyte cell line, with a monounsaturated  fatty acid (oleate) and a saturated fatty acid (palmitate) to investigate the  direct and initial effects of FFAs on hepatocytes. We show that palmitate, but  not oleate, inhibited insulin-stimulated tyrosine phosphorylation of insulin  receptor substrate 2 and serine phosphorylation of Akt, through c-Jun  NH2-terminal kinase (JNK) activation. Among the well established  stimuli for JNK activation, reactive oxygen species (ROS) played a causal role  in palmitate-induced JNK activation. In addition, etomoxir, an inhibitor of  carnitine palmitoyltransferase-1, which is the rate-limiting enzyme in  mitochondrial fatty acid beta-oxidation, as well as inhibitors of the  mitochondrial respiratory chain complex (thenoyltrifluoroacetone and carbonyl  cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone) decreased palmitate-induced ROS  production. Together, our findings in hepatocytes indicate that palmitate  inhibited insulin signal transduction through JNK activation and that  accelerated beta-oxidation of palmitate caused excess electron flux in the  mitochondrial respiratory chain, resulting in increased ROS generation. Thus,  mitochondria-derived ROS induced by palmitate may be major contributors to JNK  activation and cellular insulin resistance.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1897</offset><text>Insulin is the major hormone that inhibits gluconeogenesis in the liver.  Visceral adiposity in obesity causes hepatic steatosis and insulin resistance.  In an insulin-resistant state, impaired insulin action allows enhancement of  glucose production in the liver, resulting in systemic hyperglycemia  (1) and contributing to the  development of type 2 diabetes. In addition, we have demonstrated  experimentally that insulin resistance accelerated the pathology of  steatohepatitis in genetically obese diabetic OLETF rats  (2). In contrast, lipid-induced  oxidative stress caused steatohepatitis and hepatic insulin resistance in mice  (3). In fact, steatosis of the  liver is an independent predictor of insulin resistance in patients with  nonalcoholic fatty liver disease  (4).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2680</offset><text>It remains unclear whether hepatic steatosis causally contributes to  insulin resistance or whether it is merely a resulting pathology. Excessive  dietary free fatty acid  (FFA)2 flux into the  liver via the portal vein may cause fatty liver disease and hepatic insulin  resistance. Indeed, elevated plasma FFA concentrations correlate with obesity  and decreased target tissue insulin sensitivity  (5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3084</offset><text>Experimentally, lipid infusion or a high fat diet that increases  circulating FFA levels promotes insulin resistance in the liver. Candidate  events linking FFA to insulin resistance in vivo are the  up-regulation of SREBP-1c (6),  inflammation caused by activation of c-Jun amino-terminal kinase (JNK)  (7) or IKKbeta  (8), endoplasmic reticulum (ER)  stress (9), ceramide  (10,  11), and TRB3  (12).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3486</offset><text>However, which event is the direct and initial target of FFA in the liver  is unclear. Insulin resistance induced by lipid infusion or a high fat diet is  complex and may be accompanied by alterations not restricted to the liver,  making it difficult to determine the contribution of FFAs to hepatic insulin  resistance. For example, hyperinsulinemia and hyperglycemia secondary to the  initial event also may contribute to the development of diet-induced insulin  resistance in vivo  (6).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3976</offset><text>To address the early event(s) triggering the development of high fat diet-  or obesity-induced insulin resistance, we investigated the molecular  mechanism(s) underlying the direct action of FFA on hepatocytes to cause  insulin resistance in vitro, using the rat hepatocyte cell line  H4IIEC3. We found that mitochondria-derived reactive oxygen species (ROS) were  a cause of palmitate-induced insulin resistance in hepatocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>4405</offset><text>Effects of palmitate and oleate on insulin-stimulated tyrosine  phosphorylation of IRS-2 and serine phosphorylation of Akt and GSK-3 in  H4IIEC3 hepatocytes. A, H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the  presence or absence of palmitate (Pal) or oleate (Ole) for  16 h prior to stimulation with insulin (1 ng/ml, 15 min). Total cell lysates  were resolved by SDS-PAGE, transferred to a PVDF membrane, and immunoblotted  (IB) with the indicated antibodies. Total cell lysates were subjected  to immunoprecipitation (IP) with phosphotyrosine antibody prior to  SDS-PAGE to examine tyrosine phosphorylation of IRS-2. Detection was by  enhanced chemiluminescence. Representative blots are shown. B, the  values from densitometry of three (p-IRS-2), eight (p-Akt), or five  (p-GSK-3alpha) independent experiments were normalized to the level of total  IRS-2, Akt, or GSK-3alpha protein, respectively, and expressed as the mean  -fold increase over control +- S.E. *, p &lt; 0.05  versus insulin treatment alone. **, p &lt; 0.01  versus insulin treatment alone.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>5449</offset><text>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5473</offset><text>Materials:The antibody against IRS-2 was purchased from  Upstate Biotechnology, Inc. (Lake Placid, NY). Antibodies against  phosphotyrosine, Akt, phospho-Akt (Ser473), stress-activated  protein kinase/JNK, phospho-stress-activated protein kinase/JNK  (Thr183/Tyr185), and phospho-GSK (glycogen synthase  kinase)-3 (Ser21/9) were purchased from Cell Signaling Technology  (Beverly, MA). Antibodies against GSK-3 and phospho-c-Jun were from Santa Cruz  Biotechnology, Inc. (Santa Cruz, CA). Insulin from porcine pancreas, sodium  palmitate, sodium oleate, myriocin, N-acetyl-l-cysteine,  rotenone, thenoyltrifluoroacetone, cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone,  oxypurinol, etomoxir, and tunicamycin was obtained from Sigma. SP600125 and  apocynin were from Calbiochem. dl-alpha-tocopherol and  2',7'-dichlorofluorescin diacetate (H2DCFDA) were from  Wako (Osaka, Japan).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>6338</offset><text>Effects of palmitate and oleate on JNK activation in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes. A, H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the presence or  absence of FFAs (palmitate (Pal) or oleate (Ole)) and the  JNK inhibitor SP600125 (SP) for 16 h. Total cell lysates were  resolved by SDS-PAGE, transferred to a PVDF membrane, and immunoblotted with  the indicated antibodies. Detection was by enhanced chemiluminescence.  Representative blots are shown. B, the values from densitometry of  four (p-JNK) independent experiments were normalized to the level of total JNK  (p-c-Jun was not normalized; n = 4) and expressed as the mean -fold  increase over control +- S.E. **, p &lt; 0.01 versus  control.   , p &lt; 0.01 versus palmitate  treatment.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7056</offset><text>Cell Culture and Fatty Acid Treatment:Studies were performed  in the rat hepatoma cell line H4IIEC3, purchased from the American Type  Culture Collection (Manassas, VA). Cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified  Eagle's medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum  (Invitrogen), penicillin (100 units/ml), and streptomycin (0.1 mg/ml;  Invitrogen). The cells were cultured at 37  C in a humidified atmosphere  containing 5% CO2, with medium changes three times a week. All  studies were conducted using 80-90% confluent cells, which were treated  with the indicated concentrations of FFAs in the presence of 2% FFA-free  bovine serum albumin (Sigma).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7726</offset><text>Cell Harvest and Western Blot Analysis:H4IIEC3 hepatocytes,  grown to 80-90% confluence in 6-well plates, were treated with the  indicated reagents for 16 h in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium. After  treatment, the cells were stimulated with insulin (1 ng/ml) for 15 min. Then  the cells were washed with ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline and lysed in  buffer containing 20 mm Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 5 mm EDTA, 1%  Nonidet P-40, 2 mm Na3VO4, 100 mm  NaF, and a protease inhibitor mixture (Sigma). After sonication with a  Bioruptor (Cosmo Bio, Tokyo, Japan), the lysates were centrifuged to remove  insoluble materials. The supernatants (10 mug/lane) were separated by  SDS-PAGE and transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride membranes (Millipore,  Billerica, MA). For detection of phosphotyrosine insulin receptor and  phosphotyrosine IRS-2, the supernatants (400 mugof protein) were  immunoprecipitated with a phosphotyrosine antibody and protein G beads for 2 h  at 4  C before SDS-PAGE. The membranes were blocked in a buffer containing  5% nonfat milk, 50 mm Tris (pH 7.6), 150 mm NaCl, and  0.1% Tween 20 (TBS-T) for 1 h at room temperature. They were then incubated  with specific primary antibodies and subsequently with horseradish  peroxidase-linked secondary antibodies. Signals were detected with a  chemiluminescence detection system (ECL Plus Western blotting detection  reagents; GE Healthcare). Densitometric analysis was conducted directly on the  blotted membrane, using a CCD camera system (LAS-3000 Mini; Fujifilm, Tokyo,  Japan) and Scion Image software.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9302</offset><text>Quantitative Real Time PCR:Total RNA was extracted from  cultured H4IIEC3 hepatocytes using an RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen, Germantown,  MD), according to the manufacturer's protocol. The cDNA was synthesized from  total RNA (100 ng) using random hexamer primers, N6, and a high  capacity cDNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA).  Quantitative real time PCR was performed with an ABI Prism 7900HT (Applied  Biosystems). The set of specific primers and TaqMan probes in the present  study was obtained from Applied Biosystems. The PCR conditions were one cycle  at 50  C for 2 min and 95  C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles at 95   C for 15 s and 60  C for 1 min.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9991</offset><text>Analysis of XBP-1 (X-box-binding Protein-1) mRNA  Splicing:Total RNA was extracted from H4IIEC3 hepatocytes, and cDNA  was synthesized as described above. The cDNA was amplified with a pair of  primers (reverse 5'-CCA TGG GAA GAT GTT CTG GG-3' and forward  5'-ACA CGC TTG GGG ATG AAT GC-3') corresponding to the rat XBP-1  cDNA. The PCR conditions were initial denaturation at 94  C for 3 min,  followed by 30 cycles of amplification (94  C for 30 s, 58  C for 30  s, 72  C for 30 s) and a final extension at 72  C for 3 min. The PCR  products were separated by 2.5% agarose gel electrophoresis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>10587</offset><text>Effect of a JNK inhibitor on palmitate-induced alterations in  insulin-stimulated phosphorylation of Akt and GSK-3 in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes. A, H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the presence or  absence of palmitate (Pal) and the JNK inhibitor SP600125  (SP) for 16 h prior to stimulation with insulin (1 ng/ml, 15 min).  Total cell lysates were resolved by SDS-PAGE, transferred to a PVDF membrane,  and immunoblotted with the indicated antibodies. Detection was enhanced by  chemiluminescence. Representative blots are shown. B, the values from  densitometry of four (p-Akt or p-GSK-3) independent experiments were  normalized to the level of total Akt or GSK-3 protein, respectively, and  expressed as the mean -fold increase over control +- S.E. **, p  &lt; 0.01 versus palmitate treatment.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11376</offset><text>Measurement of Intracellular ROS:The intracellular formation  of ROS was detected using the fluorescent probe H2DCFDA, according  to a published method (13).  Briefly, H4IIEC3 hepatocytes, grown to 70-80% confluence in 96-well  plates, were treated with the indicated reagents in Dulbecco's modified  Eagle's medium for 8 h. After treatment, the cells were washed with  phosphate-buffered saline, loaded with 10 mum H2DCFDA,  and incubated for 30 min at 37  C. The fluorescence was analyzed using a  plate reader (Fluoroskan Ascent FL, ThermoLab Systems, Franklin, MA).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11946</offset><text>Measurement of Protein Carbonyls:The cellular concentration  of proteins containing carbonyl groups (those that react with  2,4-di-nitrophenylhydrazine to form the corresponding hydrazone) was  determined spectrophotometrically using a protein carbonyl assay kit (Cayman  Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI) according to the manufacturer's instructions and as  described previously (14).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12323</offset><text>Statistical Analysis:All values are given as means +-  S.E. Differences between two groups were assessed using unpaired, two-tailed  t tests. Data involving more than two groups were assessed by one-way  analysis of variance. All calculations were performed with SPSS (version 12.0  for Windows; SPSS, Chicago, IL).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>12639</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12647</offset><text>Palmitate Inhibited Insulin Receptor-mediated Signaling:Two  long chain fatty acids were chosen for the study: palmitate, a C16:0 saturated  fatty acid, and oleate, a C18:1 monounsaturated fatty acid. To examine whether  FFAs impaired insulin signal transduction in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes, we assessed  the effect of FFAs on insulin-stimulated tyrosine phosphorylation of IRS-2 and  serine phosphorylation of Akt and GSK-3alpha  (Fig. 1). Incubation with 0.25  mm palmitate inhibited insulin-stimulated tyrosine phosphorylation  of IRS-2 by 40% in H4IIEC3 cells. Downstream of IRS-2, insulin-stimulated  serine phosphorylation of Akt and GSK-3alpha were also inhibited by 0.25  mm palmitate treatment, by 80 and 70%, respectively, indicating an  insulin-resistant state. However, the protein levels of total IRS-2, Akt, and  GSK-3 were unaffected by palmitate. Furthermore, we confirmed that palmitate,  but not oleate, impaired insulin-stimulated Akt serine phosphorylation in the  human hepatoma cell line HepG2 (supplemental Fig. 1).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13681</offset><text>JNK Activation by Palmitate Contributes to Palmitate-induced Insulin  Resistance:JNK, a stress-activated protein kinase, has been  reported to phosphorylate IRS-1 and -2 at serine residues  (15,  16). Serine phosphorylation of  IRSs impairs IRS tyrosine phosphorylation, leading to a reduction in insulin  receptor-mediated signaling. Many studies have verified the role of JNK in  fat-induced insulin resistance in several experimental systems  (7,  17,  18). Thus, we next examined  the effect of FFAs on JNK activation and its involvement in insulin signaling.  Palmitate, but not oleate, dramatically increased phosphorylated JNK and c-Jun  (Fig. 2). A potent and  selective inhibitor of JNK, SP600125  (19), reversed the  palmitate-induced phosphorylation of c-Jun  (Fig. 2), suggesting that  palmitate activated JNK. To test whether palmitate-induced JNK activation  mediated cellular insulin resistance, we inhibited the JNK pathway with  SP600125. SP600125 dose-dependently improved insulin-stimulated serine  phosphorylation of Akt and GSK-3 in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes exposed to palmitate  (Fig. 3). These results suggest  that JNK activation by palmitate contributed to palmitate-induced insulin  resistance.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>14897</offset><text>Effect of palmitate on oxidative stress in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes.  H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the presence or absence of palmitate  (Pal) or oleate (Ole) for 8 h. Intracellular ROS production  was quantified using the fluorescent probe H2DCFDA. The values are  expressed as mean -fold increase over control +- S.E. (n = 4).  **, p &lt; 0.01 versus control.   , p  &lt; 0.01 versus 0.25 mm palmitate treatment.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15304</offset><text>Pathways for SREBP-1c and ER Stress Are Not Involved in  Palmitate-induced JNK Activation and Insulin Resistance in H4IIEC3  Hepatocytes:The SREBP-1c pathway has been reported to play a role  in diet-induced insulin resistance in vivo. Ide et al.  (6) found that high sucrose  diet-induced hyperglycemia and hyperinsulinemia up-regulated hepatic  expression of SREBP-1c, leading to down-regulation of IRS-2 at the  transcriptional level. However, in the present study, palmitate dramatically  down-regulated the expression of SREBP-1c in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes (supplemental  Fig. 2). Consistent with this, the mRNA (supplemental Fig. 2) and protein  (Fig. 1) levels of IRS-2 were  unaffected by palmitate. Thus, palmitate itself did not appear to cause  insulin resistance in hepatocytes via the SREBP-1c pathway.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>16116</offset><text>Effects of antioxidants on palmitate-induced intracellular ROS  production in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes. H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the  presence or absence of palmitate (Pal) and antioxidants for 8 h.  Intracellular ROS production was quantified using the fluorescent probe  H2DCFDA. The values are expressed as mean -fold increase over  control +- S.E. (n = 4). *, p &lt; 0.05  versus palmitate treatment alone. **, p &lt; 0.01  versus palmitate treatment alone. NAC,  N-acetyl-l-cysteine; Toc, alpha-tocopherol.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16624</offset><text>ER stress is induced in insulin-resistant states, such as obesity and type  2 diabetes, and in turn, this stress has been shown to lead to the inhibition  of insulin signaling, through overactivation of JNK  (9). Since excessive FFAs have  been shown to trigger ER stress in pancreatic beta-cells  (20), we examined whether  palmitate caused ER stress in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes. ER stress induces the  spliced form of XBP-1 (XBP-1s), which up-regulates the transcription of  molecular chaperones, including GRP78 (78-kDa glucose-regulated/binding  immunoglobulin protein) (21).  Palmitate at 0.25 mm did not alter the expression level of GRP78  mRNA or the splicing pattern of XBP-1, unlike tunicamycin, an agent commonly  used to induce ER stress (supplemental Fig. 3). Next, we compared the impact  of palmitate and tunicamycin on insulin-stimulated signal transduction and JNK  activation (supplemental Fig. 4). The inhibitory effect of tunicamycin on  insulin-stimulated serine phosphorylation of Akt was mild and not significant  compared with that of palmitate. Additionally, the increment in phosphorylated  JNK by tunicamycin was lower and not significant compared with that of  palmitate. These results suggest that ER stress played a minor role in  palmitate-induced JNK activation and cellular insulin resistance in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17970</offset><text>Palmitate Induces ROS Production:In addition to ER stress,  increased cellular ROS levels are known to stimulate threonine phosphorylation  of JNK (22). Indeed, ROS  levels are increased in clinical conditions associated with insulin  resistance, such as sepsis, burn injuries, obesity, and type 2 diabetes  (23). Furthermore, FFAs have  been reported to generate ROS in various cells, such as pancreatic islet cells  (24), cardiac myocytes  (25), and adipocytes  (23).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>18440</offset><text>Effects of antioxidants on palmitate-induced alterations in  insulin-stimulated serine phosphorylation of Akt in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes.  A, H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the presence or absence of  palmitate (Pal) and antioxidants for 16 h prior to stimulation with  insulin (1 ng/ml, 15 min). Total cell lysates were resolved by SDS-PAGE,  transferred to a PVDF membrane, and immunoblotted with the indicated  antibodies. Detection was by enhanced chemiluminescence. Representative blots  are shown. B, the values from densitometry of four (NAC) or five  (alpha-tocopherol) independent experiments were normalized to the level of  total Akt protein and expressed as the mean -fold increase over control  +- S.E. *, p &lt; 0.05 versus palmitate treatment.  NAC, N-acetyl-l-cysteine; Toc,  alpha-tocopherol.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19244</offset><text>Thus, we hypothesized that palmitate increased intracellular ROS production  and thereby activated JNK, leading to the impaired insulin signaling. To  evaluate this, H4IIEC3 hepatocytes were incubated with H2DCFDA, a  fluorescent probe, to visualize intracellular ROS, with or without palmitate.  H2DCFDA-associated fluorescence was elevated by 58% after  incubation with 0.25 mm palmitate for 8 h, and palmitate induced  more ROS production than oleate (Fig.  4). Consistent with this, the amount of protein carbonyls, a  marker of oxidative stress, significantly increased in palmitate-treated  hepatocytes (4.6 +- 0.5 nmol/mg protein), compared with control cells  (3.1 +- 0.4 nmol/mg protein). These results suggest that FFAs,  especially palmitate, can cause ROS production and oxidative stress in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20069</offset><text>Antioxidants Prevent Palmitate-induced Insulin Resistance:We  next sought to test whether palmitate-induced ROS overproduction had a causal  role in insulin resistance by assessing whether two antioxidant reagents,  N-acetyl-l-cysteine (NAC) and alpha-tocopherol, could  also act as insulin sensitizers. NAC and alpha-tocopherol dose-dependently  suppressed palmitate-induced intracellular ROS production; NAC at 10  mm and alpha-tocopherol at 0.4 mm suppressed ROS  production by 50 and 60%, respectively  (Fig. 5). In parallel with  decreased ROS levels, the antioxidants recovered the insulin-stimulated Akt  phosphorylation impaired by palmitate; NAC at 10 mm and  alpha-tocopherol at 0.4 mm recovered the phosphorylation by 40  and 35%, respectively (Fig. 6).  Furthermore, these antioxidants suppressed palmitate-induced JNK  phosphorylation; NAC at 10 mm and alpha-tocopherol at 0.4  mm suppressed it by 80 and 55%, respectively  (Fig. 7). These results suggest  that palmitate increased ROS levels in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes and thereby  activated JNK, resulting in insulin resistance.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21159</offset><text>Palmitate Induces ROS Overproduction in Mitochondria:To  define the source of ROS induced by palmitate in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes, we  examined the cellular pathway involved in ROS production, including NADPH  oxidase, xanthine oxidase, and mitochondria-mediated pathways.  Palmitate-induced ROS production was markedly suppressed by rotenone, an  inhibitor of mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I;  thenoyltrifluoroacetone, an inhibitor of mitochondrial respiratory chain  complex II; and carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenylhydrazone, an  uncoupler of oxidative phosphorylation  (Fig. 8). In contrast, ROS  production in palmitate-treated H4IIEC3 cells was not suppressed by apocynin,  an inhibitor of NADPH oxidase, or oxypurinol, an inhibitor of xanthine  oxidase. These results suggest that the mitochondrial respiratory chain is  involved in palmitate-induced ROS overproduction in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22064</offset><text>Palmitate Increases ROS through the Mitochondrial Fatty Acid  beta-Oxidation Respiratory Chain:FFAs are metabolized in the  mitochondrial fatty acid beta-oxidation pathway, which supplies the  mitochondrial respiratory chain with electrons. Large amounts of electrons  entering the respiratory chain may cause abnormal reduction of oxygen, leading  to ROS production. Thus, we next examined whether palmitate-induced ROS  production was dependent on mitochondrial fatty acid beta-oxidation. CPT-1a  (carnitine palmitoyltransferase-1a) is the rate-limiting enzyme in  mitochondrial fatty acid beta-oxidation. As expected, etomoxir, a CPT-1  inhibitor, decreased palmitate-induced ROS production, by 80%  (Fig. 9A).  Furthermore, palmitate, but not oleate, significantly increased expression of  the CPT-1a gene (Fig.  9B). This up-regulation may contribute to  palmitate-induced ROS overproduction, because the accelerated beta-oxidation  should cause excessive electron flux in the respiratory chain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>23065</offset><text>Effects of antioxidants on palmitate-induced JNK activation in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes. A, H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the presence or  absence of palmitate (Pal) and antioxidants for 16 h. Total cell  lysates were resolved by SDS-PAGE, transferred to a PVDF membrane, and  immunoblotted with the indicated antibodies. Detection was by enhanced  chemiluminescence. Representative blots are shown. B, the values from  densitometry of four (NAC oralpha-tocopherol) independent experiments were  normalized to the level of total JNK protein and expressed as the mean -fold  increase over control +- S.E. **, p &lt; 0.01 versus  palmitate treatment alone. Toc, alpha-tocopherol.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>23738</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23749</offset><text>In the present study, we investigated the direct action of fatty acids on  insulin signaling in hepatocytes. The saturated fatty acid palmitate, but not  the unsaturated fatty acid oleate, impaired insulin-induced tyrosine  phosphorylation of IRS-2, serine phosphorylation of Akt, and serine  phosphorylation of GSK-3alpha, all of which are indicative of insulin  resistance in cultured H4IIEC3 hepatocytes  (Fig. 10). Unlike in  vivo findings (6), the  expression of the SREBP-1c gene was down-regulated by adding  palmitate to cultured H4IIEC3 hepatocytes, which is likely a result of a  negative feedback loop for fatty acid synthesis, and IRS-2 protein levels were  unaffected. FFA-induced insulin resistance has been reported in other  insulin-sensitive cells, such as adipocytes  (18) and skeletal muscle cells  (26). These studies, together  with the present results, suggest that FFA inhibits insulin signaling at the  level of tyrosine phosphorylation of IRSs, regardless of cell type. Similar to  the findings in 3T3-L1 adipocytes  (18) and primary mouse  hepatocytes and pancreatic beta-cells  (16), the activation of JNK, a  known suppressor of the tyrosine phosphorylation of IRSs, was involved in  FFA-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of IRS-2 in cultured H4IIEC3 hepatocytes.  Because a JNK inhibitor, SP600125, largely restored palmitate-induced  impairment of the insulin signaling pathway, JNK activation seems to play a  major role in the development of palmitate-induced insulin resistance in  H4IIEC3 hepatocytes. Our results support in vivo findings that JNK is  activated in the liver of an animal model of obesity and diabetes in which FFA  influx into the liver is elevated  (9,  27). The overexpression of JNK  in mouse liver resulted in hepatic insulin resistance at the level of IRS  tyrosine phosphorylation, and the overexpression of a dominant negative mutant  of JNK in the liver accelerated hepatic insulin signaling  (17).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25706</offset><text>Given that JNK is activated by many types of cellular stresses  (28), we next searched for a  link between palmitate treatment and JNK activation in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes. ER  stress was unlikely to mediate palmitate-induced insulin resistance in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes, because palmitate caused insulin resistance independent of ER  stress, whereas tunicamycin caused ER stress without affecting insulin action.  Instead, we found that palmitate-induced ROS generation mediated insulin  resistance. ROS are one of many factors suggested to have a possible role in  insulin resistance (29,  30). ROS include reactive  products, such as superoxide anion, hydrogen peroxide, and hydroxyl radical,  which are formed as by-products of mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation  (OXPHOS). Thus, as a rule, increased mitochondrial OXPHOS flux leads to  increased formation of ROS  (31,  32). ROS can also be produced  during beta-oxidation of fatty acids, especially as a by-product of  peroxisomal acyl-CoA oxidase activity  (32). Additionally, ROS can be  produced by dedicated enzymes, such as NADPH oxidase  (33), present in phagocytic  cells, where ROS are an important part of cellular defense mechanisms. Using  specific inhibitors of subcellular ROS, we identified mitochondrial OXPHOS as  an important source of palmitate-induced ROS generation in H4IIEC3  hepatocytes. FFAs supply mitochondrial OXPHOS with electrons through  mitochondrial fatty acid beta-oxidation. A final metabolite of fatty acids,  acetyl-CoA, is metabolized in the trichloroacetic acid cycle. In the processes  of fatty acid beta-oxidation and the trichloroacetic acid cycle, NADH and  FADH2 are generated and could supply excessive electrons for  OXPHOS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>27432</offset><text>Effects of ROS-producing pathway inhibitors on palmitate-induced ROS  production in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes. H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the  presence or absence of palmitate (Pal) and each ROS-producing pathway  inhibitor for 8 h. Intracellular ROS production was quantified using the  fluorescent probe H2DCFDA. The values are expressed as mean -fold  increase over control +- S.E. (n = 4). *, p &lt; 0.05  versus palmitate treatment alone. **, p &lt; 0.01  versus palmitate treatment alone. Rot, rotenone;  Apo, apocynin; Oxy, oxypurinol; TTFA,  thenoyltrifluoroacetone; CCCP, carbonyl cyanide  m-chlorophenylhydrazone.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>28049</offset><text>Involvement of mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation in palmitate-induced  ROS production. A, H4IIEC3 cells were incubated in the presence  or absence of palmitate (Pal) and the CPT-1 inhibitor etomoxir  (Eto) for 8 h. Intracellular ROS production was quantified using the  fluorescent probe H2DCFDA. The values are expressed as mean -fold  increase over control +- S.E. (n = 4). B, H4IIEC3  cells were incubated in the presence or absence of palmitate (Pal) or  oleate (Ole) for 16 h. Total RNA was extracted and subjected to  reverse transcription. Using the cDNA as a template, the amounts of CPT-1 mRNA  were detected by real time PCR. The values were normalized to the level of 18  S ribosomal RNA and expressed as mean -fold increase over control +-  S.E. (n = 3). *, p &lt; 0.05 versus control. **,  p &lt; 0.01 versus palmitate treatment alone.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28893</offset><text>NAC, a scavenger of ROS, dose-dependently restored glutathione in  palmitate-treated cells (supplemental Fig. 5). However, glutathione  restoration by NAC was unable to completely rescue palmitate-induced insulin  resistance. Furthermore, the combination of NAC and alpha-tocopherol did not  completely reverse JNK activation (supplemental Fig. 6, A and  B) and only partly rescued palmitate-induced insulin resistance  (supplemental Fig. 7, A and B). Therefore, other mechanisms  may also be involved in insulin resistance caused by palmitate.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29438</offset><text>De novo ceramide synthesis is a potential pathway contributing to  palmitate-induced JNK activation. Ceramide derived from saturated fatty acids  has been reported to activate JNK and inhibit insulin-induced Akt  phosphorylation in myocytes  (34-36).  In our investigation, palmitate increased the intracellular content of  ceramide in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes (supplemental Fig. 8). Unfortunately, even at  the maximum myriosin concentration, the intracellular accumulation of ceramide  was not blocked by myriosin, a potent inhibitor of serine palmitoyltransferase  at the first step in ceramide biosynthesis (supplemental Fig. 8). Furthermore,  ceramide accumulation was not blocked when myriosin was used in combination  with fumonisin B1, an inhibitor of ceramide synthase (data not shown).  Therefore, we cannot rule out the possibility that intracellular ceramide  contributes to palmitate-induced insulin resistance in H4IIEC3 hepatocytes.  Further studies are required to assess the role of the ceramide pathway in  palmitate-induced insulin resistance in hepatocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>30511</offset><text>Proposed model for palmitate-induced hepatic insulin resistance.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30576</offset><text>In the present study, etomoxir, an inhibitor of CPT-1, decreased  palmitate-induced intracellular ROS production. Additionally, palmitate, but  not oleate, significantly increased the expression of the CPT-1a  gene, which may account for the observed differences in insulin action between  palmitate and oleate.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30888</offset><text>Recently, it was reported that fatty acid composition may be a determinant  in insulin sensitivity (37,  38). In this regard, we  investigated the effect of oleate on insulin signaling in palmitate-treated  hepatocytes. Surprisingly, oleate dose-dependently reversed palmitate-induced  ROS generation and JNK phosphorylation and rescued palmitate-induced  phosphorylation of  Akt.3 Further  investigations aimed at elucidating the molecular basis underlying the  differential roles and interactions of FFAs are required.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31409</offset><text>In conclusion, this study identified mitochondrial ROS generation as a  critical factor in palmitate-induced hepatic insulin resistance. Palmitate may  induce CPT-1 expression, accelerate metabolism, supply excess electrons for  mitochondrial OXPHOS, and generate ROS. ROS then desensitize the insulin  signaling pathway by activating JNK, impairing tyrosine phosphorylation of  IRS-2, and causing hepatic insulin resistance  (Fig. 10). The results suggest  that an initial event in high fat/sucrose diet-induced or obesity-induced  insulin resistance in the liver is mitochondrial ROS generation, which could  potentially be a therapeutic target. In addition to previously suggested JNK  inhibitors or antioxidants, mitochondrial uncouplers, such as cyanide  m-chlorophenylhydrazone, may provide a candidate therapeutic strategy  for this pathway by preventing ROS generation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>32287</offset><text>Supplementary Material</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32310</offset><text>   </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32314</offset><text>  </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Saltiel, A. R., and Kahn, C. R. ()     -806</infon><infon key="fpage">799</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11742412</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">414</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>32317</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ota, T., Takamura, T., Kurita, S., Matsuzawa, N., Kita, Y., Uno,  M., Akahori, H., Misu, H., Sakurai, M., Zen, Y., Nakanuma, Y., and Kaneko, S.  ()     -293</infon><infon key="fpage">282</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17241878</infon><infon key="source">Gastroenterology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">132</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>32318</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Matsuzawa, N., Takamura, T., Kurita, S., Misu, H., Ota, T., Ando,  H., Yokoyama, M., Honda, M., Zen, Y., Nakanuma, Y., Miyamoto, K., and Kaneko,  S. ()     -1403</infon><infon key="fpage">1392</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17929294</infon><infon key="source">Hepatology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">46</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>32319</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sakurai, M., Takamura, T., Ota, T., Ando, H., Akahori, H., Kaji,  K., Sasaki, M., Nakanuma, Y., Miura, K., and Kaneko, S. ()     -317</infon><infon key="fpage">312</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17464461</infon><infon key="source">J. Gastroenterol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">42</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>32320</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Boden, G. ()     -10</infon><infon key="fpage">3</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8971073</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">46</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>32321</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ide, T., Shimano, H., Yahagi, N., Matsuzaka, T., Nakakuki, M.,  Yamamoto, T., Nakagawa, Y., Takahashi, A., Suzuki, H., Sone, H., Toyoshima,  H., Fukamizu, A., and Yamada, N. ()    -357</infon><infon key="fpage">351</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15048126</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Cell  Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>32322</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Hirosumi, J., Tuncman, G., Chang, L., Gorgun, C. Z., Uysal, K. T.,  Maeda, K., Karin, M., and Hotamisligil, G. S. ()     -336</infon><infon key="fpage">333</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12447443</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">420</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>32323</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Boden, G., She, P., Mozzoli, M., Cheung, P., Gumireddy, K., Reddy,  P., Xiang, X., Luo, Z., and Ruderman, N. ()     -3465</infon><infon key="fpage">3458</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16306362</infon><infon key="source">Diabetes</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">54</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>32324</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Ozcan, U., Cao, Q., Yilmaz, E., Lee, A. H., Iwakoshi, N. N.,  Ozdelen, E., Tuncman, G., Gorgun, C., Glimcher, L. H., and Hotamisligil, G. S.  ()     -461</infon><infon key="fpage">457</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15486293</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">306</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>32325</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kim, J. K., Fillmore, J. J., Chen, Y., Yu, C., Moore, I. K.,  Pypaert, M., Lutz, E. P., Kako, Y., Velez-Carrasco, W., Goldberg, I. J.,  Breslow, J. L., and Shulman, G. I. ()    -7527</infon><infon key="fpage">7522</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11390966</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl.  Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">98</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>32326</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Turinsky, J., O'Sullivan, D. M., and Bayly, B. P.  ()     -16885</infon><infon key="fpage">16880</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2211599</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">265</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>32327</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Du, K., Herzig, S., Kulkarni, R. N., and Montminy, M.  ()     -1577</infon><infon key="fpage">1574</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12791994</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">300</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>32328</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nishikawa, T., Edelstein, D., Du, X. L., Yamagishi, S., Matsumura,  T., Kaneda, Y., Yorek, M. A., Beebe, D., Oates, P. J., Hammes, H. P.,  Giardino, I., and Brownlee, M. ()     -790</infon><infon key="fpage">787</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10783895</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">404</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>32329</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Matsuzawa-Nagata, N., Takamura, T., Ando, H., Nakamura, S., Kurita,  S., Misu, H., Ota, T., Yokoyama, M., Honda, M., Miyamoto, K., and Kaneko, S.  ()     -1077</infon><infon key="fpage">1071</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18640384</infon><infon key="source">Metabolism</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">57</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>32330</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Aguirre, V., Uchida, T., Yenush, L., Davis, R., and White, M. F.  ()     -9054</infon><infon key="fpage">9047</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10722755</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">275</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>32331</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Solinas, G., Naugler, W., Galimi, F., Lee, M. S., and Karin, M.  ()     -16459</infon><infon key="fpage">16454</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17050683</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>32332</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nakatani, Y., Kaneto, H., Kawamori, D., Hatazaki, M., Miyatsuka,  T., Matsuoka, T. A., Kajimoto, Y., Matsuhisa, M., Yamasaki, Y., and Hori, M.  ()     -45809</infon><infon key="fpage">45803</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15331609</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>32333</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nguyen, M. T., Satoh, H., Favelyukis, S., Babendure, J. L.,  Imamura, T., Sbodio, J. I., Zalevsky, J., Dahiyat, B. I., Chi, N. W., and  Olefsky, J. M. ()     -35371</infon><infon key="fpage">35361</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16085647</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">280</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>32334</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bennett, B. L., Sasaki, D. T., Murray, B. W., O'Leary, E. C.,  Sakata, S. T., Xu, W., Leisten, J. C., Motiwala, A., Pierce, S., Satoh, Y.,  Bhagwat, S. S., Manning, A. M., and Anderson, D. W. ()      -13686</infon><infon key="fpage">13681</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11717429</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">98</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>32335</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Karaskov, E., Scott, C., Zhang, L., Teodoro, T., Ravazzola, M., and  Volchuk, A. ()     -3407</infon><infon key="fpage">3398</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16601139</infon><infon key="source">Endocrinology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">147</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>32336</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Harding, H. P., Calfon, M., Urano, F., Novoa, I., and Ron, D.  ()     -599</infon><infon key="fpage">575</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12142265</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>32337</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Kaneto, H., Kawamori, D., Nakatani, Y., Gorogawa, S., and Matsuoka,  T. A. ()     -453</infon><infon key="fpage">447</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15514704</infon><infon key="source">Drug News Perspect.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>32338</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Furukawa, S., Fujita, T., Shimabukuro, M., Iwaki, M., Yamada, Y.,  Nakajima, Y., Nakayama, O., Makishima, M., Matsuda, M., and Shimomura, I.  ()     -1761</infon><infon key="fpage">1752</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15599400</infon><infon key="source">J. Clin. Invest.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">114</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>32339</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Carlsson, C., Borg, L. A., and Welsh, N. ()     -3428</infon><infon key="fpage">3422</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10433196</infon><infon key="source">Endocrinology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">140</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>32340</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Miller, T. A., LeBrasseur, N. K., Cote, G. M., Trucillo, M. P.,  Pimentel, D. R., Ido, Y., Ruderman, N. B., and Sawyer, D. B.  ()     -315</infon><infon key="fpage">309</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16126172</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">336</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>32341</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chavez, J. A., and Summers, S. A. ()      -109</infon><infon key="fpage">101</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14592453</infon><infon key="source">Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">419</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>32342</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Nakatani, Y., Kaneto, H., Kawamori, D., Yoshiuchi, K., Hatazaki,  M., Matsuoka, T. A., Ozawa, K., Ogawa, S., Hori, M., Yamasaki, Y., and  Matsuhisa, M. ()     -851</infon><infon key="fpage">847</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15509553</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">280</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><offset>32343</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Davis, R. J. ()     -252</infon><infon key="fpage">239</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11057897</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>32344</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Evans, J. L., Goldfine, I. D., Maddux, B. A., and Grodsky, G. M.  ()     -622</infon><infon key="fpage">599</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12372842</infon><infon key="source">Endocr. Rev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>32345</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Houstis, N., Rosen, E. D., and Lander, E. S. ()     -948</infon><infon key="fpage">944</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16612386</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">440</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>32346</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Brownlee, M. ()     -820</infon><infon key="fpage">813</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11742414</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">414</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>32347</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Osmundsen, H., Bremer, J., and Pedersen, J. I. ()      -158</infon><infon key="fpage">141</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1892883</infon><infon key="source">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1085</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>32348</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">De Minicis, S., Bataller, R., and Brenner, D. A.  ()     -275</infon><infon key="fpage">272</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16831609</infon><infon key="source">Gastroenterology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">131</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><offset>32349</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Chavez, J. A., Knotts, T. A., Wang, L. P., Li, G., Dobrowsky, R.  T., Florant, G. L., and Summers, S. A. ()    -10303</infon><infon key="fpage">10297</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12525490</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol.  Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><offset>32350</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Powell, D. J., Turban, S., Gray, A., Hajduch, E., and Hundal, H. S.  ()     -629</infon><infon key="fpage">619</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15193147</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">382</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><offset>32351</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Schmitz-Peiffer, C., Craig, D. L., and Biden, T. J.  ()     -24210</infon><infon key="fpage">24202</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10446195</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>32352</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Bruce, C. R., and Febbraio, M. A. ()     -1138</infon><infon key="fpage">1137</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17917654</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Med.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><offset>32353</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Cao, H., Gerhold, K., Mayers, J. R., Wiest, M. M., Watkins, S. M.,  and Hotamisligil, G. S. ()     -944</infon><infon key="fpage">933</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18805087</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">134</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><offset>32354</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>32355</offset><text>The abbreviations used are: FFA, free fatty acid; IRS, insulin receptor  substrate; JNK, c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase; ER, endoplasmic  reticulum; ROS, reactive oxygen species; NAC,  N-acetyl-l-cysteine; H2DCFDA,  2',7'-dichlorofluorescin diacetate; OXPHOS, oxidative  phosphorylation; PVDF, polyvinylidene difluoride.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>32671</offset><text>H. Takayama and T. Takamura, unpublished data.</text></passage></document></collection>
