<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20130316</date><key>pmc.key</key><document><id>9813088</id><passage><infon key="article-id_pmc">2148135</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">9813088</infon><infon key="fpage">659</infon><infon key="issue">3</infon><infon key="kwd">meiosis</infon><infon key="lpage">671</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Carmena;given-names:Mar</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Riparbelli;given-names:Maria Giovanna</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Minestrini;given-names:Gianluca</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Tavares;given-names:Alvaro M.</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Adams;given-names:Richard</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Callaini;given-names:Giuliano</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Glover;given-names:David M.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">143</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Drosophila Polo Kinase Is Required for Cytokinesis </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>52</offset><text>A number of lines of evidence point to a predominance of cytokinesis defects in spermatogenesis in  hypomorphic alleles of the Drosophila polo gene. In  the pre-meiotic mitoses, cytokinesis defects result in  cysts of primary spermatocytes with reduced numbers  of cells that can contain multiple centrosomes. These  are connected by a correspondingly reduced number of  ring canals, structures formed by the stabilization of the  cleavage furrow. The earliest defects during the meiotic  divisions are a failure to form the correct mid-zone and  mid-body structures at telophase. This is accompanied  by a failure to correctly localize the Pavarotti kinesin-  like protein that functions in cytokinesis, and of the  septin Peanut and of actin to be incorporated into a  contractile ring. In spite of these defects, cyclin B is degraded and the cells exit M phase. The resulting spermatids are frequently binuclear or tetranuclear, in  which case they develop either two or four axonemes,  respectively. A significant proportion of spermatids in  which cytokinesis has failed may also show the segregation defects previously ascribed to polo1 mutants. We  discuss these findings in respect to conserved functions  for the Polo-like kinases in regulating progression  through M phase, including the earliest events of cytokinesis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1382</offset><text>Attention has recently focused upon the Polo-like  family of protein kinases (PLKs)1 as regulators of  the cellular architecture in the passage through  mitosis (for reviews see Glover et al., 1996; Lane and Nigg,  1997). The family is named after its founding member encoded by the polo gene of Drosophila. The original polo1  allele is a hypomorphic mutation that allows homozygotes  to survive to adulthood, but results in poor male fertility  and a maternal effect leading to embryonic lethality (Sunkel and Glover, 1988). During larval development, homozygotes display both mis-shaped and monopolar mitotic spindles in the developing central nervous system  (Sunkel and Glover, 1988; Llamazares et al., 1991). In addition, non-disjunction takes place in both meiotic divisions in the male, and multipolar meiotic spindles can be  seen. The centrosomes of polo1-derived embryos fail to assemble correctly resulting in multiply branched arrays of  mitotic microtubules (Sunkel and Glover, 1988). These  embryos contain Polo kinase that is inactive as a result of  its failure to become phosphorylated (Tavares et al., 1996).  Stronger hypomorphic and amorphic alleles have also  been isolated that show lethality in pupal and larval stages  and display mitotic arrest in cells of the central nervous  system (White-Cooper et al., 1996; Tavares, A.M., H. Ohkura, and D.M. Glover, unpublished data).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2783</offset><text>A number of functional studies in a variety of other eukaryotes have also pointed to key roles for the gene family  in several stages of mitosis. A Xenopus PLK copurifies  with and can activate cdc25, and thus may play a role in  the positive feedback loop that operates during p34cdc2 activation (Kumagai and Dunphy, 1996; Abrieu et al., 1998;  Qian et al., 1998). Micro-injection of anti-Polo-like kinase  antibodies into human cells prevents the separation of  centrosomes which remain small and show reduced immunoreactivity to anti-tubulin antibodies (Lane and Nigg,  1996). A role for the enzyme in activating the anaphase-promoting complex (APC) has been suggested in budding  yeast and vertebrate cells (Descombes and Nigg, 1998; Kotani et al., 1998; Shirayama et al., 1998). Mutations in the  budding yeast gene CDC5 (Hartwell et al., 1973; Byers  and Goetsch, 1974) that encodes a Polo-like kinase (Kitada et al., 1993) result in a late mitotic arrest in which  DNA has segregated upon an elongated spindle. Two phenotypes predominate in disruptants of the fission yeast  Polo-like kinase gene plo1, namely the formation of monopolar spindles as a consequence of the failure of the spindle pole bodies to separate, and a failure to form either an  actin ring or septum before cytokinesis. On the other  hand, the overexpression of plo1+ in fission yeast leads to  the formation of multiple septa. Strikingly, septation can  be driven by plo1+ overexpression in cells blocked at any  stage of the cell cycle indicating the potential of the enzyme to overcome the dependence of this process upon  the completion of mitosis (Ohkura et al., 1995). Expression of an activated form of mammalian PLK in budding  yeast has also been found to drive the formation of multiple septa (Lee and Erikson, 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4590</offset><text>In contrast to the yeasts, no direct evidence has yet been  presented to support a role for the Polo-like kinases in cytokinesis in animal cells. However, the subcellular distribution of the enzymes immediately before and during cytokinesis in fly, amphibian, and mammalian cells suggests  this as a possibility. Early in mitosis, Polo-like kinases are  associated with the centrosome and kinetochore regions of  chromosomes, but at anaphase they become concentrated  in the central part of the mitotic spindle (Goldsteyn et al.,  1995; Logarinho and Sunkel, 1998; Wianny et al., 1998).  They associate with the mid-body during telophase and  are lost from the cell along with the remnants of this structure during cytokinesis (Goldsteyn et al., 1995). The main  features of this pattern of distribution are shared in mammalian cells with the kinesin-like protein MKLP1 (Nislow  et al., 1990), and in Drosophila with the homologous protein Pav-KLP (Adams et al., 1998). These motor proteins  have been shown to be physically associated with the respective Plk and Polo kinases. Mutations in pavarotti, the  gene encoding Pav-KLP, result in abnormal morphology  of the central spindle and a failure to localize Polo kinase  correctly, culminating in a failure of cytokinesis (Adams  et al., 1998).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5887</offset><text>The original observations of the cytological phenotype  of polo1 mutations in male meiosis were carried out solely  by phase-contrast microscopy. It is possible to observe the  meiotic spindle in this way as contrast is provided by mitochondria that are also partitioned along its microtubules.  However, the development of immunolabeling techniques  for spermatocytes, and the recent availability of antibodies  against many essential components of the mitotic apparatus and the contractile ring have led us to re-examine the  meiotic phenotype. We now show that in addition to defects in spindle pole behavior and chromosome non-disjunction previously reported (Sunkel and Glover, 1988),  failure of cytokinesis can be seen throughout spermatogenesis. We discuss the implications of this finding in terms  of a unifying role for the Polo-like kinases in eukaryotic  cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>6762</offset><text>Materials and Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6784</offset><text>Reagents</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6793</offset><text>Amersham</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6802</offset><text>Boehringer Mannheim</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6822</offset><text>Sigma</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6828</offset><text>Sigma</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6834</offset><text>The following primary antibodies and dilutions were used: a 1:20 dilution  of rat anti-alpha-tubulin YL1/2 mAb (Harlan Sera-Lab Ltd., Leicestershire,  England), or a 1:50 dilution of mouse anti-alpha-tubulin N356 mAb ( Life Science, Inc., Arlington Heights, IL), a 1:200 dilution of mouse  anti-beta-tubulin KMX-1 mAb ( UK, East Sussex,  UK), a 1:4 dilution of mouse anti-peanut 4C9H4 mAb (developed by G.  Rubin, Drosophila Genome Center, Berkeley, CA, and obtained from the  Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank maintained by The University  of Iowa, Department of Biological Sciences, Iowa City, IA), a 1:100 dilution of rabbit anti-Pav-KLP polyclonal Rb3301 (Adams et al., 1998), or a  1:500 dilution of rabbit anti-Pav-KLP polyclonal GM2. FITC, Texas red,  Cy3, and Cy5 secondary antibodies were purchased from Jackson Immunochemicals or Cappel (West Grove, PA or Malvern, PA, respectively),  Alexa 488 secondary antibodies were purchased from Molecular Probes  Europe BV (Leiden, The Netherlands). DNA was visualized with propidium iodide, Hoechst 33258 (, St. Louis, MO) or TOTO-3 iodide  (Molecular Probes Europe BV). Vectashield mounting medium H-1000  was purchased from Vector Laboratories (Burlingame, CA). BSA was obtained from .</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>8077</offset><text>Fluorescence Microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8101</offset><text>Nikon</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8107</offset><text>Kodak</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8113</offset><text>Kodak</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8119</offset><text>Immunostaining of testes from pharate adults or young (0-1-d-old) flies  was performed either by the methanol/acetone fixation method as described by Glover and Gonzalez (1993) or by the ethanol/formaldehyde  fixation method as described by Hime et al. (1996). After counterstaining  of DNA with either Hoechst 33258, propidium iodide (1 mg/ml) or  TOTO-3 iodide (1:200), the samples were rinsed in PBS and mounted in  either 90% glycerol containing 2.5% N-propyl gallate (Giloh and Sedat,  1982) or in Vectashield mounting medium H-1000. Fluorescence observations were made on a Leitz Aristoplan microscope equipped with FITC,  TRITC, and UV filters, or on a MRC 1024 Confocal Imaging Head (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) on a  Optiphot microscope. Pho-tomicrographs were taken with  Tri-X 400 Pro and developed in   HC110 developer for 7 min at 20 C. Confocal images were processed using Photoshop (Adobe Systems, Mountain View, CA) and  printed using an Epson Stylus Photo color printer.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>9115</offset><text>Electron Microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9135</offset><text>Testes from pupae and adult flies were fixed in the trialdehyde solution of  Kalt and Tandler (1971) for 2 h at room temperature or overnight at 4 C.  After rinsing in 0.1 M cacodylate buffer, pH 7.2, the samples were postfixed in 1% osmium tetroxide for 2-3 h, bulk stained in 1% uranyl acetate  in distilled water, dehydrated in successively increasing concentrations of  ethanol, treated with propylene oxide, embedded in an Epon-Araldite  mixture, and then polymerized at 60 C for 48 h. Sections cut using an LKB  Nova ultramicrotome and a diamond knife (Diatome Ltd., Biel, Switzerland) were collected on copper grids and stained with uranyl acetate and  lead citrate. Sections were observed with a Philips CM10 electron microscope (Philips Electron Optics, Mahwah, NJ) at 80 kV.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>9920</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>9928</offset><text>polo1 Mutants Show Different Phenotypes in Mitosis  and Meiosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9992</offset><text>Previous studies of polo1 mutants have revealed a variety  of spindle pole defects at different developmental stages  that have been interpreted as a consequence of abnormal  centrosome behavior (Sunkel and Glover, 1988; Llamazares et al., 1991; and summarized in the Introduction). The  most dramatic mitotic defects are seen in polo1-derived  syncytial embryos, where the centrosomal antigen CP190  fails to associate with any microtubule-organizing centers  (Sunkel and Glover, 1988). In polo1 brains, the finding of  angled bipolar spindles and monopolar spindles (Sunkel  and Glover, 1988; Llamazares et al., 1991), suggests that  the centrosomes are failing to separate properly. Cells  having more than two MTOCs are extremely rare in the  polo1 larval central nervous system. In contrast, giant cells  with multiple gamma-tubulin-containing MTOCs can readily be  observed in testes from homozygous polo1 males (Fig. 1).  Thus, whereas the mutant shows a block in centrosome  duplication and separation in the mitotic cells of the central nervous system, it seems that in the male germ-line  many rounds of centrosome duplication can occur. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>11141</offset><text>Ring Canal Formation Is Defective in Polo1 Spermatocytes</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11198</offset><text>In both male and female gametogenesis in Drosophila a  founder cell, produced by the asymmetric division of a  germ line stem cell, first undertakes four rounds of mitosis  to produce a cell of either 16 spermatocytes or 15 nurse  cells and a single oocyte (for review see Fuller, 1993; Spradling, 1993). Cytokinesis is incomplete in these divisions  and the cells remain connected by ring canals. Additional  ring canals are formed in the male at each meiotic division  such that the resulting cyst contains 64 spermatids connected by 63 cytoplasmic bridges. A phospho-tyrosine  epitope has been described to accumulate early in ring canal formation in both males and females (Robinson et al.,  1994; Hime et al., 1996). The ring canals in the male have  been shown to contain three septins, polypeptides first  identified as being required to form filaments in the Saccharomyces cerevisiae bud neck, one of which is encoded  by the gene peanut, a gene essential for cytokinesis (Neufeld and Rubin, 1994). These proteins are indeed also  present during cytokinesis in the contractile ring, from  which the ring canals are derived (Hime et al., 1996). The  normal developmental progression of spermatogenesis is  diagrammed in Fig. 9. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12434</offset><text>The appearance of the cell displayed in Fig. 1 would suggest that it has undergone the pre-meiotic cell cycles in  which the gamma-tubulin-containing MTOCs have increased  geometrically in number in the absence of cytokinesis. It  has the characteristics of a multinuclear cell that has entered meiosis. Examination of cysts of primary spermatocytes revealed them to vary in appearance from those  containing single enlarged cells to others of wild-type appearance. Many cysts were intermediate between these extremes and contained both normal and polyploid cells.  One such cyst is shown in comparison with a wild-type cyst  in Fig. 2. Although the gonial mitoses are difficult to study  because these cells are very small, the process of cytokinesis leaves its &quot;footprint&quot; on these cells in the form of ring  canals. Cytokinesis is normally incomplete in the gonial  cysts and the 16 discrete primary spermatocytes are connected by 15 cytoplasmic bridges. The ring canals are  structures formed by stabilization of contractile rings  following cytokinesis through which these cytoplasmic  bridges pass. The kinesin-like protein encoded by pavarotti (Pav-KLP) is essential for cytokinesis, and associates  with the central region of the spindle at telophase. In the  embryonic mitoses it is discarded from the cell as part of  the mid-body upon the completion of cell division (Adams  et al., 1998). In male meiosis it persists to become incorporated into the 15 ring canals of the primary spermatocyte  cyst (Fig. 2 A, red stain). The polo1 mutant cyst (Fig. 2 B)  has just 12 ring canals connecting 13 cells, one of which  (arrow) is considerably larger than the others. The reduction in the total number of ring canals in this particular  cyst indicates that the large cell has failed to undertake the  previous two rounds of cytokinesis. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>14278</offset><text>The polo1 Mutation Prevents Formation of the Spindle  Mid-zone at Late Anaphase</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14358</offset><text>To look directly for defects in centrosome behavior or cytokinesis during cell division, we studied the intracellular  distribution of both gamma- and beta-tubulins. During the transition into the first meiotic division, gamma-tubulin becomes organized as a compact body at the centrioles where it remains  until completion of meiosis II (Wilson et al., 1997). The  majority of polo1 spermatocytes showed a pattern of gamma-tubulin localization at the spindle poles indistinguishable from  wild-type during meiosis I (Fig. 3). As previously described, the gamma-tubulin condenses into orthogonal rod-like  structures during prophase I (Fig. 3 A), which transforms  into more diffuse bodies during metaphase and anaphase  (Fig. 3, B and C). At metaphase, gamma-tubulin also becomes  localized perpendicular to the axis of the meiotic spindle,  delimiting the central spindle region. In late anaphase- telophase, however, many polo1 mutant cells show defects  in the appearance of the central region of the spindle (Fig.  3, C and D). Whereas in wild-type, a distinct mid-zone  structure develops in late anaphase that shows pronounced staining for beta-tubulin and moderate staining for  gamma-tubulin (Fig. 3 C, inset, arrowheads), no such gamma-tubulin  structure is seen at this stage in bipolar spindles in the  polo1 mutant. However, gamma-tubulin still localizes to the midzone in the absence of this central spindle structure (Fig. 3  C, arrows). Many bipolar spindles fail to constrict at telophase in polo1 mutants (Fig. 3 D, arrows) to form the characteristic mid-bodies seen in wild-type meiocytes (Fig. 3  D, insets, arrows). The localization of gamma-tubulin must be  dependent upon correct mid-body formation at this stage  since we observe it to have an abnormal distribution, remaining in the middle region instead of &quot;migrating&quot; polewards to the dividing nuclei as in the wild type. Mutations  in genes encoding two kinesin-like motor proteins, Klp3A  and pavarotti, show similar defects in the structure of the  mid-zone region of the spindle in late anaphase-telophase  and also ultimately result in a failure of cytokinesis (Williams et al., 1995; Adams et al., 1998). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16547</offset><text>Secondary spermatocytes that have failed to undergo  cytokinesis in the first division enter the second meiotic  cycle and undergo centrosome separation. Such cells typically contain four MTOCs (Fig. 4, arrows). Chromosomes  frequently appear to undergo non-disjunction on such  tetra-polar structures (Fig. 4, arrowheads). This is consistent with the diverse sizes of spermatid nuclei (see also  Table I), and the non-disjunction seen by following the  segregation of marked chromosomes (Sunkel and Glover,  1988).  </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17065</offset><text>In testes from polo1 mutants we typically found 3-4 cysts  of cells undergoing meiosis, in comparison with wild-type  testes where there are 5-6 meiotic cysts. We scored 1,965  meiotic figures from 20 homozygous polo1 mutant testes,  and found 69% to show normal meioses. Meiotic abnormalities were very rare at metaphase of the first division,  but defects of the types illustrated in Figs. 4-6 were found  in a total of 31% of cells from anaphase I onwards.  </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>17527</offset><text>The polo1 Mutation Affects the Relocalization of the Pav-KLP to the Mid-zone of the Spindle and  Prevents Contractile Ring Formation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17660</offset><text>To correlate the spindle defects described above with abnormal cytokinesis, we studied the distribution of a number of proteins that associate with the contractile furrow.  We have previously shown that the kinesin-like protein  encoded by pavarotti can associate with Polo kinase. In mitotically dividing cells, both proteins can be found at spindle poles until anaphase, but become associated with the  most central part of the spindle in the region of the cleavage furrow at telophase. This pattern of subcellular localization of both proteins is disrupted in pavarotti mutants  (Adams et al., 1998). We therefore decided to examine the  distribution of Pav-KLP in meiosis in both wild-type and  polo1 mutant males. We found it difficult to visualize Pav-KLP at the spindle poles in wild-type meiosis, although we  could readily observe the protein in the cleavage furrows  at the telophase of both meiotic divisions (Fig. 5 A, large  arrow), and to the ring canals (Fig. 5 A, arrowhead). polo1  mutant cysts contain ~30% of cells of mutant phenotype  alongside cells of wild-type appearance. In such a mutant  cyst displayed in Fig. 5 B, Pav-KLP can be seen associated  with the cleavage furrow of the wild-type appearing cell  indicated by the arrow. In contrast, the protein is not  found between the telophase nuclei in the cell showing  mutant phenotype indicated by the large arrowhead, but  instead appears to accumulate in the region of the poles  (Fig. 5, small arrowheads).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19147</offset><text>The other striking feature of cysts from polo1 mutant  testes is the loss of synchrony of the meiotic divisions in  comparison with wild-type meiosis. All of the cells in the  wild-type cyst in Fig. 5 C, for example, have progressed to  approximately the same stage of telophase. Pav-KLP is  present in the rings of the cleavage furrows (Fig. 5 C, large  arrow) and in the ring canals (Fig. 5 C, small arrowhead).  In addition, Pav-KLP is found associated with some (putative immature) axonemes (Fig. 5 C, small arrow), but not  with others (Fig. 5 C, large arrowhead). We speculate that  this points to another function of this motor protein in  transporting flagellar components to its growing distal tip,  or to facilitate the elongation of organelles such as mitochondria in the sperm tail. On the other hand, the polo1  mutant cyst (Fig. 5 D) contains cells at a variety of late  meiotic stages. Many cells have a wild-type appearance in  which case Pav-KLP may be seen in large cleavage rings at  late anaphase-early telophase (Fig. 5 D, arrow), or more  compact rings at late telophase (Fig. 5 D, arrowhead). In  other cells such rings of Pav-KLP never seem to form even  though the nuclei have moved to the poles of the spindle.  This is frequently the case with multipolar cells (Fig. 5 D,  large arrowhead). The polo1 mutation does not affect the  association of Pav-KLP with the flagellar axonemes (not  shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20570</offset><text>As septins are known to become incorporated into the  contractile ring, we attempted to localize the Drosophila  septin Peanut in telophase cells from polo1 mutant cysts  during meiosis (Fig. 5 F). In wild-type cysts, Peanut appears in the cleavage furrow rings at anaphase (Fig. 5 E,  green stain, large arrow), slightly ahead of Pav-KLP (red  stain). The two proteins colocalize in the furrow at telophase (Fig. 5 E, overlap shown by yellow staining, small arrow), with Pav-KLP appearing more concentrated on the  inner side of the ring. The ring canals appear to contain  Pav-KLP but Peanut is less easily detected (Fig. 5 E, small  arrowhead). It is our impression that in mutant cysts, there  is a tendency for both proteins to accumulate in the larger  cleavage furrow rings (Fig. 5 F, large arrow). This particular mutant cyst, which has a reduced number of nuclei, has  paired dots of Pav-KLP staining that has accumulated at  the spindle pole regions (Fig. 5 F, small arrows) even  though the cleavage furrows are forming.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21602</offset><text>The loss of synchrony of the meiotic divisions within a  cyst is also apparent in the late meiotic cyst shown in Fig.  6, that illustrates the formation of actin rings at the cleavage furrow. In the wild-type cyst shown in this Fig. 6, cells  are uniformly at telophase, and show actin rings of comparable sizes, in contrast to the cells of the mutant cyst that  are at a variety of meiotic stages. Late telophase cells can  be seen in which the spindle mid-body is well formed and  is associated with a compact actin ring (Fig. 6, small arrow). Other bipolar cells in which the chromatin has migrated fully to the poles have no mid-zone structure to the  spindle microtubules, and are lacking any actin ring (Fig.  6, large arrow). This directly links the defect in the central  spindle to a failure to establish a contractile ring. A number of cells with tripolar spindles are also seen in this particular cyst. In some of these cells there is no indication of  any actin ring formation (Fig. 6, large arrowhead), whereas  in others a large somewhat misshapen actin ring has  formed (small arrowhead). Such cells could arise as a result of cytokinesis failure in the first meiotic division, and  failure of one of the centrosomes to separate in the second  division.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>22871</offset><text>Cyclin B Is Degraded in polo1 Mutant Meioses</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22916</offset><text>A number of recent papers have reported that polo-like  kinases are required for mitotic exit and cyclin destruction,  functions that are mediated through activation of the  anaphase-promoting complex (APC) (Charles et al., 1998;  Descombes and Nigg, 1998; Kotani et al., 1998; Shirayama  et al., 1998). Chromatid separation at anaphase is also  thought to be under control of the APC. Thus our observations that anaphase could occur in polo1 mutant cells did  not seem to accord with these results. We therefore examined whether cyclin B degradation could take place in  polo1 mutant testes. In wild-type meiotic cysts, a gradient  of cyclin B degradation can be seen as cells progress  through the late stages of meiotic division (Fig. 7 B). Cyclin B degradation is also seen late in the meiotic cycle in  polo1 cells that display either multipolar spindles (Fig. 7 A,  tetrapolar spindle indicated by the large arrow), or bipolar  spindles in which the central spindle is abnormal (Fig. 7 A,  small arrow). We therefore conclude either that polo kinase is not required to activate the APC to mediate cyclin  B degradation in these cells even though cytokinesis has  been affected, or that these processes (together with chromosome disjunction) are differentially sensitive to the  polo1 mutation. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>24217</offset><text>Tetranuclear Spermatids Arising from a Failure of  Cytokinesis Can Undergo Differentiation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24308</offset><text>The spermatids resulting from meiosis pass through a  stage of development known as the onion stage, in which  mitochondria aggregate into a large phase dark body  known as the &quot;Nebenkern.&quot; Within this structure the mitochondrial membranes are wrapped around each other  like the layers of an onion. Wild-type spermatids contain  one nucleus and one Nebenkern, and these bodies are of  equal size within the cyst of 64 cells. In the polo1 mutants,  the majority (82.8%) of onion stage spermatids appear  normal (Fig. 8 A; Table I). Alternatively they may have  varying numbers of nuclei of which binucleate cells  (13.1%; Fig. 8 A, arrowhead) and tetranucleate cells  (2.7%; large cell in Fig. 8 C) are the most frequent. These  cells have a single enlarged Nebenkern, and indicate a failure of cytokinesis in either one or both meiotic divisions.  79% of nuclei in the binucleate cells and 48% in the tetranucleate cells are of uniform diameter suggesting that the  major defect has been solely in cytokinesis. The remaining  cells have nuclei that show a variation in their diameter indicative of additional non-disjunction (Sunkel and Glover,  1988). Most of the non-disjunction observed cytologically  accompanies cytokinesis defects (Table I). As spermatids  initiate their differentiation into mature sperm, the mitochondria first undergo elongation. Elongating spermatids  can be seen at this stage in polo1 testes that have two or  more nuclei at the base of the sperm tail, indicative of a  failure of cytokinesis in one of the meiotic divisions (Fig.  8 D). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25877</offset><text>Elongation of the mitochondria is shortly followed by  elongation of the nuclei accompanied by growth of the  flagellar axoneme from the basal body. Sections of sperm  tails at sequential stages of elongation are compared between wild-type and the polo1 mutant in Fig. 9. Occasional  spermatids in the polo1 mutant show defective axonemes  (Fig. 9 A). However, whereas at all stages only a single axoneme can be seen in wild-type sperm tails (Fig. 9, B, D,  and F), the mutant sperm tails frequently contain either  two or four axonemes indicative of a failure of cytokinesis  in either one (most likely the second) or both meiotic divisions, respectively. The observed frequency of multiple axonemes in elongating spermatids and sperm is consistent  with the frequency of multinucleate spermatids at the onion stage (Table I).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26705</offset><text>Finally we wished to ensure that the cytokinesis defects  we describe here for polo1 were in fact due to mutations at  the polo locus, and not some other mutation carried on the  chromosome. We selected two hypomorphic mutants,  polo3 and polo8, from an allelic series of ems induced polo  mutations since we had previously determined them to be  similar in strength to polo1 (White-Cooper et al., 1996).  We then made heterozygotes between these mutations  and polo1 and examined testes preparations from such  males by phase contrast microscopy. In both cases we were  able to detect similar defects throughout spermatogenesis  to those seen in polo1 homozygotes, although quantitation  of defects in onion stage spermatids indicated that polo8 is  a stronger allele (Table II). An apparently greater frequency of defects consistent with cytokinesis failure before meiosis was seen in other stronger alleles in the series  (see Discussion). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>27649</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>27660</offset><text>Cytokinesis Can Fail at All Stages of Spermatogenesis  in polo1 Mutants</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27732</offset><text>The data that we present can best be interpreted by assuming that the polo1 mutation provides a low level of residual function that permits some cells to pass through  both mitosis and meiosis in the developing fly. However, a  considerable proportion of cells fail to do so, and in the developing central nervous system they become arrested or  delayed in a metaphase-like state in mitosis. In the testes,  on the other hand, while there are defects in centrosome  behavior and chromosome disjunction as previously reported (Sunkel and Glover, 1988) cytokinesis can also be  seen to fail at any of the developmental stages of spermatogenesis (see Fig. 10). Several pieces of evidence point  to cytokinesis defects occurring in the pre-meiotic divisions. Many cysts of primary spermatocytes have a reduced number of ring canals, the structures normally  formed by stabilization of the cleavage furrow. Moreover,  cells in these cysts may become enlarged and polyploid,  and contain multiple centrosomes nucleating multipolar  spindles. Such a phenotype can be explained by a failure of  cell division coupled with ongoing rounds of DNA replication and centrosome duplication. Cytokinesis can also fail  in either (or both) of the meiotic divisions. As a result of  cytokinesis failing in meiosis I, many secondary spermatocytes develop tetrapolar spindles and subsequently following a second failure of cytokinesis produce tetranuclear  spermatids with a single large mitochondrial aggregate.  The sperm that develop from such cells can be seen, upon  elongation, to have four axonemes. In addition, there are  also both binucleate spermatids, and elongating sperm  containing two axonemes, indicative of a failure of cytokinesis in the second meiotic division. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29495</offset><text>Most of the multinuclear spermatids have nuclei of a  uniform size suggesting that cytokinesis has been the only  abnormal meiotic event in these cells. However, when  chromosome non-disjunction has occurred, as indicated by  spermatid nuclei of heterodispersed size, this is usually associated with failure of cytokinesis. This suggests that multiple defects can arise as a result of partial loss of polo  function. The segregation defect may be related to the observed association of polo kinase with the centromeric regions of chromosomes (Logarinho and Sunkel, 1998; our  own unpublished observations).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>30102</offset><text>The Earliest Defects Before Cytokinesis Are in the  Structure of the Central Spindle</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30187</offset><text>It seems likely that defects in the organization of the central region of the spindle at anaphase anticipate the failure  of the contractile actin ring to form and the failure of cytokinesis in polo1 meiosis. The central spindle shows an  abnormal distribution of mid-zone microtubules from late  anaphase-telophase. This region normally shows some  staining of gamma-tubulin that recedes polewards as the mid-body structure matures. In the polo1 mutant a mid-body  does not form and some gamma-tubulin remains in the mid-zone  region. gamma-Tubulin at the central region of the spindle has  previously been suggested to be required to form the mid-body, and for the process of cytokinesis (Julian et al., 1993;  Shu et al., 1995). Thus a common function of gamma-tubulin in  both the centrosome and spindle mid-zone might be to act  as a microtubule organizing center, a property that might  require to be activated by the Polo-like kinases.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31130</offset><text>The central spindle defects are accompanied by a failure  to correctly localize the kinesin-like protein encoded by  pavarotti, a gene shown to be required for cytokinesis in  developing embryos (Adams et al., 1998). Moreover, rings  of the septin Peanut and of actin fail to form in the mid-region of the cell. These defects are similar to those seen  in other cytokinesis mutants. The formation of a defective  spindle mid-zone at late anaphase and failure to form a  mid-body is seen with mutations in Klp3A and pavarotti  (Williams et al., 1995; Adams et al., 1998). These genes  each encode kinesin-like proteins, KLP3A and Pav-KLP,  respectively, that have been postulated to have a direct  role in organizing the central spindle in preparation for cytokinesis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31898</offset><text>An additional role has been suggested for Pav-KLP by  its association with Polo kinase, namely that it might also  serve as a means of localizing this enzyme first to the centrosomes, and subsequently at the central spindle to choreograph formation of the bipolar spindle and then cytokinesis (Adams et al., 1998). The two proteins also appear to  be mutually dependent for their correct localization. Polo  kinase fails to localize to spindle poles or the spindle mid-zone in pavarotti mutants (Adams et al., 1998) and we now  show that Pav-KLP accumulates at the spindle poles in  meiosis in polo1 males and often fails to become associated  with the spindle mid-zone. This suggests a model whereby  the motor properties of Pav-KLP might be changed as a  consequence of phosphorylation by Polo kinase, a hypothesis that is currently under investigation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32754</offset><text>Polo kinase could also phosphorylate other cytoskeletal  components, such as septins or actin-associated proteins to  directly modify the structure of the contractile apparatus.  Such modifications may in turn lead to changes in the  structure of the central spindle. It appears that cooperative  interactions occur between the central spindle and the  acto-myosin ring to effect cytokinesis. The acto-myosin  contractile ring fails to form following mutation of the  chickadee gene, which encodes the actin binding protein  profilin (Giansanti et al., 1998), and consequently the morphology of the central spindle is affected during late meiosis. Thus it would seen that there is a mutual dependence  for the correct formation of the cleavage ring and the central spindle region.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>33535</offset><text>Why Should It Be Easier to Observe Cytokinesis Defects in polo Mutants during Spermatogenesis?</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33630</offset><text>One possible answer to this question could be that there  are different demands upon polo function in mitosis and  meiosis. In such a case one might imagine that Polo kinase  is less important for correct centrosome behavior in the  meiotic cycle, so emphasizing the requirement for cytokinesis. This may be accentuated by the hypomorphic nature  of the polo1 mutation, the residual function being sufficient to form a functional meiotic spindle, but insufficient  for its subsequent role. Examination of spermatogenesis  in an allelic series of polo mutants (White-Cooper et al.,  1996) reveals a range of meiotic defects consistent with the  strength of the mutant allele. The large primary spermatocytes we previously reported in the stronger alleles (polo4,  polo6, polo7) are very similar to those we now describe in  detail for polo1, but occur at a higher frequency. However,  the asynchrony in the passage through spermatogenesis  within a cyst is much more pronounced in these strong alleles. Few cells develop to spermatids suggesting a block to  pre-meiotic or meiotic divisions. The spermatids that are  formed show multiple nuclei and enlarged Nebenkern indicative of cytokinesis defects.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34832</offset><text>It is also possible that the cytokinesis defects seen in  male meiosis in polo1 could reflect the absence of the  checkpoint controls that monitor the structure of the spindle during the male meiotic divisions. The continuation of  the meiotic cycle in the absence of a functional spindle is  reported for the beta2t n mutant that lacks a functional male  specific tubulin isoform. The gene for this isoform is expressed at high levels in the growing stage of primary spermatocytes, and the protein is the major gamma-tubulin present  in the microtubules of the meiotic spindle, and subsequently in the flagellar axoneme. Although these mutants  lack a meiotic spindle, their chromosomes are described to  undergo normal meiotic condensation-decondensation cycles, and although homologues separate, they fail to segregate resulting ultimately in the formation of tetraploid  spermatids that begin to differentiate (Fuller, 1993). Thus  in the absence of a spindle integrity checkpoint in male  meiosis, if meiotic spindle defects develop in polo mutants,  chromosome segregation may be able to continue. However, meiosis may fail subsequently at cytokinesis. In contrast, if spindle defects occur in the mitotic divisions of larval neuroblasts, then the cycle is arrested at metaphase by  checkpoint controls and so cytokinesis is never attempted.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>36180</offset><text>A Unifying Role for polo-like Kinases in the Early  Events of Cytokinesis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36254</offset><text>The central importance of our present findings is that they  clearly establish a role for Polo kinase in the early events  of cytokinesis in animal cells, as has previously been established for its fission yeast counterpart plo1 (Ohkura et al.,  1995). Thus there appears to be a unifying role for the  Polo-like kinases in both establishing the bipolar spindle  and in regulating late mitotic events from the yeasts to the  metazoans. It is of interest that the Polo-like kinases of fission yeast and animal cells show some common aspects of  localization. In flies and mammals, Polo-like kinases are  found associated with centrosomes and centromeres early  in mitosis and then subsequently at the spindle mid-zone  and cleavage furrow before cytokinesis (Goldsteyn, 1995;  Adams et al., 1998). The fission yeast Plo1p like its animal  cell counterparts localizes to the spindle poles at the onset  of mitosis, but structures analogous to the central spindle  and cleavage furrow are not found in fission yeast cytokinesis (Mulvihill, D., H. Ohkura, I. Hagan, and D.M.  Glover, manuscript in preparation). Indeed, other proteins  required for septation such as the protein kinase encoded  by cdc7, that lies at the head of the hierarchy regulating  septum formation, have also been found to accumulate at  the spindle poles (Sohrmann et al., 1998). This establishes  the spindle pole bodies as a potential source for signaling  molecules that regulate the onset of cytokinesis in the fission yeast. Animal cells may show a variation in this theme  by which the Polo-like kinases become redistributed from  the spindle poles and centromeres to the central region of  the spindle. This could be an evolutionary adaptation that  has paralleled the increase in size and complexity of the  metazoan mitotic spindle in comparison with its yeast  counterpart. Thus the association of Polo kinase with a kinesin-like protein, recently shown to be essential for cytokinesis (Lee et al., 1995; Adams et al., 1998), may be required both to regulate the change in structure of the  central spindle immediately before cytokinesis and to correctly localize Polo kinase to its site of action late in cell division. Significantly mutations in Polo and in the associated Pav-KLP both lead to defects in the structure of the  central spindle in late anaphase and telophase, and the two  proteins appear to be mutually dependent upon each  other for their correct subcellular localization.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>38727</offset><text>Our findings have implications towards the existing  models for the origins of the signals for cytokinesis in animal cells. Rappaport (1961) has provided compelling evidence that in Echinoderm embryos asters can dictate the  position of the cleavage furrow. On the other hand,  Wheatley and Wang (1996) found that when tripolar cells  were induced to undergo mitosis, the position of cytokinesis was determined by the position of mid-zone microtubules. Moreover, Cao and Wang (1996) found that cytokinesis could be blocked by placing a barrier between the  central spindle and the cell cortex suggesting a signal for  cytokinesis emanates from the central spindle. These two  general hypotheses could be reconciled if the signaling  molecule(s), for which Polo-like kinase could be one  prime candidate, were initially localized at the poles, and  subsequently at the central spindle anticipating the position of the cleavage furrow, and if the extent of this relocalization were to vary between different cell types.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>39745</offset><text>Can Late M-phase Events Be Distinguished from Early Cytokinesis?</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39810</offset><text>It might be argued both for the S. pombe plo1 disruptant  and Drosophila hypomorphic polo meiotic phenotypes  that defects are not in cytokinesis per se, but rather in the  events that immediately precede it. Is this more than a  question of semantics? In the animal cell the distinction is  difficult, as the processes that lead to the formation of the  central anaphase-telophase spindle cannot be unraveled  from those resulting in formation of the actin ring. In the  fission yeast, cytokinesis fails in plo1 disruptants, but as a  consequence of a failure to assemble the actin ring and the  septum. Conversely, it should be noted that overexpression of plo1+ drives the formation of multiple septa, and  not the whole of the process of cytokinesis, suggesting it  might be reasonable to make a distinction between these  events.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40645</offset><text>The late mitotic phenotypes of S. pombe plo1 and its S.  cerevisiae counterpart cdc5 differ; failure of septum deposition in fission yeast and a late nuclear division arrest in  budding yeast. A role for CDC5 specifically in mediating  late mitotic events is further suggested by the recent demonstration that it is required to activate the cyclin destruction machinery (Charles et al., 1998; Shirayama et al.,  1998). A generality for this role is supported by findings  that mouse polo-like kinase can phosphorylate and activate components of the APC (Kotani et al., 1998), and that  the Xenopus homologue is required for mitotic exit and  cyclin destruction (Descombes and Nigg, 1998). In polo1  mutant testes, however, although a proportion of cells display defects in chromosome segregation, anaphase seems  to take place normally in the majority of polo1 mutant  meiocytes that will fail cytokinesis. Moreover, cyclin B is  degraded within these cells that then exit the meiotic division. These observations that suggest the regulation of the  APC is not affected in polo1. Nevertheless, it is possible either that anaphase, cyclin B degradation, and early cytokinesis may be differentially sensitive to polo kinase function, or alternatively, that the meiotic divisions have their  own specific regulatory system for these events (see also  Discussion above). We have recently characterized two  new strong hypomorphic mutant alleles of polo that show  a high mitotic index in the larval central nervous system.  This phenotype would be consistent with a role for the enzyme in regulating the activity of the anaphase promoting  complex (Tavares, A.M., H. Ohkura, and D.M. Glover,  unpublished data). It will be of considerable future interest to study the behavior of components of the Drosophila  APC in these and other mutant polo alleles that differentially affect mitosis and meiosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>42542</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>42561</offset><text>A giant gonial cell resulting from failure of pre-meiotic cytokinesis in testes from homozygous polo1 males. Staining reveals  microtubules (left), gamma-tubulin distribution revealing centrosomes (middle), and chromatin (right). Multiple monopolar spindles originate  from as many gamma-tubulin-containing foci, suggesting that centrosome duplication and separation continue in the absence of cytokinesis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>42968</offset><text>Transmission electron micrographs of polo1 (A,  C, E) and wild-type (B, D, F)  cysts of spermatids at sequential stages of elongation.  (A) Cross section of an early  elongating polo1 spermatid  showing three axonemes  (large arrowheads) associated with only one mitochondrial derivative (small  arrowhead). The structure  of one axoneme appears abnormal (large arrowhead).  A fourth axoneme is outside the frame of the picture. (B) In contrast, in  wild-type early elongating  spermatids one axoneme  (large arrowhead) is normally associated with a pair  of mitochondrial derivatives (small arrowheads).  (C) Cross section of elongating cysts at a later stage  shows that spermatids in  polo1 males may contain  four axonemes (cell indicated by arrowhead). (D)  Wild-type spermatids at a  similar stage contain single  axonemes. (E) Section of  mature sperm from polo1  males showing irregular  numbers of axonemes (two  in the cell indicated by the  large arrowhead, three in  the cell indicated by the  small arrowhead). (F) Mature wild-type sperm contain single axonemes. Although the occasional  abnormal axoneme is seen  in the polo1 mutant (A), the  majority of axonemes from  polo1 and wild-type males have an identical structure throughout the sequential stages of elongation: they comprise one pair of  central tubules surrounded by nine doublets, and nine accessory tubules in later stages. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>44371</offset><text>Cytokinesis defects in the pre-meiotic divisions are indicated by reduced numbers of ring canals, and enlarged cells in cysts of  primary spermatocytes. Optical sections of a cyst of (A) wild-type and (B) polo1 mutant primary spermatocytes. DNA is stained blue,  microtubules in green and Pav-KLP in red. The wild-type cyst contains 16 cells inter-connected through 15 ring canals that contain Pav-KLP. The polo1 mutant cyst contains 13 cells connected by 12 ring canals. One cell (arrow) is considerably larger than its neighbors.  Bars, 20 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>44918</offset><text>polo1 spermatocytes show spindle mid-zone  defects at late anaphase. Progression through the first  meiotic division in polo1 is  shown in the main panels,  and in wild-type in the insets.  Testes preparations have  been stained with antibodies  against beta-tubulin (left-hand  panels), gamma-tubulin (middle  panels), and Hoechst to  reveal DNA (right-hand  panels) (see Materials and  Methods). (A) Mature spermatocytes. Note the orthogonal rod-like gamma-tubulin  structures at the focus of  the cytoplasmic microtubules. (B) Metaphase spermatocytes. gamma-Tubulin is  transformed into more diffuse bodies at the poles of  the spindles. Bivalents congregate in single masses. (C)  Late anaphase spermatocytes. A prominent mid-zone structure strongly  stained for beta-tubulin (arrowhead in insets) is present in  wild-type anaphase spindles,  whereas no such structure is  found in polo1 spindles (arrows). gamma-Tubulin is present in  this region in both mutant  and wild-type. (D) Telophase  spermatocytes. Wild-type  spermatocytes show characteristic mid-bodies with a distinct gap in beta-tubulin staining  between the two halves of  the spindles (arrowheads in  insets); in contrast the spindle  microtubules of polo1 mutant  spermatocytes fail to organize similar structures during telophase (arrows).  Whereas in the wild-type, the  gamma-tubulin in the central region of the spindle begins to  redistribute towards the  poles, in the mutant cell it remains in the central region.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>46410</offset><text>Tetrapolar cells in which cytokinesis has failed in both meiotic divisions in the polo1 mutant. Testes have been stained to reveal microtubules (left), gamma-tubulin (middle), and chromatin (right). Each cell contains four astral microtubules and four foci of gamma-tubulin  (arrows). Chromosomes frequently appear to undergo non-disjunction (arrowheads).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>46766</offset><text>Spermatid Abnormalities in polo1 Homozygotes </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>46812</offset><text>   (A)             Nuclei per onion stage spermatid  1  2  3  4  &gt;4  Percent spermatids  82.8  13.1  0.5  2.7  0.6  Percent spermatids with variation in nuclear size   0.2   2.8  0.5  1.4  0.6  (B)            Axonemes per elongated spermatid   1   2  3  4  0  Percent spermatids  81.8  11.3  1.3  5.6  1</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>47116</offset><text>Mislocalization of  Pav-KLP and Peanut at telophase in polo1 mutants. In all  of these panels, DNA is  stained blue, and Pav-KLP  red. The third immunostain  (green) in C and D reveals  microtubules, and in E and F,  the septin Peanut. (A) A  wild-type cyst at late  anaphase/early telophase I in  which Pav-KLP can be seen  to be present in the ring canals (arrowhead) and the  contractile rings (arrow). (B)  In an equivalent polo1 mutant cyst, Pav-KLP (red) is localized in the contractile ring  (arrow) and remains in the  ring canal in normal cells. In  spermatocytes showing the  mutant phenotype, Pav-KLP  accumulates in the polar regions (small arrowhead) and  does not redistribute to the  midbody. (C) A telophase I  cyst showing the distribution  of Pav-KLP (red) relative to  microtubules (green). Large  arrow, a cleavage ring; and  small arrowhead, a ring canal.  In addition, Pav-KLP is associated with some (putatively  immature) axonemal microtubules (small arrow), but not  with others (large arrowhead). (D) Telophase figures  in polo1 in which Pav-KLP is  associated with early (arrow)  and late (small arrowhead)  cleavage rings in cells undergoing apparently normal late  meiotic events. Cleavage  rings fail to form correctly in  the multipolar figure (large  arrow). (E) Immunolocalization of Pav-KLP (red) and  Peanut (green) in a wild-type  late anaphase/early telophase I cyst. The large arrow  indicates an early cleavage  ring in which the staining for  Peanut is more pronounced  than for Pav-KLP. The two proteins colocalize in the later cleavage ring (small arrow) with Pav-KLP being more concentrated towards  the inner side. Ring canals appear to contain Pav-KLP and not Peanut (small arrow). (F) polo1 mutant cyst with Pav-KLP and Peanut  colocalizing in both early (large arrow) and late cleavage rings. Punctate staining of Pav-KLP is also seen in the regions of the spindle  poles (small arrows).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>49051</offset><text>Abnormal actin  ring formation during cytokinesis in polo1 mutants. DNA  is stained blue; microtubules  are stained green; and actin is  stained red. Actin rings at  equivalent stages can be seen  in the telophase figures from  the wild-type cyst. In the  polo1 mutant cyst, actin forms  a ring in late telophase cells  with a normal spindle mid-body (small arrow), but not  in cells in which the mid-body  has not formed (large arrow).  Ring-like structures of actin  may (small arrowhead) or  may not (large arrowhead)  form in cells with tripolar  spindles. Bars, 10 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>49626</offset><text>Cyclin B is degraded upon meiotic exit in polo1 mutants. Metaphase-telophase mutant figures in the polo1 mutant. This cyst  has several multipolar cells at stages both before and after cyclin B degradation. The large and small arrows indicate cells with a tetrapolar and abnormal bipolar spindles respectively in which cyclin B has undergone degradation. Wild-type cyst with cells showing progressive cyclin B degradation at various stages of the metaphase-anaphase transition.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>50104</offset><text>Multinuclear spermatids in polo1. (A and B) Squashed  preparations of onion stage spermatids. The clear spherical structure is the nucleus, and the dark spherical structure the mitochondrial derivative or Nebenkern. A binucleate cell with a single  Nebenkern is indicated by the arrowhead in A. C and D show  larger cells that have 5 or 4 nuclei, respectively and a single  Nebenkern. D shows spermatids at an early stage of elongation.  The arrowhead points to a binucleate cell.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>50585</offset><text>Spermatid Abnormalities in polo Transheterozygotes </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>50637</offset><text>   Nuclei per onion stage spermatid  1  2  3  4  &gt;4   Percent spermatids - polo1/polo3  88.2  11.3  0  0.3  0  Percent spermatids - polo1/polo8  79.0  16.2  0  3.2  0.4</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>50806</offset><text>A schematic illustration of  spermatogenesis in Drosophila illustrating some of the defects that arise as  a result of the failure of cytokinesis.  Color is used to depict DNA (blue);  ring canals (red); the fusome (ochre), a  structure rich in membranes and spectrin that passes through the ring canals;  microtubules (green); and mitochondrial derivatives (black).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>51173</offset><text>Abbreviations used in this paper</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>51206</offset><text>APC</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>51210</offset><text>anaphase-promoting complex</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>51237</offset><text>PLK</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>51241</offset><text>Polo-like kinase</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>51258</offset><text>References</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1751</infon><infon key="lpage">1757</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Abrieu;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Brassac;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Galas;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Fisher;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Labbe;given-names:JC</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Doree;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9601104</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">111</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>51269</offset><text>The polo-like kinase Plx1 is a component of the MPF amplification loop at the G(2)/M-phase transition of the cell cycle in Xenopus eggs</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Adams, R.R., A.A.M. Tavares, A. Salzberg, H.J. Bellen, and D.M. Glover.  1998. pavarotti encodes a kinesin-like protein required to organize the central spindle and contractile ring for cytokinesis. Genes Dev. In press.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>51405</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">123</infon><infon key="lpage">131</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Byers;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Goetsch;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">4598635</infon><infon key="source">Cold Spring Harbor Symp Quant Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">38</infon><infon key="year">1974</infon><offset>51406</offset><text>Duplication of spindle plaques and integration of the yeast cell cycle</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">225</infon><infon key="lpage">232</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cao;given-names:L-G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wang;given-names:Y-L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8688554</infon><infon key="source">Mol  Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>51477</offset><text>Signals from the spindle midzone are required for the stimulation of cytokinesis in cultured epithelial cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">497</infon><infon key="lpage">507</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Charles;given-names:JF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Jespersen;given-names:SL</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:TinkerKulberg;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Hwang;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Szidon;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Morgan;given-names:DO</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9560342</infon><infon key="source">Curr Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>51587</offset><text>The Polo-related kinase Cdc5 activates and is destroyed by the cyclin destruction machinery in S. cerevisiae</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">173</infon><infon key="lpage">184</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cooley;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Verheyen;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ayers;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1339308</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">69</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>51696</offset><text>chickadee encodes a profilin required for intercellular cytoplasm transport during Drosophilaoogenesis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1328</infon><infon key="lpage">1335</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Descombes;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Nigg;given-names:E</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9482730</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>51799</offset><text>The polo-like kinase Plx1 is required for M  phase exit and destruction of mitotic regulators in Xenopusegg extracts</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Fuller, M.T. 1993. Spermatogenesis. In The Development of Drosophila melanogaster. Vol. I.M. Bate and A. Martinez-Arias, editors. Cold Spring Harbor  Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, NY. 71-147.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>51916</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">396</infon><infon key="lpage">410</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Giansanti;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bonacorsi;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Williams;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Williams;given-names:EV</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Santolamazza;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Goldberg;given-names:ML</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Gatti;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9450933</infon><infon key="source">Genes  Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>51917</offset><text>Cooperative interactions between the  central spindle and the contractile ring during Drosophilacytokinesis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1252</infon><infon key="lpage">1255</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Giloh;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sedat;given-names:JW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7112126</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">217</infon><infon key="year">1982</infon><offset>52025</offset><text>Fluorescence microscopy: reduced photobleaching of rhodamine and fluorescein protein conjugates by n-propyl gallate</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Glover, D.M., and C. Gonzalez. 1993. Techniques for studying mitosis in  Drosophila. In The Cell Cycle: A Practical Approach. R. Brookes and P.  Fantes, editors. Oxford: IRL Press, Oxford. 163-168.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>52141</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1681</infon><infon key="lpage">1684</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ohkura;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Tavares;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8991082</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">135</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>52142</offset><text>Polo kinase: The choreographer of the mitotic stage? </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1617</infon><infon key="lpage">1628</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Goldsteyn;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mundt;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Fry;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Nigg;given-names:E</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7790358</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">129</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>52196</offset><text>Cell cycle regulation of the activity and subcellular localization of PLK1, a human protein kinase implicated in mitotic spindle function</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">267</infon><infon key="lpage">286</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hartwell;given-names:LH</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mortimer;given-names:RK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Culotti;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Culotti;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17248617</infon><infon key="source">Genetics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">74</infon><infon key="year">1973</infon><offset>52334</offset><text>Genetic control  of the cell division cycle in yeast: V. Genetic analysis of the cdcmutants</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2779</infon><infon key="lpage">2788</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hime;given-names:GR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Brill;given-names:JA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Fuller;given-names:MT</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9013326</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">109</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>52426</offset><text>Assembly of ring canals in the male germ line from structural components of the contractile ring</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">145</infon><infon key="lpage">156</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Julian;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tollon;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lajoie-Manzenc;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Mazarguil;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Puget;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Wright;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8360269</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">105</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>52523</offset><text>gamma-tubulin participates in the formation of the mid-body during cytokinesis in mammalian cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">633</infon><infon key="lpage">645</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kalt;given-names:MR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tandler;given-names:B</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">4939156</infon><infon key="source">J Ultrastruct Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">36</infon><infon key="year">1971</infon><offset>52621</offset><text>A study of fixation of early amphibian embryos for electron microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4445</infon><infon key="lpage">4457</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kitada;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Johnson;given-names:AL</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Johnston;given-names:LH</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Sugino;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8321244</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>52692</offset><text>A multicopy supressor gene of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae G1 cell cycle mutant gene dbf4  encodes a protein kinase and is identified as CDC5. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">371</infon><infon key="lpage">381</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kotani;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tugendreich;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Fujii;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Jorgensen;given-names:PM</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Watanabe;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Hoog;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Hieter;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Todokoro;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9660921</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>52836</offset><text>PKA and MPF-activated Polo-like kinase regulate anaphase promoting factor complex activity and mitosis progression</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1377</infon><infon key="lpage">1380</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kumagai;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Dunphy;given-names:WG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8703070</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">273</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>52951</offset><text>Purification and molecular cloning of  Plx1, a Cdc25-regulatory kinase from Xenopusegg extracts</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1701</infon><infon key="lpage">1713</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lane;given-names:HA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Nigg;given-names:EA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8991084</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">135</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>53047</offset><text>Antibody microinjection reveals an essential role for human Polo-like kinase 1 (Plk1) in the functional maturation of mitotic centrosomes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">63</infon><infon key="lpage">68</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lane;given-names:HA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Nigg;given-names:EA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17708908</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>53185</offset><text>Cell cycle control: Polo-like kinases join the outer circle</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3408</infon><infon key="lpage">3417</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lee;given-names:KS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Erikson;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9154840</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>53245</offset><text>Plk is a functional homolog of Saccharomyces cerevisiaeCdc5, and elevated Plk activity induces multiple septation structures</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">7143</infon><infon key="lpage">7151</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lee;given-names:KS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Yuan;given-names:YO</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kuriyama;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Erikson;given-names:R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8524282</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>53370</offset><text>Plk is an M-phase specific protein kinase and interacts with a kinesin-like protein, CHO1/ MKLP-1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2153</infon><infon key="lpage">2165</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Llamazares;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Moreira;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Tavares;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Girdham;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Spruce;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Gonzalez;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Karess;given-names:RE</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Sunkel;given-names:CE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1660828</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>53468</offset><text>Polo encodes a protein kinase homolog required for mitosis in Drosophila. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2897</infon><infon key="lpage">2909</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Logarinho;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sunkel;given-names:CE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9730982</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">111</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>53543</offset><text>The Drosophilamitotic kinase POLO localises to the centrosome, centromeres and spindle midzone during mitosis and contributes to the phosphorylation of MPM2 reactive epitopes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">371</infon><infon key="lpage">379</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Neufeld;given-names:TP</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Rubin;given-names:GM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8181057</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">77</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>53718</offset><text>The Drosophila peanutgene is required for cytokinesis and encodes a protein similar to yeast putative bud neck filament proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">511</infon><infon key="lpage">522</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nislow;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sellito;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kuriyama;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:McIntosh;given-names:JR</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2199459</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">111</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>53847</offset><text>A monoclonal antibody to a mitotic microtubule-associated protein blocks mitotic progression</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1059</infon><infon key="lpage">1073</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ohkura;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hagan;given-names:IM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7744248</infon><infon key="source">Genes  Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>53940</offset><text>The conserved Schizosaccharomyces pombe kinase, plo1, required to form a bipolar spindle, the actin ring, and septum, can drive septum formation in G1 and G2 cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1697</infon><infon key="lpage">1709</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pesacreta;given-names:TC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Byers;given-names:TJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Dubreuil;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kiehart;given-names:DP</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Branton;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2497103</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">108</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>54104</offset><text>Drosophilaspectrin: The membrane skeleton during embryogenesis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4262</infon><infon key="lpage">4271</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Qian;given-names:YW</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Erikson;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Li;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Maller;given-names:JL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9632810</infon><infon key="source">Mol  Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>54167</offset><text>Activated polo-like kinase Plx1 is required at multiple points during mitosis in Xenopus laevis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">81</infon><infon key="lpage">89</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rappaport;given-names:R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14490383</infon><infon key="source">J Exp Zool</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">148</infon><infon key="year">1961</infon><offset>54263</offset><text>Experiments concerning the cleavage stimulus in sand dollar eggs</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2015</infon><infon key="lpage">2025</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Robinson;given-names:DN</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Cant;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cooley;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7925006</infon><infon key="source">Development (Camb)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">120</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>54328</offset><text>Morphogenesis of Drosophilaovarian ring canals</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1336</infon><infon key="lpage">1349</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Shirayama;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zachariae;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ciosk;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Nasmyth;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9482731</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>54375</offset><text>The polo-like kinase Cdc5p and the WD-repeat portein Cdc20p/fizzy are regulators and substrates of the anaphase promoting complex in Saccharomyces cerevisiae.  </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2955</infon><infon key="lpage">2962</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Shu;given-names:H-B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Li;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Palacios;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Li;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Joshi;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8537435</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">108</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>54536</offset><text>A transient association of gamma-tubulin at the mid-body is required for the completion of cytokinesis during the mammalian cell division</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">84</infon><infon key="lpage">94</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sohrmann;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Schmidt;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hagan;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Simanis;given-names:V</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9420333</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>54674</offset><text>Asymmetric segregation on spindle poles of the Schizosaccharomyces pombe septum inducing protein kinase Cdc7p</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Spradling, A. 1993. Developmental genetics of oogenesis. In The Development  of Drosophila melanogaster. Vol. I. M. Bate and A. Martinez-Arias, editors.  Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, NY. 1-70.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>54784</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">25</infon><infon key="lpage">38</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sunkel;given-names:CE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3417791</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">89</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><offset>54785</offset><text>Polo, a mitotic mutant of Drosophiladisplaying abnormal spindle poles</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4873</infon><infon key="lpage">4883</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Tavares;given-names:AAM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sunkel;given-names:CE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8890161</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol  Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>54855</offset><text>The conserved mitotic  kinase Polo is regulated by phosphorylation and has preferred microtubule-associated substrates in Drosophilaembryo extracts</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">981</infon><infon key="lpage">989</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wheatley;given-names:SP</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wang;given-names:Y-L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8922381</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">135</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>55003</offset><text>Midzone microtubule bundles are continuously required for cytokinesis in cultured epithelial cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1097</infon><infon key="lpage">1111</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:White-Cooper;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Carmena;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gonzalez;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8913753</infon><infon key="source">Genetics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">144</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>55102</offset><text>Mutations in new cell cycle genes that fail to complement a multiply mutant third chromosome of Drosophila</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">467</infon><infon key="lpage">480</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Whitfield;given-names:WGF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Millar;given-names:SE</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Saumweber;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Frasch;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Glover;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3143740</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">89</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><offset>55209</offset><text>Cloning of a gene encoding an antigen associated with the centrosome  in Drosophila. </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Wianny, F., A. Tavares, M.J. Evans, D.M. Glover, and M. Zernicka-Goetz.  1998. Mouse polo-like kinase 1 associates with the acentriolar spindle poles,  meiotic chromosomes and spindle midzone during oocyte maturation. Chromosoma (Basel). In press.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>55295</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">709</infon><infon key="lpage">723</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Williams;given-names:BC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Riedy;given-names:MF</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Williams;given-names:EV</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gatti;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Goldberg;given-names:ML</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7730406</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">129</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>55296</offset><text>The Drosophilakinesin-like protein KLP3A is a midbody component required for central spindle assembly and initiation of cytokinesis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">207</infon><infon key="lpage">221</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wilson;given-names:PG</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zheng;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Oakley;given-names:CE</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Oakley;given-names:BR</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Borisy;given-names:CG</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Fuller;given-names:MT</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9133431</infon><infon key="source">Dev Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">184</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>55428</offset><text>Differential expression of two gamma-tubulin isoforms during  gametogenesis and development in Drosophila. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>55536</offset><text>Our work was supported by grants from the Cancer Research Campaign, BBSRC, and the European Union.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>55635</offset><text>R. Adams's present address is Institute of Cellular and Molecular Biology,  King's Buildings, University of Edinburgh, Mayfield Road, Edinburgh,  Scotland.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>55791</offset><text>Address all correspondence to D.M. Glover, CRC Cell Cycle Group,  Cancer Research Campaign Laboratories, Department of Anatomy and  Physiology, Medical Sciences Institute, University of Dundee, Dundee  DD1 4HN, Scotland. Tel.: (44) 1382-344793. Fax: (44) 1382-344213. E-mail:  </text></passage></document></collection>
